Chapter 81: Taboo Tradeoffs, Pt 3

Author's Note: this is a spinoff fanfiction from Less Wrong's Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality (s/5782108/1). The story spins off midway chapter 81, although the following chapters will still use plot twists from the original, before branching off in a completely different direction after ten chapters or so. (Needless to say, there will be spoilers, so you should really have read the original until at least chapter 96 – although of course, if you got here, I can't imagine why you wouldn't already have done that anyway.)

For completeness, the first part of this chapter is copied from the corresponding chapter in HPMoR. If you don't want to reread it and just skip straight to the new parts, search for "But when" in the text. If you do want to reread it, and want more context of this chapter, reread the start of this story arc at (s/5782108/78), s/5782108/79 and s/5782108/80 . Further author warnings (to avoid common erroneous expectations) are given at the bottom of the page.

In rising half-circles of dark stone, a great sea of upraised hands.

The Lords and Ladies of the Wizengamot, in plum-colored robes marked with a silver 'W', stared down in stern rebuke at a young girl trembling in chains. If they had, in any particular ethical system, damned themselves, they clearly thought quite highly of themselves for having done so.

Harry's breath was trembling in his chest. His dark side had come up with a plan – and then rotated itself back out again because speaking too icily would not be to Hermione's advantage; a fact which the only-half-cold Harry had somehow not realized...

"The vote carries, in favor," intoned the secretary, when all the tallying was done, and the upraised hands fell back down. "The Wizengamot recognizes the blood debt owed by Hermione Granger to House Malfoy for the attempted murder of its scion and ending of its line."

Lucius Malfoy was smiling in grim satisfaction. "And now," said the white-maned wizard, "I say that her debt shall be paid –"

Harry clenched his fists beneath the bench and shouted, "By the debt owed from House Malfoy to House Potter!"

"Silence!" snapped the woman in too much pink makeup sitting next to Minister Fudge. "You've disrupted these proceedings quite enough already! Aurors, escort him out!"

"Wait," said Augusta Longbottom from the top tier of seats. "What debt is this?"

Lucius's hands whitened on his cane. "House Malfoy owes no debt to you!"

It wasn't the world's most solid hope, it was based on one newspaper article from a woman who'd been False-Memory-Charmed, but Rita Skeeter had seemed to find it plausible, that Mr. Weasley had allegedly owed James Potter a debt because...

"I'm surprised you've forgotten," Harry said evenly. "Surely it was a cruel and painful period of your life, laboring under the Imperius curse of He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named, until you were freed of it by the efforts of House Potter. By my mother, Lily Potter, who died for it, and by my father, James Potter, who died for it, and by me, of course."

There was a brief silence within the Most Ancient Hall.

"Why, what an excellent point, Mr. Potter," said the old witch who'd been identified as Madam Bones. "I, too, am quite surprised that Lord Malfoy would forget such a significant event. It must have been such a happy day for him."

"Yes," said Augusta Longbottom. "He must have been so grateful."

Madam Bones nodded. "House Malfoy could not possibly deny that debt – unless, perhaps, Lord Malfoy is to tell us that he has misremembered something? I should take quite a professional interest in that. We are always trying to improve our picture of those dark days."

Lucius Malfoy's hands gripped the silver snake-handle of his cane like he was about to strike with it, unleash whatever power it kept –

Then the Lord Malfoy seemed to relax, and a chill smile came over his face. "Of course," he said easily. "I do confess I had not understood, but the child is quite correct. However, I do not quite think the two debts cancel – House Potter was only trying to save itself, after all –"

"Not so," Dumbledore said from above.

"– and therefore," intoned Lucius Malfoy, "I demand monetary compensation as well, for the redemption of the blood debt owed my son. That, too, is the law."

Harry felt a strange inward flinch. That had also been in the newspaper article, Mr. Weasley had demanded an additional ten thousand Galleons –

"How much?" said the Boy-Who-Lived.

Lucius was still wearing the cold smile. "One hundred thousand Galleons. If you have not that much in your vault, I suppose I must accept a promissory note for the remainder."

A roar of protest went up from Dumbledore's side of the room, even some of the plum-colored robes in the middle looked shocked.

"Shall we put it to the vote of the Wizengamot?" said Lucius Malfoy. "I think few of us would like to see the little murderess go free. By a show of hands, that additional compensation of one hundred thousand Galleons would be required to cancel the debt!"

The clerk began tallying, but that vote was also clear.

Harry stood there, breathing deeply.

You'd better not even have to think about this, Harry's inner Gryffindor said threateningly.

It's a major purchase, observed Ravenclaw. We ought to spend a lot of time thinking about it.

It shouldn't have been hard. It shouldn't have. Two million pounds was only money, and money was only worth what it could buy...

It was strange how much psychological attachment you could have to 'only money', or how painful it could be to imagine losing a bank vault full of gold that you hadn't even imagined existed just one year earlier.

Kimball Kinnison wouldn't hesitate, said Gryffindor. Seriously. Like, snap decision. What sort of hero are you? I already hate you just for having to think about it for longer than 50 milliseconds.

This is real life, said Ravenclaw. Losing all your money is a lot more painful for real people in real life than in heroic books.

What? demanded Gryffindor. Whose side are you on?

I wasn't advocating for a particular answer, said Ravenclaw, I was just saying it because it was true.

Could a hundred thousand Galleons be used to save more than one life if spent some other way? said Slytherin. We have research to do, battles to fight, the difference between being 40,000 Galleons rich and being 60,000 Galleons in debt is not trivial –

So we'll just use one of our ways to make money fast and earn it all back, said Hufflepuff.

It's not certain those will work, said Slytherin, and a lot of them require starting cash –

Personally, said Gryffindor, I vote that we save Hermione and then gang up and kill our inner Slytherin.

The clerk's voice said that the tally had been recorded and the vote had passed...

Harry's lips opened.

"I accept your offer," said Harry's lips, without any hesitation, without any decision having been made; just as if the internal debate had been pretense and illusion, the true controller of the voice having been no part of it.

Lucius Malfoy's mask of calm shattered, his eyes widened, he stared at Harry in sheer blank astonishment. His mouth had opened slightly, though he wasn't speaking, and if he was making any peculiar noises it couldn't be heard over the roar of simultaneous gasps from the Wizengamot –

A tap of stone silenced the crowd.

"No," said the voice of Dumbledore.

Harry's head jerked around to stare at the ancient wizard.

Dumbledore's lined face was pale, the silver beard was visibly trembling, he looked like he was in the final throes of a terminal illness. "I'm – sorry, Harry – but this choice is not yours – for I am still the guardian of your vault."

"What?" said Harry, too shocked to compose his reply.

"I cannot let you go into debt to Lucius Malfoy, Harry! I cannot! You do not know – you do not realize –"

DIE.

Harry didn't even know which part of himself had spoken, it might have been a unanimous vote, the pure rage and fury pouring through him. For an instant he thought that the sheer force of the anger might take magical wing and fly out to strike the Headmaster, send him tumbling back dead from the podium –

But when that mental voice had spoken, the old wizard was still standing there, gazing at Harry, long dark wand in his right hand, short black rod in his left.

And Harry felt his blood cool rapidly to freezing point. He stared at Dumbledore in unmitigated hatred, then glanced around and saw all the plum-colored robes, the people who would send a young girl to be mentally destroyed by Dementors, or who at least were too cowardly to speak up in her defense. All his restraint fell away.

There was also the other solution his dark side had devised.

"Then I will cancel the Patronus Charms, and prevent any more Patronuses from being cast. And then my Dementor is going to Kiss everyone here who voted to send a twelve-your-old girl to Azkaban." He was still looking at Dumbledore, but he spoke to the room at large.

Some members of the Wizengamot gasped in surprise, or in horror.

Then a greater number started laughing.

And a terrified voice cried out from below. "No! Harry, don't!"

The coldness shattered as his gaze was torn away from Dumbledore and down to Hermione. She was sitting upright in her chair, still bound by the chains, her school robes around her neck soaked through with tears. And she was looking at him in absolute horror.

"You can't kill them! You're better than that, Harry!"

"Hermione, they voted to send you to Azkaban. They deliberately chose to send a child to be tortured to death." His voice broke. "I cannot let them."

An uneasy silence had fallen over the hall, as the people in their plum-colored robes listened to the exchange. There were sounds of disbelief here and there, but no one interrupted, as the Chief Warlock held up a hand in restraint. Hermione took a few breaths before she found the strength to speak.

"Yes, you can, Harry. Because you promised me that you wouldn't help me if I told you not to."

His mind stumbled, unable to form a coherent response, to come up with a new plan. Tears were streaming down Harry's face.

"They're trying to send you to Azkaban, Hermione!"

"I know." She screwed up her eyes, swallowed, and took another deep breath. "But maybe I deserve that."

"No, you don't! Hermione, don't you believe that you deserve this, any of this! You didn't do it! Someone has False-Memory-Charmed you, or maybe cast some dark spell on you, I don't know. But I do know you!"

Hermione's eyes widened, and for a moment she looked... not happy, but hopeful. But then her face set in a determined look.

"Even if that is so, you should not harm people for my sake. You shouldn't harm people at all! There are parents here, Harry!"

"They're evil, Hermione! Would you really go to Azkaban to save them? Even knowing that you're completely innocent?"

She looked away from him, to the ground, as though this answer was taking all her strength to give. But she nodded, and almost whispered: "Yes. I would."

Harry didn't know what to say anymore, or what to do. His brain had run into a dead end. He had no solutions, and he couldn't go dark anymore, not now.

It was Dumbledore who broke the deadly silence. The Chief Warlock raised himself up to his full height and spoke in sad, but firm tones.

"And now you have all seen what you have done today. This is the child that you have condemned to be entombed in Azkaban."

"A worthy theater," Lucius Malfoy drawled from the other side of most ancient hall. "Undoubtedly composed to make the girl look better. But I for one am not convinced by some mad threat."

"Yes, obviously the boy was bluffing." Dumbledore waved a hand irritably so as to dismiss any possibility of the alternative as nonsensical. "He is a first-year child, who is merely trying to save a friend's life by using the mysterious reputation his past has given him. He is too young to understand the... delicacies of politics. Naturally, he was not truly able to carry out his threat."

The old wizard paused briefly, and gestured at where Hermione was sitting.

"But she did not know that. You have all heard her. She would willingly go to Azkaban to save you, the people who have sentenced her there."

"She was just lying to impress us." The toad-like pink-makeup woman, whose name Harry could no longer remember, was learning forward with a sickening smile. "I agree with Lord Malfoy. It was an admirable show."

"She's still under the effect of Veritaserum, Madam Umbridge," Madam Bones replied hoarsely. "She was given three drops, it takes an hour to fully wear off. She might not be compelled to say more than she wants to anymore, but she cannot yet lie."

Now many people looked sick. Now, when the vote had been and passed, they were finally starting to think.

"The blood debt stands," Lucius Malfoy said, his voice no longer sounding amused. "Emotional shows aside, she is still a murderess, and we have already voted on the matter. So let her debt be paid. Take her to Azkaban, where she will never threaten anyone again."

"Very well," Dumbledore spoke gravely. He was looking Hermione in the eyes as he tapped the rod. "I now, in accordance with the last decision of the survivors of the eighty-eighth Wizengamot, adjourn this session." Then, he bowed his head.

One of the Aurors moved forward and pressed a short rod of dark metal to the metal chair, muttering an inaudible word of dismissal. The chains slithered back as smoothly as they had come forth, but Hermione didn't move. She was trembling. The Auror laid a hand on her shoulder and pulled her onto her feet.

Hermione didn't scream, didn't beg, she didn't have to be dragged out. She just gave Harry one last, tearful look, and then turned and allowed herself to be led away by the Aurors. Harry wanted to say something, wanted to run after her, apologize, hug her, do something, but it was all too late, he didn't know what he could do anymore.

And then she was gone.

Around the room, the Lords and Ladies of the Wizengamot were rising. Some were looking slightly uncomfortable, others were hurrying out to lunch or happily talking to each other as though nothing out of the ordinary had happened. To Harry's right, Professor McGonagall was weeping. Dumbledore descended to the bottom of the dark stone stairs, and stepped up toward the spectator arc. His blue eyes were locked on Harry, as hard as sapphires. Only when he reached Professor McGonagall did his expression soften.

"Come, Minerva, let us go home. Today was a very sad day indeed." He took her arm gently in his. "And Mr. Potter, hold my sleeve. We are not done yet."

Harry obeyed, Dumbledore grabbed Fawkes by the tail, and then the fire engulfed them.

Author's Note to avoid erroneous expectations: Several people have expressed some confusion at the title of this spinoff fanfiction. To clarify:

Following The Phoenix simply refers to doing the brave/right/foolish thing.

It does not refer to any actual phoenix. I do not confirm or deny that phoenixes play a role in this work.

It is also important to note that this spinoff was written and posted before the final arc of HPMoR (between the publication of chapters 98 and 103, to be exact). Consequently, not only does it continue in a different way, but the revelations in later chapters also do not apply. This means, among other things:

* the events in Godric Hollow did not happen that way

* the secret identities and motivations of various characters are not all the same

* horcruxes don't work that way

* the philosopher's stone doesn't work that way

And I will go right out and reveal now that Harry's Pet Rock died simply because he was such an irresponsible guardian.

Chapter 82: Taboo Tradeoffs, Final

Author's Note: loyal HPMoR readers may recognize some of the lines in this chapter. This is because, despite the rather significant change in chapter 81, parts of the story are still going into roughly the same direction as in the original – both in order to resolve open plot lines, to explain the choices in the last chapter, and simply because these conversations made sense here!

Phoenix travel was a sensation entirely unlike Apparition or portkeys. You caught on fire – you definitely felt yourself catching on fire, even though there was no pain – and instead of burning to ashes, the fire burned all the way through you and you became fire, and then you went out in one place and blazed up in another. It didn't sicken the stomach like portkeys or Apparition, but it was a rather unnerving experience nonetheless.

Harry caught fire and went out and blazed up somewhere else; and just like that, he and the two Professors and the bird were occupying another place. A very well-organized bedroom, with a shelf full of books above it. A painting of a teenage girl was hanging opposite the bed, and a wardrobe stood in a corner. Professor McGonagall stumbled toward the bed, and lay down.

The old wizard squeezed her shoulder comfortingly, and then turned and reached one of his arms around Harry; and the Boy-Who-Lived and his Wizard vanished in another burst of flame.

When Harry had fully lit up again he was standing in the Headmaster's office, amid the noises of a dozen dozen inexplicable gidgets.

The old wizard sat down heavily inside his chair and fixed his piercing blue eyes on Harry.

"I wonder whether there will come a day when I regret not killing you when you were in my power, Mr. Potter."

That blow hit home very hard. Harry knew that the Headmaster was right. He had given in to the darkness today. Given in so badly that a good person would be justified in killing him to avoid whatever he might come to do next. He had genuinely been about to kill two thirds of the Wizengamot. The idea seemed nothing but horrendous to him now, and yet he had been ready to do it only fifteen minutes ago.

"I hope I have managed to convince most of the Wizengamot that you were bluffing," Dumbledore continued. "But I have never yet known you to lie. What is more, I know well that you are no fool, and you must have been aware that a bluff like that would not have impressed the members of the Wizengamot. Tell me. How would you have achieved it?"

The Dementors are Death, and the Patronus Charm works by thinking about happy thoughts instead of Death.

If Harry's theory was correct, that one sentence would be all it took to pop the Aurors' Patronus Charms like a soap bubble, and ensure that nobody within reach of his voice could cast another one. And since he had announced that the Dementor would Kiss certain people, either their expectations, or Harry's threat of its destruction, would make the Dementor obey. Those who had sought to compromise with the darkness would be consumed by it.

"I cannot tell you."

The Headmaster nodded, as though he had expected this answer.

"But you would have. As young as you are, and for all your ideals, you were prepared to destroy the very souls of seventy-three people, including two parents of your friends. Will you become a Dark Lord, Harry? Without Hermione standing in your path when you lose sight of the light, what will your first great evil be?"

Harry didn't answer. Without Hermione. For the first time, the immensity of his loss hit him. It had simply been unthinkable before, a terrible prospect that must be avoided at all costs, but he hadn't gone so far as to mentally prepare himself for the possibility of it actually happening. Yet now, it was a reality. She would never sit by him, or study with him, or walk next to him, or tell him to be nicer... she would be in a small, dark cell, screaming.

No, I didn't mean it, please don't die!

It all came back to him, but it was worse, so much worse, to think of Hermione there. He just couldn't imagine it, it hurt too much to even think of it in abstract terms.

"And why won't she be with me?" he yelled. "Because you wouldn't let me save her!"

"We can discuss that point later." Dumbledore's voice brooked no refusal. "Now, we will speak of your choices."

Harry wanted to protest, but Dumbledore's gaze was cold and his demeanor more authoritative than ever before. Guilt battled briefly with anger, but at last he tore his eyes away.

"I know it was wrong." Harry looked down at the desk. "Hermione made that clear to me. I shouldn't have done it, shouldn't even have considered it for more than a few seconds. I will do better."

"It was your dark side, wasn't it?"

Harry looked up in surprise. The Headmaster had never explicitly referred to it before, even when he had alluded to it.

"Oh yes, I know of your dark side. I have a variety of theories, even. However, I had been hoping that you could control it."

"I can! But today... I needed to call on it. My dark side came up with the debt plan, too. But then –"

"You lost control." Dumbledore sighed. "I understand. This must have been very trying for you. However, if one such failure of self-control creates this kind of response from you, I shudder to think of the faith of the world." He stood up, opened one of his wardrobes, and took out a stone basin. "There is something I want you to see."

The old wizard placed his wand at his temple, closed his eyes for a few moments, and then withdrew it. A thin silvery thread was attached to the wand, and he dropped it in the basin. With a swirling movement, the liquid turned into a small whirlpool inside the basin.

"This memory is from today. I used Legilimency to speak to Hermione Granger at the end of her trial. Put your head into the Pensieve."

Nervously, Harry obeyed, sticking his nose in. Immediately, there was a swirling sensation, and then suddenly he was back into the hated Hall of the Wizengamot. Not from the spectators' seat, but rather looking out from the podium in the highest of the half-circles. He was looking straight at Hermione, who was trying to look strong, but quite failing not to screw up her face into knots of misery.

"I am sorry, Hermione." Dumbledore's internal voice, as he remembered it, sounded strange to Harry.

"Please help Harry." This was Hermione's voice, somehow echoing inside his mind. "If he turns evil, that's worse than anything else."

"He does not listen to me like he does to you."

"Then ask him for me to promise never to give in to his dark side. As a last favor to me, ask him to promise to try never to do what I would tell him not to."

In the distance, Malfoy was talking, but Harry didn't pay attention to it.

"I will do so," answered Dumbledore's internal voice. "Please forgive me for what happens next."

"I am scared..." Hermione's voice trembled, but she didn't continue.

The memory ended with a shock and Harry ripped his head out of the glowing liquid of the Pensieve, gasping as though he'd been deprived of air. He was crying again, he realized.

"I promise," he said, his voice choking as he pushed back the tears that came despite all his best efforts. "I'm sorry. I shouldn't have done it and I won't ever be like that again, and I won't give in to my dark side, I promise I'll always consider what Hermione would want me to do." He wiped the sleeve of his robe over his face. "But I am going to get her out. I will find a way that she wouldn't disapprove of."

Dumbledore looked at him long and hard.

"If you can prove her innocence, she might yet be saved. However, as you well know, she was extremely sensitive when exposed to the Dementor in January." He suddenly looked very old. "Foolish though it was, there is one good consequence that may come of your interference at today's trial: it will not be a happy memory to her. If she can steer her thoughts to dwell on this rather than the memories of her supposed misdeeds, at least it may allow her to remember who she is. Even so, I do not expect that she will be able to retain her sanity for more than a few days. A few weeks, and she will be beyond recovery."

Harry bit his lip. A few days to get her out. If he could break out Bellatrix Black, then surely someone as nonthreatening as Hermione Granger shouldn't be a problem. The main problem was that there was no way he could do it without adult help; he didn't have a portkey, or the sheer magical power to break a hole into the walls of Azkaban or to fool the wards. Maybe Professor Quirrell could help him, but would he be willing? He didn't care much for Hermione, and would not want Harry to risk his future for her. Even if he would help, the Professor had not returned from custody, and every moment Hermione spent in that place that still haunted his nightmares was too much.

Could Dumbledore help him? But he, too, did not exactly have Hermione's best interests at heart, did he?

"Why did you stop me from saving her?"

The Headmaster looked weary.

"Because she is not worth a hundred thousand Galleons, Harry. Few people are."

"You actually put a value on her life. And you put it well below a hundred thousand Galleons." Harry's voice sounded hollow in his ears.

"And what price do you put on her life then? A million Galleons?"

"Are you familiar with the economic concept of 'replacement value'?" The words were spilling from Harry's lips almost faster than he could consider them. "Hermione's replacement value is infinite! There's nowhere I can go to buy another one!"

Somewhere inside him, his Slytherin side was glaring contemptuously. You do realize that you're talking mathematical nonsense here, don't you?

"Is Minerva's life also of infinite worth?" the old wizard said harshly. "Would you sacrifice Minerva to save Hermione?"

"Yes and yes," Harry snapped. "Professor McGonagall would be happy to make that sacrifice herself."

"Then Minerva's value is not infinite," said the old wizard, "for all that she is loved. There can only be one king upon the chessboard, Harry Potter, only one piece that you will sacrifice any other piece to save. And Hermione Granger is not that piece."

"Life is not a game of chess! This is a person you've sacrificed!"

Professor Dumbledore rested his face in his hands for a moment, but when he looked back at Harry, his gaze was controlled.

"I am well aware of that. But so is every other friend or ally you will have to save. For make no mistake, Harry, this will not be the last time such a choice is required of you."

Hermione, trembling in her chains. Looking at him with that last, tearful look of farewell. And Dumbledore wanted him to go through that again, choose for it to happen when alternatives were available. It was almost unthinkable. Harry screwed up his eyes as his wonderful imagination filled in the dots. This time it had been Hermione. Would Draco be next? Neville? Mother or father?

"People cannot live like that," he whispered.

"Not everyone can," the old wizard said softly. "I have had to learn it the hard way. I would spare you that lesson, Harry. If you were free to live a normal life, I might have let you do it. It would have been a foolish choice, which you would have paid for for the rest of your life, but if you were free, I might have let you do that for your friend, and you might not have come to regret it. But you are not free. You have a war to fight during your life, and when you are leader of that war, your allies will expect you to make more sensible decisions."

Tears were prickling behind Harry's eyes again.

"And should I kill for money too? Or kill one innocent to save two others?"

The old wizard did not answer. And Harry remembered.

"That's why you did it, isn't it? That's why you burned Narcissa Malfoy alive in her own bedroom."

Albus Dumbledore's gaze was cold as he answered. "There is no way to answer that question without immeasurable harm, whether yes or no. I will say this, though: the Death Eaters believe I killed her, and they believe that for every innocent on our side they took, an innocent of theirs would die in the same way. That belief is what has kept safe the families of all those who served the Order of the Phoenix."

"And is it true?" Harry said. There was a buzzing sensation filling him, his body growing more distant. "What Draco said, that Narcissa Malfoy never got her hands dirty, that she was only Lucius's wife? She was an enabler, I get that, but I can't back that deserving being burned alive."

"Nothing less would have convinced them that I was done with hesitation." The old wizard's voice brooked no question and no refusal. "Always I was too reluctant to do as I must, always it was others who paid the cost of my mercy. So my friend Alastor told me from the beginning, but I did not listen to him. You, I expect, shall prove better at such decisions than I."

Harry was shaking. Inside him, Slytherin was nodding along, but his other parts were recoiling in horror. Partly, he knew that the Headmaster was right. There were limits to the value of a human life. And Harry probably would be better than Dumbledore at this sort of thing. He knew the math, after all.

But it was understood, somehow it was understood, that utilitarian ethicists didn't actually rob banks so they could give the money to the poor. The end result of throwing away all ethical constraint wouldn't actually be sunshine and roses and happiness for all. Somehow Harry had understood that, even before anyone else had warned him. Before he'd read about Vladimir Lenin or the history of the French Revolution, he'd known. It might have been his earliest science fiction books warning him about people with good intentions, or maybe Harry had just seen the logic for himself. Somehow he'd known from the very beginning, that if he stepped outside his ethics whenever there was a reason, the end result wouldn't be good.

Why am I still here? he wondered. Hermione was in Azkaban; imprisoned, tormented, but not yet lost. He had to go and think for an hour or so, and come up with a plan to save her.

Would Dumbledore help him? The old wizard cared for Hermione, obviously. He probably valued her more than the 200 Galleons standard bribe for being caught in Azkaban. But most of all, he cared about Harry's safety. No, he cared for the hero's safety. He would not allow Harry to risk his reputation for her. If he knew what Harry was planning, he could simply stop him from doing so until it was too late to recover Hermione. It might only take a few days, after all, or a few weeks at most, before prolonged Dementor exposure would break her mind beyond repair.

He looked up in the Headmaster's eyes.

"Maybe I will be, maybe I won't. But for now, I am not prepared to walk away and leave my friends to die when they can be saved. And I am not prepared to throw away all my ethics for some greater good either."

It was like the old wizard had been struck, struck by a chisel that shattered him straight down the middle.

"What have I said?" the old wizard whispered. "What have I said to you?"

"Goodbye, Headmaster." And with those words, he marched out the open door, and onto the endlessly turning spiral.

Chapter 83: Following the Phoenix, Pt 1

The three of them were on their 5,609th game of Dragon Poker. (They had taken a break and tried some other games a few weeks back, but they had quickly returned to Dragon Poker, as centuries of Aurors had before them. It was simply the only card game interesting enough to play for this long.)

Li's mind was not on the game.

They had all read the Daily Prophet this morning, of course. Bahry had snorted derisively, saying that even the Wizengamot wouldn't do something that stupid. There was an age limit for a reason, and breaking it would sink Britain's international esteem to an all-time low. And that would have consequences. The Lords and Ladies of the Wizengamot might not care much about the suffering of lower beings than themselves, but they did care about their profit margins being decreased. And so, they had continued their daily routine, none of them raising the subject again as though by an unspoken agreement. But, Li noticed, Gerard McCusker was not playing much better than he was. And while Bahry was cashing in win after win – the old Auror was hard to faze – even he still glanced at the clock every once in a while.

Three booms sounded in the room. The signal of an incoming prisoner.

Li exchanged a glance with the others and jabbed his wand at the screens showing the surroundings of the prison, magnifying one of them. There, on the north side, they could see the waters, where a boat with the prisoner and three guarding Aurors was approaching. The boat was still too distant to make out any faces, but even so, the prisoner definitely looked very small.

"They can't be serious," McCusker muttered, as Li felt a lump in his throat. Bahry just swore.

The boat came nearer, and the Aurors inside it dragged their prisoner onto the little platform on the island, which lifted up into the air, following its standard path to the roof entrance. Dementors rose up as their new prey was carried over the pit, held at bay by the Aurors' Dementors but coming close enough to hungrily investigate the prisoner all the same.

Three knocks. McCusker opened the door, and the Aurors came in. With them...

Li's heart wrenched in sympathy as he looked at the little girl. Was this the mad first-year child who had come up with a gruesome plan to murder a schoolmate? She looked so... normal. And so scared. She was staring around with big brown eyes, huddling as close to the Patronuses as the ropes binding her would let her.

Auror Gawain Robards, the eldest and therefore de facto leader of the delivering trio, waved his wand and the girl was pushed into a corner. Li silently ordered his badger to stick to that part of the room.

Bahry cast a spell of silence to avoid the prisoner overhearing anything. "Auror Robards, please report." From the break-room, the off-duty Aurors looked in. Bahry irritably waved them over. "We would like to know what in the name of Merlin is going on here."

"The Wizengamot have acknowledged that the girl owes a blood debt to the house of Malfoy," Robards spoke calmly, "and have consequently sentenced her to ten years in Azkaban. We have come to deliver her."

"And did the Wizengamot" – Bahry spat the word as though it was a curse – "bother to name a level?"

"They argued to have her judged as an adult, but did not explicitly name a level. Director Bones suggests not to be excessive."

Li glanced at the girl. What would it matter? She would never last ten years; she wouldn't even last ten months. Putting her further from the Dementors would only prolong her suffering.

"That's sick," Leela McGonagall, the newest of the off-duty trio, said flatly (she was a distant relation, and everyone called her Leela because it would just feel wrong otherwise). "I don't mind giving criminals what they deserve, but that presumes they're mature enough to know what they're doing. I can't believe the Wizengamot did this."

"You don't know the worst of it," Marc Kleiner, the second of the guarding Aurors, said bitterly. "You should have heard her confession. She was horrified by what she did. And you should have heard Albus Dumbledore. And what she said in the end..." He wiped his sleeve over his face. "Obviously she's mad, and too dangerous to be allowed near other children. But I thought they'd lock her up in a closed ward of St. Mungo's or something. She doesn't deserve this."

"It's not our place to judge that," Gawain Robards said sharply. "The Wizengamot have spoken. We leave her in your custody now." With that, he nodded to the guarding Aurors, and stepped up to the door, followed by the third Auror, a pale young man who seemed to want to get away from this place as soon as possible. Marc, with a last pitying look on the young witch, followed them.

"Screw that," Leela said, when they were gone. "I didn't sign up to feed small children to the Dementors."

"You signed up to feed any criminal to the Dementors you're told to," Bahry bit at her. "She's not some innocent little puppet, no matter how cute she looks."

"Even so," Gerard said. "I agree with Leela. I don't mind thieves and murderers being here, that is what it's for. But this... it just feels wrong."

Bahry ran his hand through his white hairs. "Look. I don't like this any better than you do, but you've got to play the hand you're dealt. The girl has been remanded to our custody, and we'll just have to make the best of it." He turned to Li. "Mike, are you willing to take her to her cell, or shall I do it?"

"No," Auror Li sighed. This was the hardest part of their duties, worse than the feeding or vanishing the contents of the toilet buckets, worse even than cleaning out the corpses of prisoners who had served their time. And it was his turn. Gerard had already filled in for him when he had had to stay at home because his youngest had Glowpox last week. "It's my turn, isn't it?"

Bahry nodded. "Cell block 2 in B spiral is free," he suggested. Li nodded slowly, understanding the hint.

The cells in the highest levels were normally used for short-term prisoners: petty thieves, crooks, sometimes people who couldn't keep up with their debt repayments and needed a sharp reminder of the consequences of laxness. Each block held half a dozen cells, which were simply filled up from left to right, unless a pair of prisoners came in who should be kept separate. Several cells in the other blocks were also free at the moment, so there really was no reason for the girl to get a block of her own.

No reason at all, unless they didn't want the other prisoners to see what they were doing with her.

They could add some chocolate to her meals, perhaps even masking the flavor so she herself wouldn't know in case she got visitors. Or they could be lax when checking any visitors she got for chocolate supplies. They could even Stun her occasionally. Unconsciousness wouldn't last near Dementors; eventually it would turn into a restless sleep and then you woke up drained and hurt. However, for a few hours, it could at least provide a relief from suffering. And maybe in a while, if Lord Malfoy didn't cave in to international pressure to release her, they could "forget" to feed her, and ease her into a merciful death. It wasn't like she was going to live through her sentence anyway.

He sighed and stepped toward the child.

"Can you walk? Or should I carry you?"

"W-walk," she squeaked. Li sent his Patronus ahead to guide the way, and slowly, reluctantly, she stepped forward. He followed behind, keeping his wand pointed at her.

She stumbled several times, walking awkwardly in the ropes that bound her, and when they were just in the corridor, she fell over. He caught her with a silent Wingardium Leviosa.

"Here." With a flick of his wand, the ropes disappeared. This wasn't part of the protocol, but the prisoner was a child, unarmed, and obviously rather tired to boot. Plus, even in the extremely unlikely event that she managed to overpower him somehow, she'd still be in Azkaban, and the Dementors knew her as their prey. She gave him a brief, grateful look.

"Your name is Hermione, isn't it?" he asked. She nodded silently.

"I'm Li."

What was he doing? It was the first rule any Auror new to Azkaban was taught: do not fraternize with the prisoners. If you started thinking of them as people, the whole thing became a lot worse.

Well. It was a bit late for that anyway.

They descended the stairs (there were no cells directly by the Auror quarters; it would be too unpleasant to hear the prisoners all the time). Nearby, behind the stone walls, someone was sobbing. It was hard to make out the words here, and Li didn't try; he was all too used to it. But the girl, Hermione, stopped in her tracks, shaking.

Li sighed silently, and gave her a gentle push with his magic. "Come."

She proceeded, then, down into the corridor, where the voice became clearer: "– no, no, no! Please, I can't!" Hermione looked like she desperately wanted to run away, and Li held his wand firmly in case it would be necessary to stop her. But no, she kept walking. And Li followed.

The sobbing sounds stopped as the child, the Auror, and most importantly the Patronus entered the corridor and slowly moved toward the large metal door, and then past it. And then it started again, but more distantly. It was probably the prisoner in the leftmost cell, Li thought. The crook who had been brought in last week.

The second block of cells would be mercifully empty. They came to the door, and halted. Li unlocked it with a wave of his wand, and led Hermione to the rightmost cell, far enough from the other cell block to not hear any screams other than her own. She sat down on the stone bench that was the only piece of furniture in the cell.

And now it was time for Li to go back to the Auror quarters, and leave Hermione to the Dementors.

... He couldn't do it.

Many times before, he had wondered whether he should stop working in Azkaban. He hated this place, and more than anything he hated taking human beings to their cell – criminals, but still – and then watching them dwindle, day by day, ignoring their begging as he fed them and cleaned their cells, until he could finally release the huddling piles of misery they were reduced to at the end of their sentence. If they were even still alive. He didn't know how many made a full recovery afterwards – probably a fair few of the short-term prisoners did – but he could guess the number was low. The recidivism rate was very close to zero, at least.

Why am I still here?

He had a family to maintain. His squib wife, Lixue, had little chance of finding work in the wizarding world. Su and Kao were young, and coping with all their childhood diseases was expensive. Next year ,Su would be old enough to go to school, and need books, uniforms and a wand. Add to that Lixue's parents, who were living in, too old and uncomfortable with British culture to find work, but who helped to raise the children with traditional values... There was no way he could give them all the standard of living they deserved, if he earned only the standard Auror salary.

And did he even want to be an Auror anymore? If he resigned from Azkaban because he didn't want to deal with what happened to the prisoners, could he justify bringing people in instead?

Maybe he could find other work... a competent ex-Auror could probably get a position as a guard to a wealthy House. Or perhaps Hogwarts would need a dueling instructor next year. (He was not, of course, mad enough to consider applying as Defense Professor when the position opened up again.) The children were getting older, too; maybe Lixue, who had spent years educating their daughter and son, could find a job in the Muggle world, and leave Kao's further education to her parents... It wouldn't earn Galleons, but it would still put bread on the table.

But Lixue could never find a job as a teacher, even if she was smart and patient and knew all the techniques to get children to pay attention, because she didn't have qualifications, Muggles always wanted to see certificates. Without so much as a high school diploma, she could at best work in a shop or something like that, and could he ask that of her? Her parents would never forgive him for taking the selfish choice, putting so much on them and their daughter, and reducing the family to relative poverty. They would need to buy Su's books and robes second-hand, or worse, dishonor themselves by applying for the Hogwarts book fund. And what was to say he could even find other work? Quiting now, without having any other options lined up, would be the height of irresponsibility. And it wouldn't even help this child, Hermione, in the slightest.

He turned away then, locking the grate to the cell, and locking the metal door to the cell block behind him. He fled back to the command room as a deep feeling of sadness settled in his heart.

Minerva was lying on her bed, silent tears streaming down her face.

Hermione.

The clever, eager girl, who had read through all her parents' books (cookbooks and encyclopedias alike) and all the age-appropriate material in the local library before learning that she was a witch.

The enthusiastic young witch she had taken to Diagon Alley, who had asked so many clever questions while her father smiled indulgently and her mother looked vaguely worried, and who had been almost impossible to drag away from the bookshop.

The bright student who had learned all her books by heart before even setting foot into Hogwarts, was top of all her classes, and still studied almost every hour of every day, already trying second- and third-year spells.

The sweet child who spent all the time that she wasn't studying helping others, friends or just fellow students who hadn't even been nice to her, and always explained to the weaker students where they went wrong in so patient and kind a way.

The general of Sunshine Army, who, she was told, listened to the students in her army, and made them realize their own potential. Minerva had not liked it when she heard that Quirinius had appointed the girl – it was nothing like Hermione to fight and strategize against the other students, let alone having to play on a level with Draco Malfoy and allowing herself to get dragged into Albus's plots – but she had still been proud when she heard how Hermione was perceived, and how her "soldiers" had flourished under her command, taking initiatives and growing in self-respect.

The aspiring heroine, who had rallied her fellow students to take on the bullying problem in Hogwarts, and kept on fighting to help the victims, even when things got out of hand and she found herself the target of insults and abuse, even when it seemed like she and her friends could all come to terrible harm. The brave girl who had stood defiant before Professor Snape (as she had been told afterwards), never crying at her unfair treatment, even when all Professors who should have protected her looked away.

The true hero who had gone through a terrible ordeal, been made to believe horrible things about herself as part of some dark plot, then been forced to live through it all over again in a farce of a trial, who had seen her bright future crushed and then had what little hope she could have had destroyed by the Headmaster as he blocked Harry's clever plan to save her... and who had nevertheless found the strength in herself to speak out against her friend's bluff. The true hero, who had genuinely been prepared to sacrifice herself to save her enemies. And who would by now have been brought to Azkaban, where she would be exposed to the darkest creatures in the world, reliving her worst memories until she went mad and died...

Minerva had canceled all her classes this afternoon, and for the next day too. She had locked the door to her office. She didn't want to see anyone.

What on earth was she going to tell Hermione's parents?

There was a knocking on the door, but she didn't answer. Whether it was student or teacher, she wasn't ready to see them. And she certainly didn't want to see Albus at the moment.

The knocking continued, and a voice outside yelled something. A high voice, as from a young boy. Harry? But he must know that she didn't want to be disturbed, that she needed time to mourn. He would be in the same situation.

The knocking carried on insistently, so she finally stood up, went into her office and opened the door. And there was Harry. He did not look like he had been crying, as she had expected. Instead, he was wearing that strange cold, alert look she had sometimes seen on him.

"Harry? What is it?"

"I need an adult's help to rescue Hermione, and I don't think the Headmaster is going to do it. Will you?"

She blinked, taken aback.

"Harry... It's too late, she's gone." At Hermione's age, and as sensitive as she had proved to be on the day the students had practiced their Patronus Charms, even one day of Dementor exposure might destroy the person she had been. A week would almost certainly drive her to madness. Ten years... It would be easier for the boy to think of his friend as already being dead.

Harry gave her a pitying look.

"She is not gone. She is merely in Azkaban, and I think I can do something about that." He sat down in the chair opposite her desk. "Will you sit? It's a bit of an explanation."

He seemed so confident. Baffled, she sat down, ignoring the gross breach of etiquette of being told to sit in her own office. Harry leaned his elbows on the desk and pierced her with a serious look.

"When I was... suspected... of freeing Bellatrix Black from Azkaban, I did some thinking. There was good reason to suspect me, because I could come up with at least two ways to break someone out of Azkaban."

Her mouth opened and closed in shock. Break someone out of Azkaban? For a very brief moment, a faint twinge of hope stirred in her chest. Then common sense and terror kicked in and squashed it.

"Don't you think about it! The only one who has ever managed to break someone out of Azkaban is You-Know-Who, and even he almost failed!" Albus had said that the breakout had been supposed to be undetected, that something must have gone wrong. "The penalty for trying to escape is the Dementor's Kiss, both for the prisoner and whoever is helping them. That's... it's too dangerous Harry, for both of you." There were not many fates worse than dying in Azkaban, but having your soul destroyed by a Dementor was almost certainly one of them.

"I didn't mean that," Harry said carefully. "But I have some ideas that might also work to just... protect someone. Keep her from being eaten by the Dementors while we work on a way to prove her innocence, or at least gather a hundred thousand Galleons. I think there should be some decent legal ways of getting her out, but making solid plans in that direction will probably take a few days, especially if the Defense Professor doesn't get released soon. So we have to keep her from going insane, and preferably from suffering too much during that time and however long it takes to execute the plans."

She found herself staring at the boy. "What did you have in mind?"

"I'm not sure exactly, I'll need more information to finalize my ideas. But to get the most obvious possibility out of the way... You sent your Patronus to me all the way in Diagon Alley. What would happen if you just sent it to Hermione?"

She shook her head. "Nothing. The ability of a Patronus to protect the people around it relies on its proximity to the caster. I could probably send my Patronus to defend Gryffindor Tower from here, but if it goes all the way to Azkaban, it can do little more than relay messages."

Harry nodded. "I figured that something like that would be the case, or people would have done it already, but it was worth checking. Otherwise... Professor are you an Occlumens?"

She nodded slowly. Albus had insisted that she learn, after she had told him about the prophecy. It would be bad security if anyone could just pick the details out of her mind. It wasn't her kind of magic, and even after years of training, she would never be a perfect Occlumens, but she could make a respectable block.

"The penalty for breaking out is the Kiss. What about breaking in?"

Professor McGonagall considered this. "I am not sure. It... it doesn't usually come up. I think the official punishment is something like a month of jail time, but the Aurors typically let you go."

Harry nodded. "Professor Quirrell said something like that when I talked to him about it too. Would you be willing to take that risk? For Hermione?"

How could he even ask? "If I could, I would swap with Hermione." She sighed. "But how can it help her?"

"I have a number of plans," he responded calmly. "Not all of which I can explain. As for the simplest one, I want her Obliviated, to make her forget the memory of the duel with Draco. If that is her worst memory, her mind will get stuck on a lie. But Professor Dumbledore said that my little... escapade would probably be a bad memory to her. If we can get her to dwell on that instead, it might help her retain some sanity if all other plans fail."

The words hit her like a slap to the face. How could the boy talk about it all so calmly? And yet, what he said did make a horrible kind of sense. She hadn't even thought about it, but of course Hermione, stuck in Azkaban, would, in her mind, repeat the memory of her crime over and over, and over. Removing that memory while leaving her to the Dementors would not fix much. But perhaps it might make her situation a tiny bit better.

"And your other plans?" Her mouth was dry.

"Depends. For a start, I may want to give her a wand. Do you know what the consequences for that will be?"

A wand? "She could never use that, the Dementors drain your magic!"

"Not if she uses it to cast a Patronus Charm."

Her mind tumbled. If that could be done, why hadn't anyone... ah.

"That wouldn't work. She has to sleep, eventually. And after a night near Dementors, no one is able to find a happy enough thought to cast a Patronus. Besides," she added, remembering, "Hermione couldn't cast the spell, and the Dementors give alarm if one is kept up for more than two hours."

Harry just smiled mysteriously.

"Let us assume that that won't be a problem. What will happen to her if she is caught with a wand, but can testify under Veritaserum that she had no intention of escaping? Would she still get the Kiss?"

"Probably not... The only rule prisoners are subject to is not to leave their cell or attack the Aurors." Minerva hesitated. The guards of Azkaban, as Albus had pointed out to her, were all people who could cast the Patronus Charm. They would not be eager to let a small child be Kissed... Besides, they would want to know who gave her the wand, so at least they'd have to interrogate her, and then it would come out that she hadn't been planning escape. "But they would find out who gave it to her."

"What would happen to those people, if they were found out?"

Minerva frowned, considering. There weren't actually any laws against leaving items in prisoners' cells, just laws against breaking in and trying to help prisoners escape. There was simply no point in giving a prisoner anything other than chocolate. And she was pretty sure the law against breaking in named a maximum penalty. Still, leaving a wand in a prisoner's cell was pushing it a little, so they could conceivably be prosecuted for attempted prison break anyway. However, Amelia was sympathetic to Hermione's plight; the woman had made that very clear during the trial, and Minerva had seen the pain in her eyes when the girl was convicted. If the Director of Magical Law Enforcement stuck to the letter of the law, and accepted Hermione's testimony under Veritaserum, then such a crime would not carry more than a few months in Azkaban. Harsh enough, but survivable at least for her, if not for Harry.

"I don't know," she said eventually. "Probably not the Kiss. But that's a gamble."

Harry nodded grimly. "I don't think there's a high chance of being found out if we do this properly, but we have to be prepared for all eventualities. Are you willing to go there with me? Tonight?"

She gasped in surprise. Tonight? Taking Harry Potter to Azkaban on some plot that she only half-knew, but which sounded several degrees more insane than anything even Albus had ever come up with? Well yes, if they wanted to save Hermione they had to act as soon as they could, but was this really even a possibility?

She stared at Harry. He radiated so much confidence... He might be a little foolish sometimes, and a lot foolish at other times, but he had a heart of gold, and she would trust him to the end of the world. He must not be in danger; he was too precious to her, and too important to the rest of the world as well. But maybe, if she went with him, if it all went to hell, she could take the blame, and Harry would come away scot-free.

And if it all went well, if Harry was right, and Hermione could be saved...

"Yes," she answered firmly. She was Head of House Gryffindor, after all.

"Good," said Harry, retrieving a parchment from his pouch. "Then here's a couple of things I'll need to know first..."

Li was slightly sweaty when he arrived back in the command room, where the comforting presence of two Patronuses welcomed him. He had run most of the way, but that hadn't been the tiring part.

No, the much harder thing had been traversing this distance without his Patronus. One minute at the highest level of Azkaban shouldn't have drained him so, but he was very aware of the possible consequences of his sudden decision to leave the badger behind, and the Dementors only made that worse.

The others looked up when he came in and sat down, and a surprised look briefly crossed McCusker's face. Bahry just shrugged, and dealt him a new hand.

After nearly five years of serving together, the three of them understood each other perfectly, after all.

Chapter 93: Little Children Grow Up, Pt2

Sunday afternoon, not that the day mattered much here.

After almost a week in Azkaban, Hermione's life had fallen into a certain routine.

She slept during the night, guarded by the Aurors' Patronuses, as they had still not stopped protecting her. She never again woke up under the Dementors' influence, although one time the Patronus had left briefly in the afternoon.

When she woke up in the morning, she would find the night meal in her cell. Typically bread, which would keep for a bit, so she saved that for lunch. She would then do some exercises in the confined area of her cell to wake up properly, and practice spells until the bracelet told her someone was coming. Then she would put everything away and climb under her blanket.

It was usually Auror Li who brought her breakfast. He was kind, and sometimes he sat with her for a few minutes, talking about his children. Understanding how boring life in Azkaban must be, he had also slipped her a book on Thursday morning. Tales of Beedle the Bard. It was a children's fairy tale book, but she didn't know the stories yet, and she'd soon read it through twice. It was a pleasant relief; her anonymous benefactor had given her a lot of books, but had apparently not thought to put any light entertainment in her pouch.

She was afraid to take her wand out again until Li had gone back to the Aurors' Headquarters (since the door to her cell block was too close to the stairs to notice in time when someone came from downstairs), so she would spend the time until he had returned doing the exercises from the Occlumency book that had been in her pouch. Not that she was getting very far with that. All this mentally pretending to be someone different was really, really hard. All she felt she'd really learned after several such practice sessions was that this wasn't really the sort of thing twelve-year-old children were supposed to be able to do.

Then she would continue practicing spells until it was time for lunch, and after that spend about two hours working on partial transfiguration. This was really hard, but she was starting to make some progress; yesterday she had successfully transfigured a square millimeter of wall into glass. Once magical exhaustion started to set in, she would move on to the non-magical books, either reading or doing exercises.

In the evening, another Auror would bring her a warm meal – healthy and nutritious like all meals here, even though it was utterly bland because no one would bother to add sugar or salt to food for prisoners who would hardly even taste it. She had wondered whether the good food was because of some ancient pre-Dementor regulation about treating the inmates well, or just to keep the prisoners healthy and suffering for as long as possible. She would then do some more Occlumency, followed by a bit more magical practice, finish off with some reading, and go to sleep.

Right now, she was doing exercises from the mathematical analysis book. And she was, surprisingly, bored.

It was amazing, she thought, how you could willingly spend hours and hours doing something, but not enjoy it when you had nothing else to do. The analysis book was hard. The first chapter started by defining what a natural number was, and then moved on to defining limits, and finally real numbers. She wasn't even halfway through the exercises, and they were interesting and challenging. If she'd been at Hogwarts, she would gladly have spent weeks in the library working through this book. She might even have considered going to a Muggle university for some time after her Hogwarts education, just to learn more about mathematics and physics, because it was so intriguing.

Hermione grumpily checked her proof attempt for errors again, and spotted a subscript she had mislaid. Perhaps she could complete it with this change?

Eventually she sighed, and closed the book. It was going nowhere. She just didn't feel like working, not on mathematics, nor on history or physics or Occlumency either. She wanted to go outside, take a stroll, maybe even (she shuddered at the thought) fly on a broomstick. As long as she could get out of this blasted cell.

Most of all, she wanted to talk to someone. Those two minutes with Li in the morning just weren't enough, and there was no one else to talk to. She was feeling lonely.

Today was Easter. Her parents would have been told, by now, that their daughter wouldn't come home for the holidays because she was in jail. Or would Professor McGonagall simply have lied, and claimed that she was dead? It might be kinder to them than knowing their daughter to be in Azkaban, but they were Muggles and so didn't know what the wizard prison was like.

Would they be allowed to visit her?

She desperately wanted to see them, even if it meant them seeing her sunk so deeply. She wanted to talk to them, at least over the phone. But she had no way to do that.

Well, actually...

She looked at the blazing humanoid, which stood next to the badger and lit up the room. Patronuses could be used to send messages, couldn't they? She and Harry had talked about it, before finding out that neither of them could do the charm, and theorized that the trick was probably just done by desiring someone else to know your happy thought. And she had a corporeal Patronus now, she could try it.

But what could she tell them?

And if they didn't know what happened yet, wouldn't this cause Professor McGonagall to find out, and then get in trouble for not reporting the huge breach of the law that someone had given her a wand? (Because she was quite sure that Professor McGonagall wouldn't report her, no matter what.)

Was the risk too great to be worth it? She really did want to talk to her parents... But what if they weren't alone?

A distant yell broke her out of her thinking. Very occasionally, she would hear them, the prisoners of the next block. They'd have to be yelling very loudly to be audible all the way over here. A nightmare, probably. She swallowed back the lump in her throat. Every once in a while, there was this reminder that she really had nothing to complain about. When all around you, people are cold and miserable, having nightmares in their sleep and reliving their worst memories in their minds while awake, a little loneliness just didn't compare.

... maybe there was something she could do.

It wasn't time for the evening meal yet, not by far. She should be safe for hours. It would be risky, but if the other prisoners didn't see her, they couldn't betray her. At most they could say that someone had been casting a Patronus, but why would anyone suspect the 12-year-old fellow prisoner in the next cell? And supposedly the Dementors also couldn't see you, if...

"Cloak," she whispered to her pouch, and the silvery cloak jumped into her hand. She threw the cloak over her back, and saw herself disappear, as the soft song lightly touched her mind.

"Alohomora." The grate to her cell clicked open. She sneaked outside, leaving the grate open because she might have to run back on a moment's notice if an Auror decided to come down for whatever reason.

"Alohomora." The metal door followed, as she swayed just a little from the magical effort of casting the spell twice in short succession.

And there she was, in the corridor filled with flickering gas lamps, where Li had walked her to her cell. She tiptoed towards the next cell block. Being closer, she could hear the sound of sobbing, but it stopped as she (and the Patronus) came closer.

"Stay!" someone inside yelled.

She stood still for a minute, replenishing her magical energy, then whispered "Alohomora."

Carefully, she opened the door. The smell assaulted her first. Urine, vomit... Hadn't the Auror cleaned this up when he got here a few hours ago, or was it fresh? She always tried to time her bathroom visits to avoid stinking up the cell, but these prisoners probably didn't have as much control over themselves...

In the first cell she saw, a man with horrible sunken eyes stared out of the bars. He looked so tired, so pained, that she almost lost control over the Patronus. But she pushed down on that emotion, and forced herself to look away and not think about what she was seeing too much. You're going to help them, she told herself.

There was movement in the two cells left of that one, she saw. But the two cells to the right, closest to her own cell block, were still empty.

Can you go into the fourth cell without showing yourself to them? she thought to the humanoid. If she left the Patronus outside the door, the Aurors might see its shine from the stairway before she felt them coming, but inside the cell block it would be safe (as long as the prisoners wouldn't be so stupid as to tell their guards about it). The Patronus just nodded, and shifted sideways somehow, and then it stood in the cell next to the man with the haunted eyes.

Stay, she mentally instructed, and then she closed the door, whispered Colloportus and went back to her cell like a good little prisoner.

Professor Michael Verres-Evans was reading the newspaper with a frown as Harry entered the apartment on Monday morning. All post arriving in their Oxford house was automatically delivered here to Hogwarts, so it was a Muggle newspaper, but the news seemed to be on very similar lines to the Daily Prophet. Harry winced as he saw the headlines.

Father looked up when he saw Harry come in. "It appears," he said in a low voice, "that zombies have attacked the town of Easingwold last Saturday. Some people have videotaped it. There are also pictures of zombies walking the highways. I would normally disregard this sort of thing as sensationalist nonsense or an elaborate hoax, but..." he helplessly waved an arm, indicating his surroundings, "I realize that perhaps I should be more open to the supernatural. Is this something your people know more about?"

Harry sank down in the deep, soft sofa opposite his father. Mother, he saw, was peeking out from the bedroom door.

"I guess this is where I tell you about You-Know-Who."

"No, I don't know who."

"Lord..." Harry took a deep breath. "Voldemort," he whispered. It sent shivers down his spine, saying the name himself.

"Lord Voldemort?" Professor Verres repeated at a normal tone.

"Don't say the name!" Harry exclaimed. "Please. It's bad enough that Dumbledore and McGonagall keep using it. It just feels like... I can't even explain. We call him He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named or You-Know-Who usually."

The Muggle man raised his eyebrows. "That seems a bit extreme."

"That was him, wasn't it?" Petunia Evans-Verres had come in and sat down on the sofa next to her son. "He's the one who killed Lily. And James."

"He is," Harry nodded. "He was apparently this kind of dark wizard who tried to take over the country by terror. People fought him, of course, but it's a lot easier to break things down than to protect them. Thousands of people died, not just magical folk, but of course Muggles thought that it was just accidents."

His father nodded. "That's roughly what Petunia told me after you went to school. And then he killed Lily and James, and he tried to kill you but some accident happened and he died, right?"

"That's the story, yes. Except that, one, he's not actually dead. Two, there was this prophecy about him and me, apparently we're destined enemies and one of us is going to have to kill the other. And three, it turns out he's actually an evil genius, and I have no idea how I'm going to fight him, or even what he's really trying to do."

The cup of tea mother had been holding fell to the floor and broke in pieces with a clatter. Father stared at him.

"I think your imagination is getting the better of you, son."

"No, dad." He took out his wand, pointed it at the carpet, and muttered "scourgify, everto". The tea stain and the broken pieces disappeared. "I am deadly serious. I didn't really believe it either, at first, but I was wrong. He really did survive, and I'm going to have to fight him someday. Sooner rather than later, probably, because people are dying. We're fairly sure he's behind the zombie attack. And he was definitely the one who framed who Hermione."

"We?" Professor Verres repeated. "Who's 'we'? Some friends of yours?"

"The Headmaster of the school, who's also the de facto leader of the light side of the war. Two other professors, and Moody, that's an Au- a policeman, although he's retired."

The Professor stood up, looking very angry indeed. "What the hell is going on in this school? Are your teachers actually telling an eleven-year old child to fight a terrorist? Are they mad? I'm taking you home right this second."

Petunia shot her son a questioning look, which he answered with a slight shake of the head. Her voice was thin when she spoke. "They won't let us, Michael."

"They have no legal right to stop us –"

"Right? You're Muggles," Harry bit. "You have as much standing in the magical British legal system as, I don't know, gorillas. It's not acceptable to torture or kill you, but you don't count as people either. No wizard is going to bother listening to any of your arguments." He shrugged. "And while I don't agree with that in most cases, I think this time it's for the best."

"What?"

"Dad, please, forget about me being only eleven for once. This dark wizard terrorist is real. He's killed off half a village full of Muggles just two days ago. How hard do you think it would be to do the same in Oxford? He knows where we live! I'm not sure how safe it is here in the school, but I'm not going home, and I don't think you should either!"

The Professor was breathing heavily. "All right. We can talk about this. Are you sure he's trying to hurt you?"

"I'm not sure of anything," Harry admitted. "Least of all what he's trying to do. But he knows me. And he absolutely, definitely, takes an interest in me. Besides, he is mass-murdering people, dad!"

"Which is not your responsibility! You're a child, Harry!" He paced the room, agitated, something he very rarely did. "Prophecy or not, you are too young to be involved in a war." He paused, and visibly forced himself to restore his calm. "Don't you dare do anything to put yourself into harm's way. I will be talking with your teachers about what they're putting into children's heads."

"I'm not really a child anymore, dad." The boy sighed, and stood up from the sofa. "But I guess I'll always be one to you no matter what happens. And maybe that's okay." He went to the door. "I must go now, I'm meeting someone at eleven. But I'm sure Professor McGonagall won't mind talking to you. I'll be back for lunch."

The meeting with Lesath Lestrange wasn't very successful.

Lesath had worked his way through the books on Harry's reading list, spending every waking hour on them. Today he'd asked his "master" for explanations of some of the harder concepts.

But he still couldn't cast the True Patronus Charm.

He tried, over and over. His wandwork was perfect. And yet he couldn't produce a Patronus. Harry thought he could sense it, the point where the boy failed. The little hesitation in his voice. Lesath was too afraid. Try as he might, he could never believe to his core that he had it in him to turn on death, Dementors and other evils, and win.

When the boy finally lowered his wand, there were tears in his eyes.

"I am sorry, my Lord. I have failed you."

"You haven't," Harry reassured him, even though he had to make an effort not to show his disappointment. "It was a gamble from the start. Only one wizard in ten can learn to cast the normal Patronus Charm, and I think this one is a lot harder and doesn't have the mist-form. In time, you might still learn it. It requires a pretty large change in your mind, to take to this spell. That costs time."

The boy nodded. But it was clear he didn't believe it.

"Besides," the Boy-Who-Lived added. "I don't think you need to be able to cast the spell to pass it on. If something should happen to me, you will be able to make sure that this spell is not forgotten."

The fifth-year boy's eyes widened in shock. "But surely nothing could hurt you?"

I wish, Harry thought, but instead he just said: "I lead a dangerous life, Lestrange."

There was silence, for a while.

"If I should die," the Boy-Who-Lived spoke at last, "Then find other people to teach the spell to. Only those who cannot cast the normal Patronus Charm, even though they have tried, and their gestures are perfect. People who don't seem dark or unhappy. Definitely not those who believe that blood purity makes you a superior person, or who have similar ridiculous biases against other people. They must not be willing to sacrifice other people for some greater good. And ideally, choose people who can shield their mind with Occlumency."

Lesath shifted on his feet. "Those are a lot of requirements, my Lord."

"Yes," Harry agreed. "But you will have time. I hope this will not be necessary, but if something does go wrong, it will be your task to make sure that the knowledge of this spell does not die with me."

"Yes, my Lord."

"I finished my review," father said when Harry came into the apartment for lunch. "I've just given it to your Deputy-Headmistress to post, when she came to see how we were doing. We have an appointment with her later this afternoon."

Harry nodded. "Anything you want to do before?"

The professor beamed brightly. "I would definitely like to see that library of yours."

Hundreds of thousands of books.

Bookcases reaching up to the distant ceiling, meters high, with ladders to reach the higher shelves.

Silence, except that sometimes the books seemed to rustle, even though there was no wind. There was a lone student sitting at a desk somewhere in a distant corner, but he wasn't making any sounds.

The air, saturated with the smell of old books.

"Son," Professor Verres-Evans said with a hint of awe in his voice. "I think I'm going to cry."

It was almost two hours later when Petunia – who had been quietly bored until Harry found her a book of fairy tales, which might be all about magic but that was only normal, for fairy tales – pointed out that she could really use a cup of tea before their appointment with Professor McGonagall.

As they walked back to the apartment and passed a corridor, Harry thought he heard a sharp intake of breath. It cut off immediately, and when Harry looked around, he just saw a hint of a black robes disappearing in the shadows.

It was only after he had delivered his parents to McGonagall's office half an hour later, and started trudging back to his common room, that a figure appeared before him.

"Come with me," Severus Snape said softly.

The two of them were sitting in the office of the Deputy Headmistress of Hogwarts. The middle-aged dark-haired woman in front of them looked well-organized, firm, reliable, but none of that would ever stop Petunia from remembering that she could kill the two of them in a second if she so wished. She might not have much reason to do that, of course, but the woman was also quite capable of removing their memories of everything magic-related in their lives, something which Lily had said happened quite regularly. And as that not only included the existence of her sister, but also their son, it would be just as bad as killing them.

Michael took up the conversation. He always did the talking for the both of them.

"My son seems to be under the impression that he is destined to fight this evil genius, who killed his birth-parents, faked his own death, framed a fellow student, and is now setting zombies onto normal people." He spoke calmly, but there was an edge to his voice. You'd have to know him well to understand that he was angry.

The woman raised her eyebrows. "Did Harry say that?"

"Yes. Did his imagination run away with him?"

"No, that is pretty much accurate," the older woman said. "But I shall have to ask him about the 'faking death' part. As far as I know, Lord Voldemort survived the death of his body merely because he is immortal, not because he planned on it."

Michael opened and shut his mouth a few times, seeming lost for words, but then apparently decided not to pursue this track of conversation.

"My son is also under the impression," and his tone turned more sharp, "that this is somehow his problem. That he will have to fight this dark wizard, and I quote, sooner rather than later. That he has to worry about how he's going to do that. This it is his responsibility to get his friend out of jail. And yesterday, he seemed remarkably depressed, like he was thinking that this zombie attack was somehow his fault."

A sad look crossed the witch's face. "I suppose that was to be expected."

Michael's eye spasmed a little, and Petunia carefully laid a hand on his leg. She had explained to him, earlier this morning, what the magical response to Muggles getting uppity was. That he couldn't throw up too much of a storm, demand his rights, threaten with legal action or notify the government. He hadn't liked it much, but she had got through to him, and she hoped he would remember.

"Why," he bit, when he had control over his voice again, "have you even been telling him any of these things? Does the concept of a child not mean anything to you? He is eleven years old. He should be playing and reading science fiction books. Not thinking about how he's going to kill some dark terrorist!"

"We never planned to tell him," the woman said. "Not until he was fifteen at least. But he guessed at the truth early on, and I... didn't quite manage to hide my shock, which led him to figure out that something was going on. From there on, it has been a series of uncanny derivations, nagging and even blackmail from his side. We always knew that his childhood could not be long, but I assure you we did try to shield him from too much knowledge, danger and politics for as long as we could. Unfortunately, he would have none of it."

Petunia exchanged a look with her husband. He looked as resigned as she felt. That did sound like Harry indeed.

"We only invited him into our council last week, after Miss Granger was arrested," the Scottish witch continued. "He demanded to be involved, as the fate of his two best friends was at stake; and even if he hadn't, it would have been foolish not to consult him, as he knows more about both children than any of us. As it was, he made several valuable contributions, and almost managed to save Miss Granger from Azkaban." Her face took on a sad look. "Unfortunately the price was still too high."

"Five million pounds," Petunia whispered. "It would have been higher without Harry?"

The woman shook her head. "The only reason we could pay for her freedom at all is because of Harry. He found a... legal trick, to gain some leverage over Lord Malfoy. Anyway, after that, he demanded full information, and with his friends already being targeted for his sake, we could not withhold the words of the prophecy from him any longer. Within an hour, he solved a problem we've had for years, and then... Well, in hindsight we should have consulted him much earlier. Without his input, we would still not know that Voldemort was hiding right under our noses."

What? Beside her, Michael blinked.

"Ah," Professor McGonagall said. "I see he hasn't quite told you the finer points of the situation."

They looked at each other again.

"He gave us the two-minute version," Michael spoke. "I don't suppose you would care to fill us in on the rest?"

"Of course," Professor McGonagall sighed. "With the current situation it's not like secrecy is still an option anyway." She rung a small golden bell, and with a *pop* a creature appeared on her desk. Petunia almost jumped back in shock at the ugly little thing with its leathery skin, bat-like ears on an over-sized head and bulging green eyes.

"Lakey," the Deputy Headmistress said. "Will you fetch us some tea and coffee please? I suspect we will be here for a while."

The office of the Head of House Slytherin was a lot like the Potions dungeons. Cold, drafty-looking stones, shelves with all kinds of things drifting in jars on them, books that somehow managed to look nasty despite having plain coverings and closed bottles with mysterious substances. A fire lit in the fireplace as the assassin stalked in ahead, which somehow made the room look even eerier rather than more comfortable.

And then Severus Snape sank into his chair and suddenly turned into someone else. His face showed the strange sad look that Harry had seen only once before, in a hallway several months ago. "Please, sit down."

Harry sat down in the other chair, as the Potions Master incanted a series of privacy spells.

When the Professor was done, he spoke again, with a strange tone to his voice. "Your aunt looks well. She has... changed, since I last saw her."

Harry nodded silently, still wondering what this was about.

"I never knew that Lily made peace with her sister," the Potion's Master whispered. For a few moments, it was as though he had forgotten Harry's presence. But then he shook himself.

"I do not know how best to broach this topic, Mr. Potter, so I will simply say it... before the Dementor, you recovered your memory of the night your parents died?"

Harry silently nodded.

"If... I know it must not be a pleasant memory, but... if you could tell me what happened...?"

"Why?" Harry said. His voice was solemn, definitely not mocking the pleading look that Harry had never expected to see from that person. "I wouldn't think that would be a pleasant thing for you to hear either, Professor –"

The Potions Master's voice was almost a whisper. "I have imagined it every night these last ten years."

"I –" Harry hesitated, but took a decision. It was not a request that Harry could really bring himself to deny. But he could get something out of it. It was not likely that he would have many opportunities to speak to the Potions teacher alone, and he might speak more openly without the Headmaster's presence.

"Will you tell me exactly how you came to learn about the Prophecy? I'm sorry to make this a trade, I will tell you afterward, only, it could be really important –"

"There is little to say. I had come to be interviewed by the Deputy Headmistress for the position of Potions Master, and so I was waiting outside her office while the applicant before me, Sybill Trelawney, ended her interview for the position of Professor of Divination. Minerva had already opened the door to send her away when the prophecy came. As soon as Trelawney finished speaking her words, I fled, forsaking my chance at Hogwarts's Mastery, and went to the Dark Lord." The Potions Master's face was drawn and tight. "I did not even pause to consider why that riddle might have come to me, before I sold it to another."

"A job interview?" Harry said. "Where you and Professor Trelawney both happened to be applying, Professor McGonagall was interviewing, and the door just happened to be open at the right time? That seems... like rather a large coincidence..."

"Seers are the pawns of time, Mr. Potter. Coincidence is beneath them, and they are above it. I was the one meant to hear that prophecy and become its fool. Minerva's presence made no final difference to how it came about. There was no Memory Charm as you supposed. The voice of a seer has a quality, an enigma which even Legilimency cannot share. How could that be imbued in a false memory? Do you think the Dark Lord would believe my mere words? He seized my mind and saw the mystification there, even if he could not seize the mystery, and so he knew the prophecy had been true. The Dark Lord could have killed me then, having taken what he wanted – I was a fool indeed to go to him – but he saw something in me I do not know, and took me into the Death Eaters, though on his terms rather than mine. That is how I brought it about, brought it all about, from beginning to end, always my own doing."

Severus's voice had gone rather hoarse, and his face was filled with naked pain. Harry filed the information away for future analysis – there were some very suspicious parts in this explanation, but he would have to go to the library to get a clearer idea of how prophecies worked. And he couldn't keep Professor Snape waiting while he thought.

Harry swallowed twice, and began recounting the memory.

Wednesday afternoon, in the Deputy Headmistress' office.

"Harry..." she was almost pleading. "I had to spend quite some time assuring your parents yesterday that we were not deliberately involving you in a war." She had had good explanations, of course, because in this case they were quite innocent. But she had still felt monstrously guilty explaining to the Professor and his silent but obviously perceptive wife why their bright young child had turned into a grave adult over the course of the school year.

The boy raised his eyebrows. "I do hope you're not letting them talk you into treating me like a child again. You are better than that, Professor. People are dying and you need me. If even a single life is lost or ruined because you withheld information for me, would that be worth it?"

It hit her. Harry always had that way of pushing her triggers. "No eleven-year-old should even think about such things!"

"I can agree to that," the Boy-Who-Lived answered reasonably. "But that is not the world we live in, Professor McGonagall. I am already thinking about such things. Is it better to work from old data and consider a lot of possibilities which are irrelevant, or to focus on what is actually happening? And something is happening, I can see it in the way you look and act."

How had the boy become so perceptive?

"There's been another attack." Albus had told her a few days ago that she should give the boy any information he asked for. He had looked sad, when he said that, but she hadn't pressed for his reasons. "A primary school in southern Wales."

A look of dismay passed over the boy's face, and then left, as the face settled into that too-hard look again. "Any survivors?"

"Nobody died," she answered. "But the children and teachers were all unconscious when they were found, and their right legs had been cursed off. St. Mungo healers are trying whether magical healing can regrow the limbs, but Professor Dumbledore says there isn't much hope."

"Ah." The boy seemed to consider this information. "Did they go back in time to..."

"Yes," she immediately confirmed. It hadn't been foremost in her mind when she heard, she was too shocked to learn about the roughly hundred and fifty children who would be maimed for life, but Albus and Amelia had a different way of thinking. "Director Bones went back in time the instant she was informed, but it was already too late; the victims were unconscious and the perpetrator was gone. We learned about it only long after the event, you see. There were no Muggleborns, Squibs or anyone familiar with our world in that village, to warn us before the Muggle authorities got there."

"Ah," the boy said again. "That's going to be hard to cover up."

She nodded. Albus had spoken heavily of the Ministry's and international concerns about that. One obviously magical attack in a week was quite a disaster already, but two might be enough to endanger the International Statute of Secrecy. The eyes of the magical world were upon them, now. He had added, with a grim note to his voice, that he had barely managed to stop the Minister of Magic from having all the children killed, as their deaths at the hand of some crazed killer would be far easier to explain than their survival in this way.

"Thank you," the boy said quietly. "I will think about this."

"Harry, you can't do anything here. And you don't need to. Why don't you leave this to Albus? He knows how to fight a war."

The boy smirked bitterly as he stood up.

"Because I don't trust his judgment."

Harry trudged back to his dormitory, frustrated.

People were dying, or getting hurt for life, and there was nothing he could do about it. Even if he wasn't stuck in this school, he couldn't anticipate where the enemy would strike next, and so he couldn't stop it from happening. Nor did he have the power to do anything about the consequences. He couldn't cast a charm that would give a schoolful of cursed children back a semblance of their legs. He couldn't trace down remaining Inferi, or cast protective charms over every single Muggle dwelling in the country, And if there were political aspects to this mess, Dumbledore wasn't telling him about them.

So he stayed put, like a good little child. He spent time with his parents. He also spent a lot of time in the library, looking up spells that he could cast which might come in useful. He had nagged Professor McGonagall to sign a permission slip so he could look up information about prophecies and possession in the restricted section, but got almost nothing out of it: the books on prophecies had done little but confirm tentatively what Dumbledore and Snape had told him, whereas the books on possession were too limited and often contradictory. Quietly, in the secrecy of his trunk, he practiced speed-casting the True Patronus Charm – if it came to a confrontation, it might play into Quirrell's hands to be seen to block the Killing Curse, but it would, on the whole, still be preferable over not doing so. He had tried talking to Draco, but the boy seemed to be avoiding him. He still hadn't figured out a way to conclusively prove Hermione's innocence – using a Pensieve to reproduce his conversation with Quirrell might help a little, but it would lead to all kinds of questions about his history with Quirrell, including the Azkaban breakout. Even if that was not an issue, Pensieve-memories could be changed, so it wasn't likely to be enough.

He practiced dueling with Neville every day, even though he didn't expect those skills to be of any use: it would be years before he'd have the sheer magical power to even be able to disarm a Death Eater. As for landing any spell on Lord Voldemort, a.k.a. Quirrell, well, having gone over the possibilities it didn't seem like a wise thing to try. Never mind the chance that it would kill both of them – if their magic resonated out of control again, it might well cause a magical explosion with massive casualties. Quirrell might be able to stop that, as he had done before, but in this case he had very little incentive to be the surrendering party. It would be like a game of chicken, with incredibly high stakes.

And besides all that, of course, he had done a lot of thinking.

Grindelwald was my dark mirror. He was what I could have so easily become, if I had given in to the temptation of believing that I was always right.

Dumbledore had told him that, months ago, when the world still seemed innocent. Like Grindelwald had been his foe, he believed that Voldemort was Harry's, and therefore Harry should understand him better than anyone else. And in a way, Harry could see that now. Despite everything, he still felt a bond with the man he had known as Quirinius Quirrell.

Had it all been an act? Or had some of his real self shown through? Harry suspected the latter. He could see how someone who, roughly, thought as Professor Quirrell had seemed to, would be willing to kill innocents to achieve some dark purpose of his own. What kindness and humanity he had shown had been a lie – and in hindsight, that was never very much to begin with – but his dry humor, cynical outlook and moments of depression might not have been.

Why would someone deliberately become a monster? Why do evil for the sake of evil? Why Voldemort?

He still didn't have an answer to that question. The entity who had used Bellatrix Back, Memory-Charmed Hermione Granger, nailed Yermy Wibble's family's skins to a wall and now handicapped a schoolful of innocent Muggle children was empty inside, that was certain. He felt no warmth for other people at all, and did not get affected by their suffering. And it seemed plausible, although it was painful to imagine, that Professor Quirrell could be like that –

– but not without good reason. That was the thing, really. Harry found it incredibly hard to believe that the person he thought he had known would take pleasure in the suffering of others. He might not care about it, but if he merely did not care, he would not go out of his way to inflict pain on innocents without an ulterior motive.

What does he want?

Harry had asked Professor Quirrell that question before. And he'd gotten a pretty clear answer.

I want Britain to grow strong under a strong leader.

Plan iss for you to rule country.

The answer fit what he had been doing. In the guise of Professor Quirrell, he had helped Harry grow stronger. He had taught him to control his temper. Had set him up as an army General and forced him to fight against impossible odds. Had helped him sow fear in the hearts of his schoolmates, when he had protected Hermione and the other heroines. He had painted him in a light that was both good and evil, light and darkness, so that Gryffindor and Slytherin would both be willing to follow him. And he had tried to get Harry to publicly defeat the Dark Lord again, with a large international audience.

Why do evil for the sake of evil?

If Harry had guessed correctly, the initial goal had been to set up an evil puppet for Monroe to fight. The greater the evil you defeat, the greater the hero. Yet this plan had failed, and so Monroe had disappeared, but Voldemort had gone on. He might have conquered the country easily, but he could not hope to also win the hearts of the people. There were too many who would never willingly follow a wizard who gained power by force, and thus Britain would stay divided, and not grow strong like he wanted. And so he hadn't conquered the country. He had prolonged the war, become known as the most terrible dark wizard in history. The scenario was perfectly set up to make a new hero arise.

Harry Potter.

Was the prophecy a fake? Severus Snape certainly didn't seem to consider it possible, but that didn't mean it wasn't. It just meant that Voldemort would have needed to know something that Snape and the others didn't.

A one-year-old child, with a prophecy about having power the Dark Lord knows not, who defeated the greatest dark wizard who ever lived. Harry had read some of the books about himself, and the theories as to why it had happened were wild. There were enough of them to allow everyone to believe whatever they wanted. And if that child went on to defeat that same dark wizard again, doing the impossible deliberately, and not as some strange kind of magical accident... such a hero might be able to unite the country.

Why exactly would the person behind Voldemort / Quirrell / Monroe want Harry to rule the country? Because he thought Harry might end up doing exactly what he wanted done? Because he believed that he could manipulate him?

Because he fully expected to be able to control him?

There was something special about the Boy-Who-Lived. He had a dark side which gave him extreme deductive power, and felt a mysterious feeling of doom around his destined foe. Dumbledore had guessed that Voldemort had tried a form of mind-control that had – unintentionally – grown into him. But if it had not been intended, then why would he still want Harry to rule? Why continue the same charade and play the part of Voldemort sowing terror?

Harry had initially refused to participate in the plan to pretend-defeat Lord Voldemort, which would perfectly set him up to take a leadership role should the need arise. But his co-operation might not be required. If Voldemort officially returned, then Harry could hardly step aside. It might not happen at the International Confederation of Wizards – Dumbledore was making sure he was there every moment of the day (taking excursions back to Britain only when Time-Turned) and Moody covered the place when he was asleep – but there would undoubtedly be other opportunities. And he had the feeling this week's attacks were simply a stepping stone to his ulterior plan.

Thursday evening.

The two of them were standing on top of Ravenclaw Tower together.

Earlier that day, Harry had been surprised to see Parvati and Padma at lunch. He had plopped himself down next to Padma (he was going to have lunch with his parents, but he could be five minutes late) and given her a querying look.

It had turned out that she and her sister had been sent back to the comparative safety of Hogwarts, as their parents lived in a primarily Muggle town, and had been scared by the dual attacks. And so it begins, Harry had wryly thought.

There was one advantage. Padma had also told him that she'd finished reading the books he'd given her. And before leaving, Harry had urged her to spend the rest of the day thinking about a world without death.

And now here they were. Twilight had fallen, with the stars just starting to become visible overhead.

"Why did you ask me to imagine a world without death?" she asked.

"Did you?" he asked in return.

She nodded. "I would have called it silly last week. If you can't die, you'll just grow indefinitely older and get sick and if you get cursed you're screwed forever. But I guess what you really meant was a world where you don't have to die, right? Like in your books, people don't age, and diseases are curable, so you have eternal life and eternal youth."

"Yes. That is what I meant."

She nodded again. "That would be rather nice. I guess overpopulation would become a problem, but then, we could solve that, right? If we can go to other planets..." She hesitated. "Muggles haven't actually done that, have they?"

"They have gone to the moon," Harry answered quietly, looking up at the half-full moon above the castle. "And some other planets in our solar system. Not any further yet, but they will. They're figuring out the underlying rules of the universe, and even without magic I think they'll find a way to at least get to Alpha Centauri within the next century. There were only two generations between the first airplane and the first moon landing, and computers are still getting twice as good every one and half year. Add magic into the mix, and I imagine we could do wonders."

"We'd have to get around the International Statute of Secrecy, though," Padma pointed out. "Because even if wizards started doing science, there wouldn't be enough of us to make that kind of progress."

"Would that be bad thing?"

"No," she said with a smile. "I guess not."

"Do you believe in it?" He kept his tone wistful, definitely not pushing. "Do you think we could do it? Unite the magical and Muggle worlds, get rid of old age and diseases, make everyone immortal, travel to other stars... Can you believe in that?"

She looked up to the stars in silence for a while.

"I don't know," she said eventually. "But I'd like to try."

"Do you have any guess why I asked you to imagine such a world?"

"Because you want to built it?" she guessed.

"That is one of the reasons, yes."

"But Dementors don't really fit in that picture," she hazarded.

"No, for multiple reasons," he said with a smile. It was time, he decided. "They represent death."

The girl beside him turned her head sharply. "What?"

"The fear is just a side effect," he explained, keeping his voice calm as though he were telling her something perfectly normal. "The Patronus Charm works best for those who are not afraid of death, and can think of happy stuff instead even when a shadow of Death is standing right in front of them."

"Ah," she said. Then, after a pause, "I can see why that wouldn't work."

Harry nodded. "But there is another way. I do not fear death either. Why fear what I fully intend to defeat? And nor should you."

There was silence, for a while.

"You're quite ambitious," she said eventually.

"I know," Harry responded.

After another minute of silence, she took out her wand, and looked at it thoughtfully. It was hard to see her face, now, as darkness had fallen while they talked.

"Do I just think of that world you had me imagine, with eternal youth, and going to the stars?"

"Don't just think about it," Harry breathed. "Intend it. It is the world we will make together, you and I and Hermione, and everyone else who will join us."

She nodded, and set her feet into the pose Mr. Lupin had taught them.

"Expecto Patronum!"

And there was light.

Chapter 94: Nihil Supernum, Pt 1

Friday April 17th, 1992.

Hermione Granger was pondering escape.

She wasn't really considering it, the otter had told her not to escape, and it would put the Aurors in so much trouble if she was found missing. But the otter had told her not to and that meant that it was possible, and at least she wanted to figure out how before deciding not to do it.

The Cloak was bound to help. If she could somehow get outside, she could just walk towards the shore, and the Dementors wouldn't affect her; they wouldn't even notice she was out of her cell. Also, the Aurors wouldn't see her because she'd be invisible. But the only door in the fortress that she knew of was the door in the Aurors' Headquarters, and there was no way she could get through that without it being noticed. Plus, she'd be on the roof, fat lot of good that would do.

No wait, that was easy. She'd already done it. Gecko setae. The material would probably work on metal as well as stone, so she could transfigure gloves and just Stick, plop invisibly down to the bottom of the building. A minor silencing charm would mute the sounds.

It would be really dangerous, though. She had no feather-falling potion this time. And if there was wind, the cloak might get blown away while she was clinging to the wall, and she'd be exposed both to the Aurors' eyes and to the Dementors. There was no way for her to assess weather conditions from here. Besides, how would she even get to the roof, or otherwise outside?

What would Harry do?

No. No way. Even Harry wouldn't be stupid enough to transfigure a hair into TNT and blow up the wall. Transfiguration had rules for a reason, and she felt dirty for even considering it as a remote possibility that someone else might do in the hypothetical escape situation that she was not, to be perfectly clear, at all considering really doing.

What else would Harry do?

General Chaos had many tricks up his sleeve; he used any remote bit of obscure magic or Muggle technology that he could think of. So now she browsed through her excellent memory for a way to make holes in the wall.

Oh. Right. It wouldn't even require Muggle technology.

So she could break out, climb down and simply walk to the shore unnoticed. That would be dangerous, but if she went down the stairs to the bottom of the building first, she could minimize the risks. Although then she might have to think of some Muggle methods to get from the island to the mainland, when she didn't even know the direction or how far she'd have to go... It would certainly be awkward to break out of Azkaban undetected, and then proceed to drown because she couldn't swim that far. But if she could transfigure a raft and a compass and just go east –

A distant yell broke her out of her thoughts once more. It was muted by the walls, but even so, it was still audible.

She trembled. It was hard enough to not think about it for most of the day, when there was silence. Hard enough to just be content to study while her Patronus guarded the people in the cells next to hers, or in the corridor below her, but never both at once. Hard enough to ignore that, further down, people were suffering even more, and she could not help them because it would be too dangerous. But when she could hear the screams, it pierced right through all her mental barriers. Never mind that the scream itself meant that there was still a lot of life left in them, she wanted to make it stop, but to do so she'd have to take her Patronus away from the other people it was protecting...

She felt it, the Patronus going out of control. She clamped down desperately on her emotions, but it was already too late. For a split second, the badger in her cell seemed to stare down, and she quickly dropped her wand. The badger resumed its normal floating as though nothing had happened. The Aurors might have noticed, or they might not have. She'd find out soon enough whether they came down, but she didn't care right now.

Tears streaked her face. The Patronus made everything so much harder, it strengthened your emotions of protection. How could she cast it again and not have it go out of control now? But while she couldn't control her emotions, she wasn't protecting any of the prisoners, and they all needed her, the ones on her own level, and one level down, and all those others whom she couldn't reach, living in nightmares day and night. If only there was a way to protect them all...

Maybe there was.

The realization hit her with the force of a tsunami. The otter had told her how to do this. If she made her Patronus go bright enough, it would destroy Dementors, but she should never do that, for it would kill her.

But if she could destroy all the Dementors in Azkaban first, wouldn't that be worth it?

She could send her Patronus down right now, down into the pit. The Aurors would see it, but if she let her emotions go out of control, chose to protect all the prisoners right away, they might not trace its source until it was too late. And with the Dementors gone, at last the prisoners of Azkaban could have... not much a life, really, take away the Dementors and this place was still worse than the worst Muggle jail... but they wouldn't be suffering any more, at least. Maybe it would help.

I will die.

It was a scary thought. She didn't want to die, she wanted to live, to see that bright future without any Dementors, without death, without needless suffering and cruel prisons and evil governments, she wanted to be with her parents and Professor McGonagall, and Harry and Padma and Hannah and Daphne... And would her sacrifice even be worth it? She was only a child, she only had a little power, if she gave all her life-force and it wouldn't have destroyed all the Dementors, then wouldn't the prisoners still continue to suffer? Would it all be in vain?

She hesitated.

And then a bird appeared in her cell.

She yelped, jumped back in fright, bashed into the wall and nearly fell over. Rubbing her head, she stared at the creature. Its eyes were bright, its shining wings flapping slowly, keeping it at eye level. It was surrounded by flames, red and gold.

CAW!

"Sssssh!" she shushed desperately. "What if they hear you, and come look?" How could she explain a phoenix in her cell? She didn't even know how it got there.

Caw!

Let's go. That was what it meant.

"Whose phoenix are you?"

Caw. Yours, if you choose.

The phoenix was here to help her, to destroy the Dementors in the pit and save all those prisoners who so desperately needed her help.

"Can you help me get down into the pit?" A Patronus was more effective if it was closer to its caster. If she was near the Dementors, the chance of destroying them all before she died would be much greater.

Caw. Uncertain. She bit her lip. She could go out of her cell, walk down the many stairs of the building, and send her Patronus when she was at the bottom. It would be closer, but the walls were thicker there, she knew, and enchanted with many protections, or the Dementors would corrode them over time. She didn't know whether that would make a difference, but it might.

"If I break a hole into the walls here, can you fly me down?"

Caw!

"It will take me a few hours to do that, would you wait for that?"

Caw!

It would wait until she was ready. The morning patrol had only ended an hour or so ago; she had plenty of time before the Aurors would come into her cell with the evening meal. Barring unforeseen circumstances like new prisoners, there was absolutely nothing stopping her from transfiguring a hole into the wall, being flown down into the pit invisibly, and throwing all her life force into the Patronus, to destroy every single Dementor that tarnished this place, if she could hold out for that long. She could feel the silvery light in her, even with her wand still on the ground, longing to burst out.

But she would die.

The destruction of its prison would bring chaos to the country. And what was worse, they'd find out she had a wand. There would be questioning, and those kind Aurors who'd protected her would be in serious trouble. And Harry... if they found out she'd gotten help, they'd be sure to trace down her anonymous benefactor...

But at least she wouldn't be able to betray anything. If she was dead, they couldn't give her Veritaserum. They could never read her mind anymore.

She swallowed then, and took her decision. Picking the wand up from the floor, she placed it against the wall, and started her transfiguration.

"Mr. Potter, I have made a formal statement to the Ministry that your Time-Turner is locked to the hours between nine and midnight."

"Sure. By all means, tell them you've changed it. The point is, under the current circumstances, it is madness for me not to have all protections I could possibly have."

She hesitated, but finally she nodded, and opened her hand. The Boy-Who-Lived laid the Time-Turner into it, and she brought forth her wand and did as he had asked, releasing the time-keyed enchantment she'd laced into the shell's lock.

Harry Potter flipped open the golden shell, looked at the tiny glass hourglass within its circles, nodded, and then snapped the case shut.

"Thank you. And speaking of protections, I would also like three two-person broomsticks, six phials of feather-falling potion and three invisibility cloaks to store in my pouch and give to my friends. I would be happy to buy them by owl-order, but it appears that I have no authority whatsoever over my own vault. A number of spare wands and emergency-portkeys in the form of rings, toe-rings and other items of jewelery, and two spare Time-Turners for my friends would also be helpful. If you know of any spell that could be used to block light from a certain direction, I would like to learn it. And is it possible to acquire either dynamite or more subtle, magical ways to get through walls?"

With a sigh of relief, Hermione finished her transfiguration.

She checked her watch. Ten past four. This had been a long trance, but that was not surprising given that she'd only trained with partial transfiguration for less than two weeks. But it was done now, and if she did not tarry, she could be out there before the Aurors came for the evening meal. And she had better, because even if the bird could hide itself, there was no way they wouldn't notice the fact that a one-millimeter-thin section of the wall, tracing the form of a 70-by-50-centimeter rectangle, had been turned into cotton. All except for the tiny, almost invisible bit at the top, where a buckytube fiber held the metal inside the rectangle into place.

She pulled a hair from her head, and transfigured it into a knife; thin, but with a long enough blade to reach the end of the wall. That was easier; just a normal transfiguration. She cut easily through the cotton. And then there was only a tiny buckytube string, holding up the heavy piece of metal, that separated her cell from the outside world.

Once she finited the buckytube, and the tiny bit of the original metal broke because it could not hold up the whole rectangle by itself, there would be a loud clang, she figured, so she set up a silencing barrier so it would not be heard outside her cell.

She took the cloak out of the pouch necklace, and carefully took the latter off her neck. She rolled the necklace into the cloak, and laid it down, invisibly, below the bench.

She was trembling, as she tried casting her Patronus again, and she had to clear her mind and repeat the incantation before it took hold, and the blazing humanoid appeared. There were only two things left to do.

She breathed, steaded her voice, and said: "Tell Harry..."

"... not likely, but I will see what I can do," Minerva concluded.

The boy looked grim. "I suppose I'll have to be content with that, for now. But why is the ministry so obstinate? Has Professor Dumbledore not explained the situation to them?"

"He tried," she answered. "Some key figures like Amelia Bones believe him, but the Minister of Magic and others do not. With those people being certain to contradict him, it would be unwise to speak out in public." She sighed. "So instead he has told people that our Defense Professor has shown signs of evil, and that he was likely the one behind the attacks, and the Azkaban Breakout. We have preciously little evidence to go on, however. Even if they did acknowledge the situation, though, I doubt they would see the need to guard your friends with Time-Turners. Most Aurors don't have Time-Turners, only senior Aurors are even aware of them, and the Ministry keep close tabs on who possesses one. And while the Ministry would not object to a light-diversion charm, even I don't understand how it would help you."

The boy shrugged. "Blinding enemies to get away without getting hit myself, to name an example. Most shields –"

And then she almost jumped back in shock at the sudden light, she'd only seen that kind of brightness once before, as a blazing silver humanoid appeared in her office.

"Harry," it said, in Hermione Granger's voice. "Someone gave me a wand, and books, and... People are suffering here, and they need help. So I'm about to cast your Patronus Charm, and not hold back. I will die, but maybe it will help."

Minerva gasped. Harry Potter sat rooted to his chair in horror, as the humanoid continued:

"I'll leave the books in my cell, below the bench. Please say goodbye to my parents for me, I don't dare tell them myself. And to my friends, to S.P.H.E.W. and my army. Thank you for everything, Harry. You were always my best friend. I'm sorry."

"No! Wait!" Harry shouted, but the Patronus had already turned back and disappeared, it hadn't been instructed to wait for an answer.

He turned to her, then. "We've got to do something! I didn't mean for her to kill herself, that was my job, damn it!"

She was shaken and struggled for words, but she kept calm. "This seems a bit over my head." What could she do to stop the girl, from here? "Expecto Patronum." The silver cat appeared.

"Go to Professor Dumbledore, and tell him: An emergency has come up. I need you here immediately."

The Patronus blasted back into the cell, and said in a strange voice, which she guessed might be her own: "Harry potter says: No!"

She shook. She was scared. The wand slipped from her fingers, and the Patronus went out, leaving only the lesser light of the badger.

Caw? the phoenix asked.

She bent down and picked up the wand again. This was no time for hesitation. The other prisoners needed her. She took a deep breath, pushed aside all those fears, and forced down the sick feeling in her stomach. The last seconds of her life ticked away as she called back the will to protect everyone, pictured the bright world that they could make – perhaps she wouldn't be part of it, but this first step would contribute – and pointed her wand at the wall.

"Finite Incantatem."

With an enormous crash, the metal fell onto the floor before her.

She grabbed the phoenix's tail in her left hand, bent down low enough to fit through the hole, and launched herself off the edge. As she fell – the phoenix soaring down together with her, bringing her right over the center of the pit, the unmitigated fear of more than a hundred Dementors washed over her, but she was not afraid. She pointed her wand straight down.

"Expecto Patronum!"

And the world exploded in a burst of silver light.

Tick.

Tick.

It was taking too long, every second's delay might mean it was already too late...

Tick.

And then a burst of flame announced Dumbledore's arrival in the office.

"Professor, we need to get to Hermione now! She's going to destroy all Dementors, and she'll die, and I have to help!"

Albus Dumbledore didn't argue, he just grabbed the boy by the arm, and with a burst of fire they were in Azkaban. There was a small hole in the wall, just enough for a child to fit through if she curled up. And on the other side of the hole –

Harry didn't hesitate. He scrambled down to the floor, pointed his wand right at the center of the supernova outside, and yelled "Somnium!"

The light disappeared.

Li jumped back from his chair as suddenly light flooded in through the window. Silvery light, as though from a Patronus, but outside...

"What the –" Bahry exclaimed, and then they all jumped back as the light burst through the window, shining like the sun, and they could not see, but they could hear it all too clearly.

Phoenix song.

The light almost blinded Li even with his eyes shut tight, he could feel it on his skin, and his heart filled with joy and release at the light and the song. It was terror and beauty, joy and agony, as he fell to the floor and lay there for long seconds, his whole being vibrating with the song.

And then, almost as suddenly as they had come, the light and the song both cut off.

All three Aurors were lying on the ground. They looked at each other in confusion.

It was Gerard McCusker who first ran to the window and looked down. He turned back to them in a confused horror. "Where have they gone?" But Li had already known. Something felt... right that had always been wrong when he was here.

"I'm calling Director Bones," Bahry One-hand grunted. "Call back your Patronus, Mike. She'll probably be here five seconds after I give the alarm."

The light disappeared.

There was no feeling of emptiness.

Behind him, Dumbledore was casting incantations in something that sounded like Latin, and then he grabbed underneath the bench, and Harry saw the cloak and pouch appear in the old man's hands.

"The Dementors are gone. I do not sense them anymore," the Headmaster said. From the folds of his robes, he produced a broomstick somehow, which he made invisible with a wave of his wand and pushed into Harry's hands. Then he threw the cloak over him. "Go. Go now, while they are too preoccupied with Miss Granger and the other prisoners to notice you. Use the portkey in your game of cards when you're a few miles away, after twenty minutes or so. Then let whoever is there help you get back to my office in Hogwarts, and meet me there half an hour ago. I will take care of this."

Harry looked out of the small hole, towards where Hermione was lying. Was that... a phoenix by her side? But Dumbledore was right, he should hurry. He could find out the truth later. "Don't change her memories."

"Her memories will betray that she had your cloak, and that will implicate you."

"So be it. A large part of her personality ties in to her brilliant memory, and the things she learned in the last two weeks might be important. She's already got two fake memories, I don't want any more of that stuff in her head. If she cannot rely on her memories, it might destroy her!"

"Very well. But now go."

He went. Nobody saw, or stopped him.

Albus Dumbledore cast a few spells to weaken the protections on the pouch, and carefully placed it back beneath the bench. Then he turned himself and Fawkes invisible, widened the gap in the wall briefly to pass through, and let the phoenix fly him to the window of the Aurors' Headquarters two levels up. The room was already filling up with people, Auror after Auror entering through the cabinet. He selected a suitable trio of not-overly-experienced Aurors, quietly flew right behind them, and turned visible with a burst of fake flame.

Wands turned on him. "Hold your fire," Amelia Bones's voice commanded. "I was wondering whether we'd be seeing you here, when I got the message less than a minute after you were called away."

"The Potter boy warned me," he explained simply. "He said he had information that Miss Granger might be about to do something very foolish."

Chapter 98: Nihil Supernum, Pt 5 – Aftermaths

Hermione stood doubtfully before the gargoyles.

After catching on fire and blazing up in the mostly abandoned Great Hall (that had been a pretty wonderful experience – far better than the portkeys the Aurors had used to transport her from and to the Ministry), Professor McGonagall had gone to her office while Harry led her and his parents to a pleasant little apartment she hadn't seen before. There, they had had lunch (lunchtime was over, but Professor McGonagall had promised to have food sent over there anyway). Hermione had been bursting with questions, but with Harry's parents there, she didn't dare ask them. Dr. Verres-evans and Mrs. Evans-Verres were obviously trying to project confidence towards their son, but it was abundantly clear that they had been pretty shocked by the whole situation. So she and Harry had gently filled a little conversation with talk about phoenixes and their abilities (Harry's father had seemed rather interested in the idea of using phoenixes for space travel, and had made a number of interesting suggestions), and then left afterwards so the two adults could have their breakdown in peace.

Harry had proposed going to Professor Dumbledore with her, but then Vincent Crabbe had come and ordered Harry to "da boss". She wasn't invited and couldn't come along to say thank you (she'd have to find a way to do that afterwards, preferably in private as he might not want to be seen associating too much with a Muggleborn), so she'd gone to Dumbledore's office on her own.

But the gargoyles, she realized, had not been informed of the appointment, and she didn't know the password. Should she go to Professor McGonagall, or –

She looked at Xare, who cawed in agreement. You couldn't Apparate or Disapparate in Hogwarts, but phoenixes did not seem to be subject to such restrictions. She pictured the end of the spiraling stairway in her mind, right before the door, and grabbed the phoenix's claw. One burst of flame later, she stood at the place she had imagined, and knocked. The door instantly swung open.

The Headmaster of Hogwarts, Chief Warlock of the Wizengamot and Supreme Mugwump of the International Confederation of Wizards was sitting behind his desk, a twinkle in his eyes.

"Ah, Miss Granger," he said brightly. "Do come in. I was wondering whether you would use the door or simply come straight into the office."

"That wouldn't exactly be polite," Hermione answered, as she stepped inside and the door automatically closed behind her. She sat down into the deep, fluffy chair that was placed on the other side of the desk.

"Indeed it would not, but those of us who enjoy the company of a phoenix do not always observe such niceties. Now..." Some of his earlier seriousness returned. "Has Mr. Potter already informed you of the events which have occurred in the last two weeks?"

"No," she shook her head. "we were with his parents, you see, and..."

"They have quite enough to be going on with, yes. Well, then I suppose I shall give you the rough overview. Miss Granger, Lord Voldemort didn't really die when he attacked Mr. Potter some ten years ago. I knew he could not have – there were many reasons to believe that he had taken precautions against physical death, and is effectively immortal until we find out how to negate those precautions – but have kept it a secret to avoid widespread panic. I also hoped that the respite would be long enough to rebuild our world and increase our strengths before the next war comes, although I fear it may have come too soon. The man you know as Quirinius Quirrell was in fact the shade of Lord Voldemort, possessing the body of what I suspect was initially a willing victim. Since Harry realized the connection last week, Professor Quirrell has fled the school and gone on to terrorize Muggles, by sending an army of Inferi against a town in Scotland and by attacking all children and teachers in a primary school in Wales. Hundreds of Muggles have died in the last week, and almost a thousand have been severely wounded or permanently maimed, while I have honestly no clue as to what his purpose is. He was, of course, also behind the event that had you sent to Azkaban, which, given that he saved Mr. Malfoy's life, seems to have been solely aimed at you – or rather, at manipulating Harry by putting you in danger. Oh, and before I forget, there is a prophecy that identifies Harry as Voldemort's destined enemy, who will grow up to be his equal, and will have power he knows not."

She blinked. "That's rather a lot to take in at once."

"I do apologize for burdening you with this, Miss Granger. However, whether you wish it or not, you are involved now. Lord Voldemort has chosen to use you twice. What is more, as the second person in our country with a phoenix – and, indeed, the first without a tainted history – people will look to you for protection."

It was a little too much. War? Hundreds of deaths? And Professor Quirrell being Voldemort? She knew all about the last war, of course. Everyone did. The idea of all that starting over was terrifying. And Dumbledore expected her to take a lead in the fight?

But she could see, in her mind's eye, a town full of Muggles getting slaughtered by Inferi. She could see the faces of her Housemates, who almost never spoke of their family because there was always someone in earshot who'd lost someone dear to them. And she could imagine Hannah, and Parvati, and Hufflepuff Mike and even some people she only knew by face, and the idea of any of them getting hurt was just too terrible and of course she'd do what she could to stop that, but what could she do... Xare nuzzled her face affectionately.

No savior hath the savior...

"I'm only twelve," she whispered desperately.

"And yet you are a hero, Miss Granger," he said with a sad smile. "And always will be."

"What would you have me do?"

"Nothing, for now. I merely wished you to be prepared for the inevitable. Ultimately, this battle truly is Harry's, for he is Voldemort's destined enemy. But he could never be everywhere at once, and other heroes will be needed. As for the present, there are different concerns. I believe Harry's book list for you contained an introductory text on Occlumency?"

"Yes," she answered. This seemed like safer ground. "But I didn't get very far. These exercises seem really hard."

"I would not expect you to succeed them so quickly. In fact, you are too young. Occlumency lessons are generally not attempted before the age of fifteen at least. But in your case, it is dangerous that you cannot hide your thoughts. Therefore, we should perhaps arrange something after all."

"But if I can't learn it yet..."

"I sincerely doubt that you will be able to succeed a complete block, at your age. But with enough training, you may be able to detect intrusion, and that will already be helpful. The question is how to train you. We went to quite some lengths not to spread any knowledge of the secret revealed in today's proceedings beyond those who can use it to cast the spell. Unfortunately, anyone teaching you Legilimency would certainly learn of all you least wish to be known –"

That didn't sound particularly pleasant, even if she wasn't trying to hide anything important.

"– so whichever instructor we find for you must agree to be Obliviated afterwards." He looked briefly tired. "But that would not suffice, would it?"

Her thoughts flashed back to the panicked look on the face of the Obliviated Auror, Shacklebolt, when he failed to recast his Patronus the first time.

"How about someone who was at the trial?" she suggested. "They couldn't be harmed further."

The Headmaster shook his head. "I would gladly teach you myself, Miss Granger, but that must not be. Remember that two pieces of information were removed by the Aurors after the trial. One, the secret that will curse you to be forever unable to cast a Patronus Charm. The other, the way of casting the True Patronus Charm. If I should learn the former, then the latter will be unlocked, and that a simple half-hour Obliviation would not remove. Taking into account that the agreement we made crucially relies on everyone accepting the Obliviation, Lucius Malfoy would not be pleased if he learned that I had been told the secret afterwards." He sighed. "A flaw which I really should have considered at the time."

"I see." She thought about it. "So it would need to be someone who wasn't at the trial, and who already cannot cast the Patronus Charm."

"Would that be enough?" He asked.

"Yes, I think so. If he or she gets Obliviated afterwards, at least."

The Headmaster nodded. "Very well, I shall arrange that." He extended a hand to Xare, who, after a questioning look at her, hopped gently onto his hand. "Now. About your family... Harry has insisted that his parents stay here, for their protection. I did not believe it necessary at first, but on closer consideration, he might well be right. However, I am quite certain that yours are not in a similar danger."

Danger? "Would V– You-Know-Who attack them?"

"No, I don't think so. He stands little to gain from attacking them – his interest seems to be focused on Harry, and Harry, I believe, would not be severely affected by your parents' deaths. You have been targeted, but only for Harry's sake. I will ward your parents, of course, in as unobtrusive a way as possible. But I don't think it would be in their best interests to uproot their lives."

A cold hand of fear clasped around her heart as the Headmaster spoke so calmly of her parents being murdered. She took a deep breath, then another, forcing herself to consider his words rather than protesting immediately. It hadn't even occurred to her that her parents might be in danger. Even if it had, she wouldn't have considered asking for them to stay here before the Headmaster brought it up. If anything, she'd try to persuade them to leave the country, but they would lose all their clients if they just left on short notice, so it was very unlikely that she could convince them that they were in enough danger to do that – especially since, according to the Headmaster, they weren't.

She swallowed. "What kinds of wards?"

"The strongest I can provide for them. I shall ward them myself, before the day is through. They will have emergency portkeys and methods to give warning to either me or the Auror office – that much I can do without giving them undue alarm, as a safety measure after the attacks in Easingwold – and numerous invisible wards and detection of any magic in their vicinity. I promise that they will be as safe as I can make them."

"All right then," Hermione sighed. "Can I see them?"

Professor Dumbledore looked uncomfortable. "You can, certainly... but whether it's a good idea –"

"What do you mean?"

The old wizard gently rubbed the firebird's beak. "With a phoenix, few places in the world are closed to you, so yes, you are able to visit your parents if you so wished. However, I do urge you to be cautious. While they are not likely targets, you are, and therefore in leaving the protection of the Hogwarts wards to visit them, you might inadvertently endanger them. What is more, you are in the unenviable position of not being able to be honest with your parents without giving them great alarm. Can you envision how they would respond if they should learn of the dangers you have faced, and may still be facing?"

"They'd be terrified," she breathed. They'd want to take her away from Hogwarts, from magic. If they learned the full story, they definitely wouldn't want her anywhere near Harry. They might well try pulling her out of school against her will. She could stop that by filing for independence with the Ministry of Magic, but she couldn't do that without effectively losing her parents.

"I see you comprehend the danger," the Headmaster spoke after a pause. "Miss Granger, this decision is truly yours. Your parents have been told that you are sick with Spattergroit – a highly infectious disease, which keeps them from visiting you, and which would have explained your death if your sentence had ended differently. You might choose to continue the deception, or to reveal the lie to them; that decision is entirely between you and your parents. However, whichever path you follow, you must not act rashly. Weigh your options before you take a step."

"I will." Maybe she could find someone to talk to about this. Were there other Muggleborns who'd been in situations like this? There had to be, surely, there'd been a war only ten years ago and Muggleborns had been targets. But none of those were people she knew, or whom she could easily approach with questions.

For the first time ever, she really wished that she had a magical relative, an adult. Someone she could talk to about this sort of thing, who would understand what had happened and who knew the Muggle world and could give her advice. Hell, she'd even be happy with just someone she could talk to like she talked with her parents but who would be familiar with magic and all around it, who would know what Azkaban was and what a phoenix meant, someone who understood the world she lived in and wouldn't go mad with fear if she told them what had happened to her. Professor McGonagall was close, but she had many children to be responsible for, and it wasn't quite the same.

"What are you thinking of?" The Headmaster asked gently.

"I was wondering..." She looked at the ancient man, who had known her grandmother, spent months with her. "You were a friend of Elizabeth Beckett, weren't you?"

"Yes," he said sadly. "I do apologize for not telling you about her, but I felt it was not my place."

"Do you know whether I have other magical relatives?"

"None in Britain. John and Elizabeth were estranged from the rest of their family. There might be some distant relatives in America, but none that I would know how to find."

She nodded, only slightly disappointed. It had been a long shot anyway. "Do you have any pictures of my grandmother?"

He hesitated, but only briefly. Then he stood up. "Come."

Draco's face did not betray anything when Harry stepped into the otherwise abandoned classroom Crabbe had led him to. He could not guess what his friend was thinking. But he knew what he should say.

"Thank you."

Draco looked at him coldly.

"Thank you," Harry repeated. "You might well have saved my life as well as Hermione's today."

"I didn't do it for you," Draco said with a slight sneer to his voice. "I did it for Granger."

Now that was something you wouldn't expect to hear every day from that particular direction.

I'm sorry, Harry did not say, because he wasn't, and still he had to stop himself from blurting it out. Today, Draco Malfoy had stood up against his father to defend a Muggleborn, which would probably never have happened without Harry's manipulation, and that was a wonderful event that might well reshape the future political landscape of magical Britain, but Harry could only imagine what it might have cost the boy.

"You swore enmity on my house," Draco said, his voice controlled.

Oh. Right. He had totally forgotten about that.

"Draco, I'm sorry. I didn't mean it! It was just... I was trying to find anything to say that would stop your father from sending Hermione to Azkaban."

"And you honestly thought that would work?"

"Your father seemed scared of me. It was the only thing I could think of then. I'm sorry, I wasn't thinking properly."

There was a brief look of consternation on Draco's face, as though he was remembering something relevant. But then his features turned cool again.

"My father asked me to suggest that we dismiss the enmity between our Houses. Do you accept?"

"Of course."

"Very well. I shall let him know."

"Draco..."

"I won't consider you my enemy anymore. But let's get one more part straight." Draco was staring at him now, a fierce light in his eyes. "You wronged me. And you owe me."

"Acknowledged," Harry said quietly. "Conditional on the rest of it, of course."

Draco nodded. Then his face relaxed.

"Speaking of debts," he said in an artificially light tone. "Have you determined whether Dumbledore deserves your enmity yet?"

"Actually," Harry answered, "I wanted to talk to you about that."

"You're not going to chicken out on me, are you?"

"No. The thing is... I have made progress. I asked him about the things you told me – well, not about his sister, that would just be too personal, but the other stuff – and he had some surprisingly good explanations..."

"Good explanations?" Draco repeated incredulously. The anger seeped from his voice.

"I'm not saying – look. About the Grindelwald thing..." he paused a moment, giving Draco time to calm down.

Dumbledore had told him that Grindelwald had a dread device that made him truly invincible – at least while his Muggle pawns were providing him with blood sacrifices. Without those sacrifices, his defenses had still been impenetrable even by the most powerful wizard alive.

And Harry had a pretty good idea what that dread device was.

He'd felt it, when he held Dumbledore's wand. The sheer power running through his fingers. Another man's wand was supposed to be less powerful than your own, but this one felt somehow right, even as there was the sense that it was not his...

The feeling reminded him a lot of his cloak.

He had not recognized the dark wood, which meant that it could well be elder, a very unusual material for wands. And if Dumbledore possessed the elder wand, the Deathly Hallow that was supposed to increase its wielder's spell power by a thousandfold, making him or her truly undefeatable, there was one obvious place where he might have got it. Grindelwald could not be defeated with spells alone. His shields unbreakable, his attacks immeasurably powerful. But while Dumbledore could dodge Grindelwald's spells, and keep attacking to drain his magical power, eventually exhaustion would set in. It was, quite possibly, the only flaw of the unbeatable wand.

And Dumbledore had asked him not to speak of it, for none must suspect that he possessed the device in question. And that made sense too, as there were probably a lot of wizards who would happily murder him in his sleep for it, or else attempt to steal it. And it would be dangerous, for such a person to hold such a wand. Much safer to keep it in Dumbledore's hands who was, at least, not trying to use it against other people.

"He gave me an explanation, but he made me swear not to tell anyone."

"Oh, come on."

"I wasn't sure whether to believe him at first, but I have seen proof since. On my art as a rationalist, I promise that by my best judgment, I think he was telling the truth: he had a very good reason to postpone his attack, he really did fight until Grindelwald fell over in exhaustion, and he also has a good reason not to speak of it."

Draco frowned, but he seemed to consider the words at their value, at least.

"I'm not sure what to think of that."

"And you shouldn't be," Harry shrugged. "I can promise you that I judged as best as I could, but it's perfectly reasonable to want to see the evidence with your own eyes rather than just taking my word for it. That's what scientists do. But at least this should tell you that an alternative explanation exists, and that it can seem convincing enough to at least mild scrutiny by a rational person."

Draco nodded, his mouth a thin line. "And the rest of it?"

Careful now. If it was difficult for Harry to objectively assess the morality of torturing an innocent to death for cool utilitarian considerations, it would be a lot harder for Draco, whose mother had been said innocent.

"Did your father ever tell you about the circumstances of... your mother's death? I mean, did he tell you why Dumbledore said he did that?"

"Dumbledore just told him it was a warning." Draco's voice broke. "A warning! What kind of warning is that?"

"But your father never told you what the warning was for?"

"What does it matter? He just wanted to hurt father! He's evil!" The last words came out as a scream.

"People don't usually do evil just for the sake of evil, Draco. And Dumbledore has a phoenix, he can't do evil without at least believing that it serves a noble purpose, don't you see? If he just... If he killed your mother for revenge on your father or some other petty reason, Fawkes would leave him! So if he really did it, he has to have had a reason, that was enough that he could at least convince himself that it was worth it."

Draco was breathing heavily. "Like. What?" He glared at Harry. "How can you even consider that there is a good reason for that?"

"Draco..." Harry looked him in the eyes. "How many innocents has your father tortured to death, or delivered into Voldemort's hands for that purpose?"

Draco gasped and stepped back, as though hit by a physical blow. "That is... I don't... That was not the same thing at all and you know it!"

"Isn't it?" Harry spread his hands helplessly. "Consider the reverse situation. Suppose Dumbledore didn't just take your mother, but he burned other relatives of Death Eaters as well, and his friends helped him do that... And then suppose your father got the wife of one of those friends in his hands..."

"Stop." Draco had turned his face away. There was a sob in his voice.

Harry fell silent. He wasn't mad or cruel enough to push his friend. What he'd just done to him was bad enough.

It was a while before Draco spoke again.

"That does sound an awful lot like revenge."

Harry shook his head. "It was a standoff. You-Know-Who and the Death Eaters had no qualm hurting the families of those who resisted them, because they believed Dumbledore would never retaliate in kind."

Draco just stood there, his back still turned to Harry.

"I don't know whether he did it," Harry said eventually. It was a risk, perhaps, to raise this possibility, for if Lord Malfoy would come to believe that Dumbledore had lied it would endanger light-side families again. But surely Voldemort would have thought of this too, and he had accepted the standoff. "He had every motive to take the credit if someone else did it. Or maybe he killed her, but he didn't burn her, and he just faked the evidence."

Draco shook his head. "No."

After a while, he turned around. His face looked a bit red, but otherwise coolly controlled.

"He still owes us a debt, no matter how good his reasons might have been. So, are you taking him as your enemy or not?"

"I still don't know whether he did it, Draco," Harry pointed out. "I know why he did it, if he did it. But –" (as the boy started looking angry again) "I have taken first steps towards taking him as my enemy. I don't accept him as my mentor, or follow his little plans. And I don't trust his judgment. Frankly, I was rather peeved when he stopped me from buying Hermione free, and that's just one example. Is that enough, for now?"

Draco just looked at him.

"I don't think I am ready to deliberately go and destabilize him, even if I could," Harry clarified. Draco seemed to be demanding more, but that, Harry was not quite ready to give yet. "I don't like what your father is doing very much either, and whatever else, Dumbledore does put a check on him. Also, he is legally my guardian and he could make my life really difficult, if he wanted to." That, and I may need his help to deal with the Voldemort problem. I don't think Lucius Malfoy would be as co-operative, even if I did help him get rid of Dumbledore."

"Go," Draco said softly.

"Draco –"

"Just go."

He went.

A deep silence clung to this room, a stark contrast to the office below. A crystal globe hung on the ceiling, casting a silver light over the black walls and floor. And below that, rows upon rows of pedestals with photos, broken wands and other objects. Her breath stopped in her throat as her mind refused to process what she was seeing.

"What is this place?" she whispered, although most of her already knew.

"Think of it as a graveyard," the Headmaster answered.

No, she thought, not a graveyard. This was far more than that, for, she suspected, he had known every single one of the people here. Godric Gryffindor might have had a room like this, for the many friends he had lost in battle. But she had never thought of Albus Dumbledore in that way, and it almost broke her heart to see the kind old hero here among the keepsakes of the fallen. He had done so much, and lost so many.

"Come." He strode through the pedestals, and with only a little hesitation she followed him, until they reached –

She blinked. Upon the pedestal where he stopped was a picture of herself, not moving, because it was the one she recognized as her last school photo before Hogwarts. Beside the photo lay her wand, unbroken. He took it, and silently handed it to her.

"I suppose this pedestal will not be needed anymore," he said matter-of-factly, taking the picture and putting it somewhere into a pocket of his robes. Then he tapped the pedestal with his wand and it sunk down into the ground. He stepped to the side, leading her to the pedestal next to this one, which bore a single photo and a cylinder.

"This," he said, "is your grandmother."

The woman in the picture was about thirty years old. Short of stature, she thought (although it was hard to tell in a photo) and a bit squatty, with black hair hanging loosely down her back. She seemed kind, even though there was a strong, unyielding expression in those dark-brown eyes.

There was no wand on the pedestal, not even a broken one. Most other pedestals did hold a wand, and Dumbledore had been with her when she died, hadn't he? That was what he had told her before, when speaking of his battle against Grindelwald: fewer remember Elizabeth Beckett who died opening the way so I could pass through. Had another relative inherited it? Or...

"What happened to her wand?" she asked. Her voice came out sounding almost normal.

"It was shattered," Dumbledore says simply.

But he doesn't say when, she noted. Had Elizabeth Beckett lost her wand in the battle where her brother died, and later fought with his wand in place of her own? She almost asked whether he would consider himself a friend of the family, but she knew better than to do that. She was not an Occlumens yet, and if the Headmaster was the one who had helped Harry help her, it would be better for her not to know.

She looked at the picture again, wondering about the woman she had never known, but with whom she still felt a connection. What had she been like? Gryffindor, Head Girl, brilliant scholar and extremely brave. But those were just words, it still didn't let her know her.

"Come," the Headmaster said gently. "It does not do to dwell on the past. We had better live in the present, and I believe you have more than enough present concerns."

That was certainly true. She nodded, and allowed him to steer her away, down the stairs, back to office where Xare waited for her on Fawkes's golden podium.

Draco was lying in his bed, silent tears streaming over his face.

It wasn't fair.

Why did Harry keep doing this? Wasn't it enough that he'd taken Draco's belief in blood purity, did he have to whittle away at his grasp of good and evil too?

The painful thing, the horrible thing was that a part of him realized that the Boy-Who-Lived was right. He had always envisioned Dumbledore's acts against his mother as senseless cruelty, but of course they weren't just that; it had been a war, both sides fighting for what they believed in. If he was completely honest with himself, Dumbledore hadn't done any evils, as far as he knew, that father would not have done in his place. Even killing his sister – if a Squib girl was born in the Malfoy family, it was not at all inconceivable that she would have an accident before anyone ever found out about it. And the thing with Grindelwald... he didn't think father could have pulled that one off, but if he could get away with it, he would have, and Harry had seemed quite certain that Dumbledore hadn't even done that anyway.

And yet of course, obviously Dumbledore was evil. But if you started thinking like that, you had to wonder about Lucius Malfoy too...

Draco sobbed, and cursed the day in Diagon Alley when he first met Harry Potter.

"Mum. Dad. What are your plans?"

It hadn't been long after his meeting with Draco that Harry had realized that there was a very important thing he had forgotten to discuss. Excitement of the day notwithstanding, tomorrow classes in Oxford would start again and Professor Verres-Evans might be tempted to return to work. So Harry had quickly aborted his stride towards the Ravenclaw common room, and turned into the corridor that led to his parents' apartment instead.

"We're staying here," mother answered.

"Oh, that's great," Harry said with a surge of relief. "You believe in the danger now, then?"

"Your Headmaster was here just a few minutes ago," father said. "Apparently he's already arranged for me to have had a severe 'accident' while on holiday in Canada. I am now apparently staying in a private clinic there, and it will expectedly take at least until the end of the semester before I am fully recovered." He shrugged. "It would have been more polite if he'd asked us first whether we agreed with the arrangement, but it seems that I'm now on sick leave for the rest of the school year, and I don't mind that. Today's events have made me realize that, well, you appear to be caught up in something larger than I would have expected, and whether your mother and I are in danger or not, we'd both prefer to be here to support you when necessary."

"Thanks, Dad," Harry sad. "And Mum. It does mean a lot to me." Knowing that his parents were as safe as Dumbledore could make them was helpful, although not quite enough to not worry about their safety at all. But if Voldemort could break into the school, then he could also hurt Hermione, or Draco, or any of his other friends, so at least he didn't need to be more worried for his parents than for all the other people he cared about.

"So I guess you'll be having a lot of time for research this semester, Dad? With no teaching duties to distract you?"

"No, actually," Professor Verres-Evans said. "Your Headmaster has offered your mother and me both positions as guest lecturers."

"What? What will you be teaching?"

"Muggle Studies," mother said. "I'll be telling third-years about daily life in Oxford and I'll give an introduction to law to the fourth-year students. Your father will teach some basic ideas of science to the sixth-years."

"Indeed," father added. "Apparently Professor McGonagall was intrigued with some of the ideas you told her about, even if she considered them quite absurd." He showed a brief smile. "I suppose I am going to have an interesting time with this."

"Oh yes." Harry answered, a gleam in his eyes as he imagined the primarily pureblood students getting introduced to ideas such as a court system where innocent until proven guilty applied, or learning about questioning your beliefs and the experimental method. He was pretty sure the Headmaster was planning to shake the students up a little, at least where his mother was concerned. Perhaps Dumbledore had only intended for his father to explain the results of science, but Harry knew him too well to doubt the lesson plan. "You two are going to be awesome."

In his office, the Headmaster of Hogwarts spun his Time-Turner four times, and set off to find Padma Patil. If anyone would benefit from being told how to send a Patronus to someone else, and at what time doing so might just be a good idea, the girl whom Harry Potter had named his heir was probably it.

When Hermione entered the Great Hall for the after-holiday feast, Xare riding on her shoulder, there was a sudden hush.

Everyone turned to stare at her.

And then the applause started.

It started at the Gryffindor table, of course, but then the others joined in. Ravenclaw, Hufflepuff... Even a fair few Slytherins were clapping, which surprised her briefly until she realized that of course several of the children in that House had relatives in Azkaban.

She arrived at the Ravenclaw table and sat down next to Su. Harry, who had apparently walked in right after her, sank down on her other side.

"I'm glad you're back," Padma said from where she was sitting on the opposite side of the table.

"So am I," she said. And she was, even as she suppressed a brief note of sadness because nothing ever would be the same again. She had gone to Azkaban and returned with a phoenix. There was a war going on, and sooner or later she might be called upon to protect her friends as well as strangers. The days of plotting battle tactics against Harry and Draco, caring about house points and telling everyone that Harry was not her boyfriend were over. But still, it was good to be back home at Hogwarts.

Harry got the Slytherin delivery after dinner, and read it later inside his trunk.

I did it.

-LL

Chapter 100: Lost Innocence

(April 20th 1992, 7:30am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 1)

DEMENTORS ARE A PHYSICAL EMBODIMENT OF DEATH. YOU CANNOT FIGHT THEM ANYMORE. YOU CANNOT RUN. TODAY, THEY WILL ATTACK. PREPARE TO DIE.

The words slammed into Hermione's consciousness. She winced, and then winced again as she realized the implications.

They have no consciousness of their own, Harry had said earlier. They will act as people expect them to do. People thought they could make deals, and that's why it worked. And she had known that it was true. Attacking the members of the Wizengamot, rather than the two prisoners, had not been in the interest of yesterday's Dementor – but it had done so because everyone expected it to. And in January when the Dementor had spoken to her, she had been afraid for Harry and distrustful of Professor Quirrell, and it had told her exactly what, deep down, she expected to hear. And in speaking those words she had set expectations too, which might have been part of what had given the Dementor its power over Harry afterwards.

With these words, Professor Quirrell – Lord Voldemort – had perfectly set up the expectation that Dementors would attack. And that would make them act. Even far away from wizards, Muggles who had never known about Dementors would fear them. They would expect death to come for them, and therefore, come it would.

Almost on the instant of the message, two pictures with notes attached appeared in the air and drifted down. Alastor grabbed, read, and then thrust one to Barnok, and the other to her.

"Two people to Russia, two to France."

Madam Bones had explained that in the early minutes of the hour, sometimes they would be sent somewhere together, as there were places with too many Dementors for one person to expectedly handle – Albus Dumbledore had suggested that Hermione's destruction of Azkaban had nearly killed her, so chances were that this was approximately the maximum size a single True Patronus-caster could handle with the help of a phoenix. So, they had agreed that Harry and Hermione, who both had experience destroying Dementors, would ideally split up at least the first time, and help Padma and Lesath, who had not.

They wasted no time. Barnok and Sally both looked at the photo and then grabbed Harry and Lesath and disappeared in equal bursts of flame. Hermione took the hand of the strange, pock-marked man, stared briefly at the picture, and then passed it to Tamara before envisioning the place. She touched Xare's claw, and an instant later they were in the building of the picture, with dark-blue walls, and wizards running in terror. Only seconds had passed since the announcement, and the guards of this Dementor-prison had just seen their Patronuses pop. Fear and cold burst around them like a whirlwind.

"Aaah!" Padma screamed, but Hermione wasted no time. Any second now, a Dementor might catch one of the guards, and these were Dementors with reason to be really, really angry. Pushing all her will to protect towards her hand, she raised her wand. "Expecto Patronum."

Padma followed the example, failing at first, but on the second try the Patronus did come. She still looked shaky, however.

"Don't let the fear get to you," Hermione urged. "Think of it as – as five seventh-year bullies coming at you with wands out. Sure, you're afraid, but that wouldn't stop you from trying to hex them."

Padma nodded. "Now how do we do this?" The two Patronuses were blocking the Dementors' progress, but it wouldn't stop the effect from filtering out in other directions.

"Just want to destroy them. Let go of your restraints." As she spoke, she did so, her Patronus growing. Padma followed suit.

The phoenixes sang, and cried on them. It was a marvelous moment as they felt all Dementors in the dome dissolve one by one, as the French guards stared at them in bafflement. It was like Azkaban had been, but better, because they were doing it together.

Alastor Moody nudged her. "Stop." He was wearing dark spectacles. The Dementors must be gone; no need to protect these people further. She willed her Patronus to dim again, and beside her, saw Padma do the same.

"That was wonderful," the other witch sighed.

"I'm glad you like it," Moody grunted. "Because you'll be doing it until you fall over in exhaustion. Let's get back to the Ministry for the next task."

(April 20th 1992, 7:30am and 20 seconds, the Russian Dementor containment park)

"The fear is not natural!" Harry yelled at Lesath. "It's just your enemy trying to make you afraid! You can destroy them first!"

The boy had fallen over at the first wave of despair – which Harry could hardly blame him for, it had been far worse even than the lower levels of Azkaban – but now a determined look crossed his face, and he tried casting again (Harry kept his Patronus away from Lesath, of course – if he couldn't cast the spell under these conditions, he shouldn't be doing this).

"Those people, Lesath. They are good people. They need us. Help them."

"Expecto Patronum?"

It sounded hesitant, and the Patronus came slowly, but it came. And when it was there, it grew.

"Well done, Lesath."

"Thank you, my –" he turned it into a cough. "Harry."

"And now... let go of your barriers. Pour everything into the spell. But make sure you can stop when they tell us to."

And so he did, sending the silvery feelings out into a joyful burst of light. He had imagined what this would be like, before. Dreamed so often of going to Azkaban and just letting go and burning away every last Dementor in that dreaded place. He had cursed himself over and over for not taking the chance when the phoenix came to him, when he could have gone and survived. And now he was finally doing it. He wasn't sure whether this place was also used as some kind of human prison or was just there to block Dementors – given the lack of walls he suspected that there had been some kind of deal with these Dementors at least – but it didn't matter. Dementors should not exist. And after today, they wouldn't.

Barnok, the Ethiopian phoenix owner who was accompanying him, shook him, and Harry let go of his wand. The light winked out; Lesath had stopped before him. All around them lay the tattered cloaks of over a hundred Dementors.

"Didn't you hear me?" Barnok asked.

Harry shook his head, slightly embarrassed that Lesath had managed to control himself better than he had. "I was too much into the spell. Sorry."

"Let's go," Sally suggested, and she and Lesath disappeared again.

(April 20th 1992, 7:32am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 1)

The instant Pamda and Hermione reappeared in the DMLE, a note was already fluttering down. Alastor Moody grabbed it. "Two people, India."

At that moment, Harry and Lesath appeared again, and Padma just saw two new notes appearing before she, Hermione, Alastor and Tamara burned up.

(April 20th 1992, 7:33am, the Indian Dementor-villlage)

They arrived at a dreary-looking village, surrounded by forests. It was mid-afternoon, but despite the lack of clouds it didn't seem sunny, here.

The Auror's crazy blue eye rolled around in its socket even as the brown eye looked at her. "Other side," he ordered, and a new image was pushed into her mind.

She obeyed, and they reappeared at a different part of the village, close to vegetable fields and rows of fruit-bearing trees. Here, the feeling of dread was worse by a tenfold. People were here, Muggles by their looks, but weak, scrawny. Some were shouting, or running back towards the village. Some had fallen over, just holding up their hands to ward off an invisible foe. And from the forest, the sense of fear and despair was increasing, as the Dementors who apparently surrounded this village in large numbers were closing in. Dumbledore had described places where Dementors were deliberately given Muggle victims to drain over time, and this seemed like it might be one of them. Those poor people...

In the distance, she already saw the burst of silver light as Padma had cast her spell. Hermione quickly followed suit. From today on, the people of this village would finally be free.

(April 20th 1992, 7:38am, Detroit, USA)

It was night, here. Nothing indicated that anything was wrong, except a deep, miserable feeling in the air. The note sending Padma and Tamara to this area of Detroit had been blue, indicating that Dementors were known to live around here, but that their exact location was unknown.

She raised her wand and cast the spell again. And yes, now she felt them. There were several, in the weathered buildings around her. She held on while she felt them, and then lowered her wand, nodded to Tamara, and flamed off to receive her next assignment.

(April 20th 1992, 7:41am, a small settlement in Australia)

Hermione had cast the Patronus spell the instant Xare brought her here, but they had arrived too late to stop it, and the few moments before the Patronus appeared had been enough to see.

Some man, terrified, batting wildly at the air as a Dementor grabbed him and placed itself over his mouth. In that single instant, just before she could help, the eyes changed from terrified to utterly dead and empty.

She wanted to cry out, but she needed all her concentration to hold on to the Patronus, to protect the other people here, and so she forced herself to protect everyone, and not let herself see those empty eyes again in her imagination until the last Dementor was gone. And then her wand slipped from her fingers as a sob rose in her throat.

This place had been on a purple note: Dementors expected (they probably lived in the forest area around), but likely too far away to need to go for them immediately. And that, it seemed, had been a miscalculation.

The man who had been taken right before her eyes had only been one of the victims. Behind him, she saw others, many others, their empty bodies still standing or even walking, but all with those same horrid dead eyes.

A hand was laid on her shoulder and her wand thrust back into her hand. "Hermione... We must go on." The voice was gentler than Alastor Moody had been so far, and this was the first time he called her by her first name.

She nodded, and looked out over the battlefield again. Besides the Dementor-Kissed, there were other people, moving carefully among the victims. Many had died, but more were still alive. And that was what it meant to be a hero too, she realized. It wasn't just doing scary things and going to Azkaban and dying for a greater good. It was also losing, losing badly, and going on anyway to help those who still lived.

Today was going to be horrible, she knew, as she held Moody's hand and touched Xare's claw to go back to London. But every single life that could be saved was worth fighting for.

(April 20th 1992, 7:46am, the temporary Dementor-crisis control chambers)

Amelia looked at the red note with a frown of worry. Already?

She was handling the distribution of assignments over the children in the six rooms. The other countries had agreed to trust her to take the lead, both because the children who could destroy Dementors were all British, and because she could be expected to be fair, as the United Kingdom and Ireland themselves were unlikely to be attacked (all their Dementors had been around Azkaban or in the Ministry). In the first minutes, she had sent them to all the large, controlled pockets whose control suddenly fell away. Those were done. Next were the locations of expected Dementor-pockets: most governments kept tabs on where Dementors hid out, even if they didn't explicitly capture or make deals with them, so Aurors of all countries had been Apparating around to check for the feel of Dementors.

A red note indicated a confirmed attack, but the frightening thing was the location. The note named a district in Lashio, Burma, and she was pretty sure that that city had not been on the list of expected places. Which meant that it hadn't been a priority to check out by Aurors and government officials, so this report must have come from someone noticing a Dementor without explicitly looking for it. And she had a pretty good idea of what might have caused them to notice. How long had it taken them to notify the right people in their Ministry?

She looked at the numbers of the six doors surrounding her. Someone had just arrived in the first room, so procedure called for her to send this assignment there. Poor child.

(April 20th 1992, 7:47am, Lashio, Burma)

As the light faded away, Harry stared at the carnage. People were running and screaming. A child was sobbing in a corner next to the vegetative empty hull that might have been its mother, once. Near the doors and on the stairs and escalators, the ground was slick with blood and gore, from the people who had been trampled in the mad panicking rush as everyone tried to flee the invisible horror. And all around, dead blank stares looked into space, from the faces of people who were just standing, or walking at random, or who had fallen over.

One Dementor had done this. Attracted by the shopping excitement of a Monday afternoon, and unrestrained by the threat of Patronus-captivity, the thing had entered a busy mall and gorged itself. It had not worn a cloak, and Muggles could not see Dementors, so the people had never seen the creature that was killing them. But they had felt it, and they had seen the effects.

"People are dying," he said hoarsely. He didn't know anyone here, but the blood and the limbs and the empty eyes shook him on a deep emotional level anyway. "Can you send your phoenix to the wounded?"

"No," the Ethiopian wizard sighed. "You are needed elsewhere. I am notifying the authorities to send a cleanup squad here. Other phoenixes can heal, today. We have different people to save."

(April 20th 1992, 7:51am, Hogwarts)

Michael was worried.

Harry hadn't come for breakfast, even thought he had said he would. Then there had been that strange voice in his mind, and he had suddenly remembered all that had been said at the trial. He had a strong feeling that Harry was wrapped up in this somehow, but nobody had come to explain, which could either mean that he was wrong or that whatever was going on was too serious to waste time on talking to some Muggles.

And so he had ventured out of the apartment and tried to find his way to the Great Hall. Petunia had not wanted to join, probably because she was far too sensible to risk getting lost in a magical castle, but you didn't become a university professor by avoiding risks. So Michael had gone alone, while Petunia stayed behind to raise the alarm if he would not return.

It wasn't even that hard. Their apartment was close to the Entrance Hall, and even when the staircase he tried to descend ended up in an entirely different place than where it had seemed to go when he started walking down, there was a remarkably helpful portrait to point him back on track. So it was only six minutes later that he stepped through the large open doorway into the Great Hall.

Students were scattered around the hall. A lot of the food on the four tables was left uneaten. There were shouts of "Expecto Patronum" everywhere, but no apparent results. Yes, he thought. Something definitely seems wrong.

Professor McGonagall walked towards him with a resolute step.

"Mr. Verres. I am so sorry, but we had quite forgotten about you in all the chaos."

"It's okay," he answered. "But what's going on? And where's my son?"

She told him.

"Ah." Michael considered the situation. His son was off saving the world. He should probably be more worried, but since yesterday the part of his brain in charge of estimating task difficulties was confused.

Little children grow up indeed. There didn't seem much point in trying to be a good, supportive father for a small child-going-on-teenager anymore. But perhaps he could still be an acceptable lackey to a young hero.

"Is there anything I can do to help?" he asked the Deputy Headmistress. She seemed hesitant, so he quickly added: "I think that if I had magic, I would be able to do that spell. Hermione's explanation resonated a lot better with me than it seemed to do with the other people yesterday."

Now she looked interested. "Do you also understand why you are different in that?"

He nodded. "It's a classical error of thinking, the belief that some realistic developments are just too good to be true. But I have a little more grounding in history, and I know where the human mind tends to go wrong."

She stared at him. "Can you teach us?"

(April 20th 1992, 7:59am, Almere, Netherlands)

The dark-haired goatee-wearing man, who had fallen over next to Lesath, looked a lot like he remembered his father. Father, who was now safe, whom he would get to visit and maybe even take care of.

Muggles were running and screaming, and unmitigated Dementor fear washed around him, but Lesath didn't care. It was unnatural, as Lord Harry Potter had said, and there was nothing to frighten him anymore. They could fix the world, together. This was just a part of it.

He looked at the terrified middle-aged man. Everything will be alright, dad.

"Expecto Patronum!"

Once more, the silver light fled from his wand, spreading over the sports stadium. He could feel it enveloping the people and touching those shadows of Death spread out over the place. Some of them were close, some of them were distant, but if he opened up enough, he could destroy them all.

The light brightened and brightened; even with his eyes closed it was intense, but he could feel them getting torn apart.

No more Dementors!

These monstrous creatures would never soil the earth with their presence again, they would never hurt anyone he cared about again!

He could almost feel the life leaving him, but he didn't care, he was doing what he needed to do...

(April 20th 1992, 8:00am, Almere, Netherlands)

Sally desperately clung to the fallen body of the boy she was supposed to be protecting.

Oh no. No no no no no.

She had been looking at the Dementors, not the boy, and so she had only realized what was happening when he fell. And yet more light had flown from his wand even as he was falling unconscious, so she had snatched it out of his hand, but it might already be too late...

Despair washed over her. The last, most distant Dementor was still there.

Shit!

In a burst of flame, she, the boy and the phoenix arrived at the entrance of the Dalton Magical Malady Center. She grabbed her mirror, barked to the responding Auror that someone else needed to get to Almere, and drew her wand.

"Innervate."

The boy did not stir.

"Vitalis Revelio," a Healer who had rushed over said, and Lesath Lestrange was surrounded by a weak pink-red glow. He was an inch from death, but he still lived.

Several incantations later, the Healer had determined that he was not in any real danger, but did need rest. The phoenix tears had stabilized him, but he had almost no life force left, and there was only so much even a phoenix could do. He was transported to one of the beds in a private ward.

"A few hours sleep should do the trick," the Healer promised. "And let your phoenix cry on him every ten minutes or so, that will speed it up. After that, I'd recommend a few days of minimal exertion."

Sally sighed. One down, three to go.

(April 20th 1992, 8:05am, Hogwarts)

"So you see," Michael concluded, "you are taught to accept certain 'facts of life'," (he made the airquotes, of course), "Seven centuries ago, people accepted that the only ways to preserve knowledge were to either learn it by heart, or hand-copy texts. A hundred years ago, no one would have believed that it was possible to go through childhood without contracting measles, smallpox and various other diseases. Sixty years ago, it was almost impossible to imagine Europe not torn by war. Fifty years ago, the idea of people leaving the earth was an absurdity. And even now, many people – including wizards, it seems – do not realize that complete information freedom is within reach.

"The world is not fixed. Just look at how much has changed in the last century alone! I don't know what the future will be like, but I expect that the next thousand years will be spectacular. And I don't know about you, but I certainly intend to be around to witness it!

"Thank you!"

He jumped off the Head Table as applause broke out. The Deputy Headmistress beamed at him.

"That was a very inspiring speech, Professor."

"Thank you, Professor. I am not sure it will be enough, though. It takes a while to change your mind about something as fundamental as this. Children do tend to be more open to new ideas, but it will need time. I planted the seeds, but –" he shrugged helplessly. "I don't suppose you have invented time machines, have you?"

She gave him a strange sideways look, and then the sounds of the Great Hall seemed to be muted.

"None that will let you go back for more than a few hours, no," she answered.

"Wait. You actually have time machines?"

"Yes... But please realize knowledge of their existence is restricted – I depend on your secrecy. This is how we're currently averting the worst of today's disaster, by sending your son and his friends back as often as the laws of time permit, to stretch the crucial fifteen minutes as far as they will go. In fact, your son had a Time-Turner from the start of the year. It's how we've been dealing with his sleep disorder."

"You gave Harry a time machine to treat his sleep disorder?" He just managed to keep his voice down, but he did not bother trying to keep the horror out. There were just so many flaws with this plan that it was a miracle wizards had not yet destroyed the world, although he wasn't excluding the possibility for the next ten years.

Professor McGonagall's shoulders slumped and something almost like a groan escaped her. "Not again."

(April 20th 1992, 8:18am, Linfen, China)

The problem with the True Patronus Charm, Harry realized, was that it required a certain mental state that was rather hard to maintain if you were were being confronted with the consequences of your failure, over and over.

Because this was his fault. Of course it was. That was the whole point of heroic responsibility, that everything was your fault. And especially this, because he was pretty sure that the situation had been set up for his sake.

He had known that something like this might be coming. He had refused to cooperate with Quirrell's plans to become hailed as a savior, and so Quirrell had given him no choice. All these people were killed for him. And as Harry looked out over what amounted to a battlefield, he had trouble imagining the earth among the stars and mankind traveling from galaxy to galaxy. Whatever he might do with the rest of his life, the people lying dead here would not be part of that future. It was Hermione's explanation, the will to protect the survivors, that drove his Patronus forward now, weak and wavering at first, but enough to stop further destruction.

This isn't right, he thought, as he poured everything he still had into the spell. Everyone should live forever. These people had no less right to live than the others.

But perhaps he could still save them.

The Patronus brightened to a small sun as he realized the obvious. He had rejected Death as the natural state of affairs, had decided to heal the wound in the world. But that would not be enough. Even if he could heal aging and stop disease, there would still sometimes be accidents; even if he could back everyone up somehow so they could be recovered after death, it would not bring back all those billions of people who had died before.

"Harry Potter, stop!"

He dropped his wand. He couldn't stop the spell, not when the thought was exploding from him like a supernova, but this he could still do. The light disappeared, but the feeling remained.

There is no reason to accept death. Not while there is magic in the world.

All those people in front of him might yet be saved. The demented still had intact brains, all their memories and personality might still be there somehow. No one had ever figured out a way to reverse the Dementor's Kiss, but no one had known how to destroy Dementors either. Perhaps it was well within the realm of science to bring them back already, and otherwise magic might do it in the future.

And as for the others... There were time machines, weren't there? Sure, they could only go back for six hours, but if time travel was possible in the universe, then why not go further? If they could truly figure out how time worked, why should they not be able to make read-only time machines that could go back six billion years, and allow them to make a backup of every sentient being that ever lived? And if that took another thousand years to accomplish, then so be it; no one would ever truly die in that time...

How had he ever been so unambitious as to desire an end to death only for the people of the present and future?

"Are you okay?" Barnok asked. Harry nodded, and bowed down to pick up his wand.

He had vowed to wipe Dementors from the earth. He had vowed to bring an end to death. And now, as the Ethiopian wizard took his arm and teleported him back to the Ministry, he made a new vow. A world without death meant a world where no one had ever permanently left.

The next few groups of Dementors were a lot easier to vanquish.

(April 20th 1992, 8:20am, Lodz, Poland)

Padma stared around at the result of another bloodbath, her face hard. The Dementor had caused huge traffic accidents in between its other... activities.

This felt a lot better in the first five minutes, she thought, disgruntled. But there were just ten minutes to go, and then she'd get to live those wonderful five minutes all over again.

(April 20th 1992, 8:21am, Hogwarts)

I'm right by your side, son. Don't be afraid.

Draco pictured the scene in his mind and called up all the feelings of the moment.

"Expecto Patronum."

Nothing. Just an ever-growing certainty that this wasn't going to work.

After trying to cast the Patronus Charm over and over, he had started to notice it: the little moment of distraction right before the final brandish. The phrase DEMENTORS ARE A PHYSICAL EMBODIMENT OF DEATH hadn't seemed so important at first, compared to the PREPARE TO DIE parts, but when casting the spell now, it was like his mind was inevitably drawn back to it. And in that final moment, the spell felt wrong, somehow.

It didn't make any sense! Why should some tidbit of knowledge that didn't even really seem to fit ruin the spell? And yet, what seemed to be a stupid claim at first felt simply true while casting the Patronus Charm.

Draco sighed and gave up. Apparently, if he was going to do this, it would have to be in Potter's way. He'd been trying that for almost twenty minutes already, but it also didn't seem to be going anywhere. Still, he probably had a better chance of pulling it off than anyone else here.

(April 20th 1992, 10:50am, Dalton Magical Malady Center)

The boy, Lesath, opened his eyes.

"Where am I?" he asked.

"Hospital," Sally answered simply. "You lost control in the arena, and I didn't notice in time. I'm sorry."

He sat up, eyes wide. "What time is it?"

"It's ten to eleven. You were unconscious for about three hours," she explained.

"So... I can still go back?"

"The Healers say you need rest..."

"I don't want rest, I want to destroy Dementors! Look, I'm fine!" He pushed the blankets away as if to prove it.

She considered him. It would be in the world's interest if he fought. She didn't want him to die, but if he wanted to risk it, that was his choice. She'd learned to respect people's choices, in her twenty-five years with a phoenix.

"Very well," she decided. "We'll go back in ten minutes, when your old self isn't going to be in the DMLE anymore." And she would make very sure to add a note to the presence roster, whenever he was the only one there, that he was only to receive small assignments. She'd almost gotten him killed once, and she wasn't about to repeat the experience.

(April 20th 1992, 7:29am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 2)

Lesath and Sally were the last of them to appear.

"So, we're all still alive then," Hermione concluded. She sounded weary, but then, they all were. One hour of constantly watching strangers die had dampened their spirits somewhat.

Then the others all winced, presumably because the voice sounded in their heads again. Harry didn't hear it, like he hadn't heard it the first time. Professor Quirrell's magic could not interact with his own, and so it seemed that he had been excluded from receiving the unblockable mental message.

A single photograph with a note fluttered down. Barnok grabbed it and passed it around to the other phoenix owners.

"Northern America," Sally explained. "The camp where they send all the Dementors they catch, along with criminals to execute. I know the place. There's a good thousand of the creatures there, along with over a hundred guards."

With four bursts of flame, they went, to save at least the guards before their captives could strike. They had five to ten glorious minutes to go.

(April 20th 1992, 7:57am, Cairo, Egypt)

"Innervate."

Padma looked up into the eyes of the kind middle-aged witch. She was feeling drained. The phoenix was singing and the song was healing, but it just wasn't enough to cure the mental exhaustion, or to make her forget all that she'd seen today. She was tired, and she'd just lost control over her Patronus and had to be knocked out. She didn't want to go on, but she had to; the world needed her, there were still over four hours to go to save as many people as possible. This was Parvati's job, damn it, she'd chosen Gryffindor, not Padma, but she couldn't destroy Dementors...

"Are you okay?" the woman asked gently. Padma nodded. She'd have to be.

(April 20th 1992, 8:03am, Sydney, Australia)

Albus Dumbledore burned into existence in a poor part of Sydney, where another group of Dementors had wreaked havoc. The warning had come too late here for the children to avoid the damage. The street was silent, even as the dead lay among the wrecks of cars and the empty bodies of the soulless. The sudden blast of Dementor-induced fear, or perhaps the presence of soulless humans walking onto the streets, had evidently distracted drivers. None were left alive; if anybody had been only wounded, the Dementors had taken care of them, too.

With a sweep of his wand and a curse of dread power, bolts of yellow light spread out and struck the victims of the Kiss in the heart. They fell without struggle, without even a quivering in the air, as there was nothing left to pass on. In death, they seemed peaceful. It was the only grace he could still give them, that their loved ones would not witness their true fate. Scant comfort though it was, their bodies would be at peace, at least, even as their souls had been consumed.

Tears did not come easily to the old man anymore. Life had forced him to become hard. But his stomach still wrenched together, and his throat caught, at the terrible, senseless loss. He had seen the consequences of atomic bombs, but this was worse, for the people who died in that war had only lost their lives...

Why do such evil? He had never understood, until Harry had unwittingly explained it. To Voldemort, as to Harry, every death was like a Dementor's Kiss. To be accustomed to the idea of thousands of people losing their soul every single day... Indifference towards other people's lives would be a sensible barrier. Albus could understand turning evil if the universe seemed so bleak, and he respected Harry Potter for not giving in to such feelings.

Fawkes cried out and flew ahead, and Albus Dumbledore followed. Further along the Dementors' path, people were still alive to be fought for. And no matter how much he himself was hurting, while there were still people who needed him he would go on. For that, too, was what it meant to accept a phoenix.

(April 20th 1992, 8:07am, Charlerois, Belgium)

The Patronus spell made it a lot harder, Hermione thought, to stomach the loss of thousands of human lives. Every death was a tragedy, but it hit just that much harder when you were constantly reminding yourself of the value of life, and realizing that a victory over death might be in reach within the next hundred years.

She went on anyway, of course. She held on to the thought, even as every new place she went tore at her heart, because she needed to, and because she did believe in it. The lives of the survivors were precious above all. And she would be there to protect them.

(April 20th 1992, 8:21am, Mexico City, Mexico)

The two of them burned back into existence at what looked like a marketplace. Padma didn't even know what continent they were on, just that it was dark, and there were demented people walking around aimlessly. There were few, but if it was night then it seemed likely that many had also been taken in their beds. However it was, she and Tamara had come too late; the Dementors had moved on, but where to?

She felt scared, and was starting to despair. What chance did they really have to stop all this?

"Cast, quickly," Tarama hissed to her, a real tone of urgency to her voice. Then Padma saw it too, not a hundred feet away, flying towards them at speed. Real despair washed over her. They were going to die.

No, she forced herself to think. You are only Death. Humanity can get over you.

It was getting harder and harder, to really believe in that thought.

"E-expecto Patronum."

A great silver humanoid completely failed to appear. Padma just registered that the spell had felt wrong, as the thing flew straight at her, Tamara cursed something in Arabic, grabbed her by the arm, and they both disappeared in a burst of flame just before the Dementor reached them.

(April 20th 1992, 8:22am, Hogwarts)

A burst of flame announced the arrival of a phoenix in the Great Hall. Minerva was already on her feet when she recognized the Patil girl, who was gently being pushed down onto Professor Trelawney's chair by an unknown woman. Padma was crying, she saw.

She poured a mug of tea and pushed it into the girl's hand. "Drink," she ordered, even as she rang the little bell to order chocolate.

Padma obeyed, silent tears rolling over her face. "I'm sorry," she burbled in between gulps. "I'm sorry, I'm sorry!"

What has this poor child been going through?

"You have no need to be, Miss Patil," she said sternly. Whatever had happened, the girl should not blame herself for failing to live up to the insane pressure put upon her. "You are already doing so much more than anyone has any right to expect of you. How many Dementors have you been exposed to today?"

"Hundreds," the foreign witch who accompanied the girl said, as she stepped back towards the table and put her mirror away. She was not looking that well either, Minerva thought.

"I have warned Madam Bones," the woman told Padma in a heavy accent. "She will send someone else there. Don't worry, everything will be fine. But I think you need to rest for a while."

Minerva nodded in agreement and shoved the chocolate pudding which had appeared on the table towards the two. "I quite agree. Now eat a little. I think the both of you should."

She went back to the students in the hall, correcting gestures and stature as they tried to cast the True Patronus Charm. None of them had managed it yet, despite the Muggle man's inspirational lecture. Professor Verres and now Petunia, Lily's sister, were mingling with the students, answering questions and (in the Professor's case) giving encouragement. It might all be futile, but if even one more person learned in the next few hours, it could take a lot of pressure off the others, and would certainly help save lives. Not that she really wanted to put another student through all that.

She glanced back at her star-student Padma Patil, who was quietly picking at her pudding with a tear-stained face. It broke her heart to see the child like this. How many deaths had she witnessed today? And would she ever be the same again? Some hurts could not be healed, even with memory charms...

(April 20th 1992, 8:33am, Hogwarts)

"Death is just the next great adventure," some third-year Hufflepuff girl was saying. "Honestly, all this talk about defeating death seems rather dark to me."

The Muggle man reached under his chair and slowly, carefully, drew forth a gleaming knife. The girl's eyes widened in shock.

"One of the seventh-years made this for me," the man clarified. "Since you don't see any problem with death, I assume you won't mind if I stab you?"

Draco quietly smirked at the girl's spluttering and walked away. The Muggle had interesting ways of making his point, but Draco didn't think he was going to teach him more than Harry already had. Not that Potter had ever tried to teach him this skill...

Or had he? Potter had told him the fundamental idea, tried to get him to agree, even made him swear a vow. No one should have to die if they don't want to. That was the underlying thought of the new Patronus spell. Had it been Potter's intention all along to guide him so that he could eventually learn this spell? Was that what he'd done to Padma Patil? He didn't think they'd been close, but the whispers in the Hall were saying that she'd been out there, destroying Dementors, alongside Potter and Granger.

He stole a glance at his second-in-command, who was sitting at the Head Table looking desolate. Whatever she'd been doing had been incredibly hard on her. Did he really want to put himself in that situation?

No, that was wrong. Having an additional skill – and one that seemed highly desirable at the moment – could only be a good thing. Patil may have overstretched herself, but he was a Malfoy; he would not be forced to put himself at risk.

He put his hands and feet in the position Potter had taught him, and called up the memory once more, readying himself for the True Patronus Charm.

That's what I want you to say. Not who was right or who was wrong. Just that it was sad when your mother died, and sad when my mother died, and that it would be sad if Hermione Granger died. Every life is precious. Can we at least agree on that?

But there are other lives that are still alive to be fought for. Your life, and my life, and Hermione Granger's life, all the lives of Earth, and all the lives beyond, to be defended and protected –

He held the thought in his mind, held on to the idea that every life was precious, Harry's mother's as much as his own mother's; held on to the oath he had made.

"Expecto Patronum!"

But it still felt hollow.

(April 20th 1992, 8:40am, a hotel in Aberdeen)

Severus Snape zapped through the various TV networks to watch the news. The Ministry would tell Albus what they believed was going on in the Muggle world, of course, but the Ministry tended to use sources like Arthur Weasley, who didn't understand as much about Muggles as he thought.

Every single channel seemed to have news about the Dementor attacks. There was speculation about the strange message. There were hand-made videos of people trembling and then their eyes glazing over, the sign of a Kiss. Someone had even managed to catch the Patronus and one of the children on tape; Lesath, he thought. There were also amateur videos of witches and wizards killing the soulless.

The commentary was baffled, scared, and very, very angry. On various channels, people were speaking of a war. The Muggles didn't know exactly what was going on, but they knew that they were being wronged.

On one channel, the prime minister of Japan was giving an emergency press address. Did he know about wizardry? Most governments gave updates to the Muggle leadership. The Potions Master could not understand Japanese, but he got the impression from the responses that the man was telling the people things they did not already know. And if he wouldn't, the current Prime Minister of the UK was sure to speak up soon; he had been on the brink of revealing them after the attack on that school last week, which was not unreasonable given the atrocious way the Ministry of Magic had dealt with it.

The International Statute of Secrecy was at an end. There was no way they could ever Obliviate everyone of the day's events. Even if they could, it would be next to impossible to trace down all the video material.

Grimly, he zapped to the next channel only to see an amateur video of a magical explosion in the London Underground.

(April 20th 1992, 9:01am, Hogwarts)

Padma sipped her second cup of tea guiltily. She should probably go back, even if she did get a sick feeling in her stomach at the thought of fighting again, but Tamara had recommended a full hour rest, and she hadn't really felt strongly enough to argue that. Destroying Dementors had felt good at first, but now she just kept seeing the dead, empty stares of the victims. Would she even be able to do it anymore? She had already failed once... did she still believe that they could make the world a wonderful place?

Around her, shouts of Expecto Patronum filled the air. Many students were gathered around the Great Hall, trying the new version of the Patronus C, to little success. They might well have the will and the mental strength – many of them had been able to cast the normal Patronus Charm, after all – but they probably couldn't think in the right way, they didn't have Harry's training.

A burst of silver light blasted into the room. Heads swiveled. Tamara's wand shot into her hand, but the light was already dimming. And there, next to a bright human figure, stood Cedrid Diggory, a broad smile on his face.

Tamara jumped up. "Half an hour to brief him," she whispered to Padma, then strode off towards Cedric. Without a word of explanation, she grabbed his arm and disappeared with the fifth-year boy in another burst of fire.

Another person to fight, Padma registered. If Cedric started in half an hour, he could destroy Dementors for four full hours. Which meant that, even if she gave up now, there would be someone going on in her place.

And that was really the thing, she realized, as she took another sip of tea, and felt a warm feeling spread through her body. Whatever happened, someone would carry on. Maybe individual humans could not defeat death – billions had died in the past, far more than the lives which had been lost today – but humanity would go on. She would not have expected Cedric Diggory to manage this spell, but perhaps it made sense. The "Super-Hufflepuff" had the talents of multiple houses, but was a Hufflepuff because he excelled above all at the qualities of his house: dedication and loyalty. If anyone could internalize the power of working together to achieve the seemingly impossible, it would be him.

She felt good, faith returning to her mind and strength to her body. Today, they would wipe Dementors from the face of the earth, if all went well. In the next hundred years, she was sure that they would end war and famine. And one day, they would even defeat Death. How could she have forgotten that it wasn't about her, that she was just a small part of a much bigger whole?

Her wand felt comfortable in her hand. She would be able to cast the spell again, she knew. So when Tamara returned to take her back to the Ministry, she was ready.

(April 20th 1992, 7:30am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 3)

"Cedric!" Harry yelled enthusiastically. The fifth-year boy just grinned at the other four children.

"Your father got me to understand. He is a great lecturer, you know."

Four notes fluttered down, and the phoenix-owners snatched. Sally's required two people.

"I'll go with Cedric," Harry offered. Sally and Barnok swapped notes, and the five groups went to their assignments again.

(April 20th 1992, 7:52am, Tehran, Iran.)

The light burst forth again from Harry's wand, as he mentally promised the dead and demented that he would bring them back. No matter what, he promised, as he sensed the two Dementors be ripped apart, I will dedicate my life to finding a solution.

A small part of him wondered, not for the first time, whether he was just willfully deluding himself. But he shut that part of himself up, hard. This was not the time for self-doubt. The people needed him.

(April 20th 1992, 7:29am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 4)

They were seven! Two Gryffindor boys and a Slytherin girl had joined them. Lesath wasn't there yet, but maybe he would come only on the instant of the announcement.

"Hey, Timothy!" Cedric was greeting. A lot of the enthusiasm had gone out of the boy in the hour since they last saw him.

"Hey Ced," one of the two Gryffindors said tiredly. "The three of us are only here for one turn more. We've been at it for half an hour already, we used all spins of the Time-Turner to make it this far."

"The first minutes are better," Padma reassured them, although she didn't look very excited either.

The voice resounded in their heads, and the assignments appeared.

(April 20th 1992, 8:24am, Untergurgl, Austria)

Padma and Tamara hung together on the tail of the phoenix, trying to trace down the Dementor by going in the direction where the fear was the strongest, ignoring the scattered bodies lying on the ground below them.

They had got the assignment the instant they returned to the DMLE, so it might have been queued for a minute or so, and the Dementor had already left the place they were sent. They had to find the creature now, for if they went back and let Aurors pinpoint it, they might find it in the 8:29 minute when there was no one in the crisis rooms anymore.

(April 20th 1992, 8:29am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 5)

"Time," Barnok said. He and Harry popped to crisis room 6, he threw the chain of the Time-Turner over Harry's neck, grabbed his phoenix firmly to transport the creature along, and planted his hand on the first unopened box in the line of boxes placed at the far end of the room. The lid sprung open, revealing a paper saying "No".

It was only to be expected, sometimes. If Harry went back, then he might end up getting an assignment that his earlier self had already done.

Barnok just grabbed the paper and burned with Harry to the 7th, and last, room.

(April 20th 1992, 8:29am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 7)

"Room 6, box 2," Barnok told the waiting Auror. The woman would go back in time when all was over and place the NO-notes into the boxes that should have them. A new paper was already fluttering down to send Harry to his next assignment.

(April 20th 1992, 8:30am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 7)

Hermione appeared just in time to see Harry disappear. Her heart leaped: Cedric was the only other Patronus-caster she had seen in the sixth room, and she'd been really worried about the others. She'd known that Padma wouldn't make it, because the girl had told her about her one-hour break during a brief lull in the fourth room, but Harry? And Lesath?

She just saw the bursts of flame of others arriving – Lesath and Cedric – before she was sent off to Japan again.

(April 20th 1992, 8:51am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 7)

They were all there, that much Padma had established. All eight of them: Padma, Harry, Hermione, Lesath, Cedric Diggory, Timothy and Patrick Brandon, and the Slytherin girl introduced to her as Rianne Felthorne.

They all looked really, really tired. There was a table piled with food here, and some comfortable sofas in case it got too much for a while, but taking a break didn't really feel like an option when you knew that every second you wasted another person might die. All the places where Dementors were expected had been checked in the first forty minutes, so what remained now were the Dementors which had evaded detection before. Usually single Dementors, living in out-of-the-way places. And since it had taken more than an hour to hear about them, most of them had caused significant damage before the children were sent to destroy them, even if they had needed a while to travel to some part of civilization.

She still took some time to eat half a bar of chocolate. More people would survive if she lived to help them than if she let the Dementors overcome her, after all.

(April 20th 1992, 11:26am, DMLE Dementor-crisis room 7)

They were sitting around the dinner table in a subdued mien. Yes, they had saved billions of lives today. But it didn't feel all that great.

The reports had steadily trickled down, and nothing new had come in in the last half hour. Aurors, Ministry officials and legions of volunteers all over the world had been recruited to search for traces of Dementors or wounded people for the rest of the day.

They didn't know the exact death count yet, but it was in the six or seven figures. Hundreds of thousands of lives lost, in the few hours since breakfast time.

"You killed them?" The voice should have sounded indignant, but it just seemed hollow. None of them had much capacity for emotion left.

"Yes," the old wizard sighed. "We destroyed the empty hulls of their bodies. Primarily in the hope of saving the Statute of Secrecy, but also because it is kinder to their friends and relatives, this way. We've probably missed a fair few who have wandered off before we could reach them, but –" he shrugged helplessly.

"You should not have done that. What if they could have been saved still?" Harry asked. Hermione thought he didn't sound like he believed it himself. Just another ten thousand victims or so who might have been saved some other way. "And don't tell me no one ever figured out how to do that. No one ever destroyed Dementors before either."

There was a brief silence, at that.

"You yourself have named the Dementors as Death, Harry," the old wizard wearily pointed out. "Would their Kiss have any lesser effect?"

"There is little to lose by trying!"

"There is everything to lose. You underestimate the emotional impact on the survivors of not finding the corpse of their beloved ones. Besides this, the ancient texts speak dark words of the Dementor's Kiss. Perhaps these were based on guesswork, perhaps not, but if we assume that these elders knew something we did not, then it seems beyond a doubt that the Kiss is worse than death, for all the pre-Merlin sources agree on that one point. If this is not because they destroy souls, then it might be for one of the other reasons suggested by the scholars who tried to translate the now-lost Atlantean texts on the subject. Would you also object to destroying the bodies if the people are still there, unable to control their bodies, with all their hopes and happiness drained away permanently? What if they lost their ability to think, but not to feel? For those, too, are not uncommon explanations."

"Ah," Harry said. "I guess I see the point."

He didn't press further, which was unusual for him. But he too needed some rest, like all of them did.

They ate further in silence.

"I almost gave up," Padma confessed into the silence. "I lost faith that we could do it, and I almost stopped wanting to go back and fight. I don't think I'm really cut out to be a heroine."

Professor Dumbledore gave her shoulder a squeeze. "I understand well how you felt. When you have been exhausted for many hours, when pain and death is no longer a passing fear but a certainty, then it is harder to be a hero, Padma Patil. And yet you did continue. Do not sell yourself short."

"Is it always like this?" Hermione asked.

"No, not always," the ancient hero said gently. "There are many good days among the bad. When you see the smile of a child. When you know you have saved someone who would otherwise have suffered or died. That's what makes everything worthwhile."

"I will have beds made for you all," Madam Bones offered. "You cannot go back to Hogwarts yet, especially since some of you are still there, learning the True Patronus Charm. If we receive new reports, we'll wake one of you up."

"I still have one Time-Turner spin remaining," Harry offered.

Madam Bones considered this. "That might be useful, although it may be best to keep your last turn in reserve for emergencies."

"I don't want to sleep right now..." Rianne said thickly. "I don't really want to live through all that again in my nightmares."

"You'll be given potions for four hours of dreamless sleep. After that, we'll send you back to Hogwarts."

The children climbed into the beds they were offered, even as Professor Dumbledore and Madam Bones exchanged looks with each other. The children had stretched themselves beyond belief and deserved some rest. It was probably better not to burden them with the more worrying implications of the day's events for now.

-o-o-o-o-o-

Author's Note: some answers to questions that might come up, so I won't have to do it in future notes...

Q: isn't this a rather enormous risk for Quirrell to take?

A: don't forget that, as mentioned in the last chapter, a Time-Turner was involved. Quirrell had access to information from two hours in the future before executing his plan. One might imagine that he, or the person who was sending a message back in time for him, tested certain victory-conditions (such as Harry's and his own survival) before committing to the plan.

Q: okay, so Quirrell apparently used a Time-Turner to guarantee success (or at least lack of Harry-killing ;)) before sending his message. What happened to people in places like Azkaban which are warded against Time-loops?

A: Azkaban cannot interact with its own future, and therefore nobody inside has heard the message. Unfortunately, everyone who has heard the message has also interacted with Azkaban's future, and as that's definitely going to affect what they'll communicate, they cannot interact with Azkaban either. This means that for instance Amelia Bones has no way of contacting them until 9:28, which is rather inconvenient as the Aurors there are still able to cast a Patronus. The Aurors probably realize that something is wrong, as all their communication with the outside world has stopped, but they cannot find out what without leaving (and if they do, they cannot come back). So yes, some people remain who can cast a normal Patronus, but with the entire rest of the world knowing the secret, it's going to be hard for them to remain ignorant for very long.

(None of this is in the text, because it really isn't all that important; the protagonists don't even think about it, except Amelia and Albus who merely find that it doesn't help them.)

Q: the initial plan called for everyone who learned the True Patronus Charm afterwards to drop back in time to 7:30 and go to the second room. Why did Cedric go to the third room on his first time?

A: due to a miscommunication about fallback places, Tamara had taken Padma to the Great Hall in her second iteration. Thus, her second instance had already interacted with Cedric, which meant that, to avoid paradox, it was better for him not to directly interact with her past. This is why he went to one room further (which still allowed him the full four iterations his Time-Turner could give him).

Q: why are there students of all houses casting a True Patronus Charm?

A: because I envision the TPC as a spell that really uses the strengths of all four houses:

* [Slytherin] you need a lot of ambition to fully intend to reshape the world, cast down places like Azkaban and even overcome death

* [Ravenclaw] you need the perception to recognize the flaws in the world and the intellectual honesty to not lie to yourself about them, while also being able to envision a plan for fixing those flaws

* [Gryffindor] you need to have strong will to protect others, and courage to take on all the nasty pieces of darkness in the world, giving your life if necessary towards building a better one

* [Hufflepuff] you need to have the dedication to spend your life making that dream a reality, and the friendship and faith in your peers to know that others will carry on even if you fail

Harry, who invented this form of the spell, has talents spread across all houses. The others might lean more towards two or three in particular, so they focus on a specific aspect of the happy thought.

Chapter 105: The Philosopher's Stone

It's all my fault.

Not all, Slytherin corrected. I daresay there are some other people who can claim a share of the blame.

This is my war, these are my friends. I should have protected them.

We will, Gryffindor promised. We will find a way to bring them back.

Even if that is true, it may well take centuries. They will not understand the world they live in, or even know their friends or families anymore. Whatever else may happen, I have failed today.

Why hadn't he thought about tear gas and smoke bombs in time? He of all people should have realized the possibility! Why hadn't he stopped Professor McGonagall before she did something so utterly Gryffindor as leaving the wards? Why had he allowed his parents to stay, rather than forcefully evacuating them? Why hadn't he sent for Dumbledore immediately when the attackers came, or at least when Hermione wasn't returning? And why oh why had he not insisted that they all go abroad, Apparition-possibilities or not, over staying inside hostile territory?

With a burst of flame, another wizard appeared. Harry pushed his grief and self-reproof away. He needed his composure for this confrontation.

"I have taken him to Australia," Dumbledore answered his questioning look. "I will not say where, not out loud. I have arranged a new identity for him and your mother, and enough money for a single man to live in hiding for several months. I have also brought her body back to a normal temperature, since leaving her as she was would arouse suspicion. Instead, I have placed her under an anti-decomposition charm at your father's insistence."

"Will that not stop her from being revitalized?" Harry queried with a frown.

The Headmaster shook his head. "In the highly unlikely event that doctors could help her, I do not believe the charm would make any difference. This is an advanced spell for certain magical experiments, developed by a friend of mine. It can be used on living creatures without issue; it merely remains inactive, and wears off after a few minutes, if it covers someone with an active heartbeat."

"Thank you," Harry said quietly. "And now, will you explain what's been going on?"

"I am afraid that the night's events are not yet fully clear, although I hope that in time, they shall be. Nevertheless, there are some things I would discuss with you. Come with me."

With a flash of fire, the two of them arrived in a small stone room, with a handsome wooden desk and a comfortable chair behind it. The floor was cluttered with stuff, piled high. With a wave of Dumbledore's wand, a second chair appeared, but Harry did not sit down.

"Where are we?"

"The Chief Warlock's Chambers. These rooms are so well-protected that there is little chance that they will be penetrated by Muggles."

Harry was almost speechless with indignation. "You shouldn't leave the forest! What if there's another attack while you're gone?"

"I am there right now, Harry. We have nearly fifty minutes before the younger me goes back in time to send your father to safety, arrange international assistance, and bring you here."

Oh. Right.

"Very well, then." His eyes turned cold. "Will you tell me where you were, when the children in your care needed to be evacuated? How could you dump all that on Hermione?"

"Hermione Granger was entirely capable of saving both children and staff." His eyes gleamed darkly, his voice was hard. "It is not my duty to patronize other heroes. I will protect those who need it, but I knew that my help was not required there."

Harry looked at the clutter. There were many things there he recognized from previous visits to the Headmaster's office. Portraits. A Pensieve. The sorting hat.

"Those who need it?" He almost yelled it. "You left the children alone to save things?"

"My first stop were the kitchens, in fact." The Headmaster sat down. "The House Elves are as much my responsibility as the children, and they are incapable of leaving the castle without being commanded to do so. Having sent them away, I went back in time two hours to make my preparations. I disabled all the wards that would warn me of student injury or death. I set up new wards that would inform me of the location and time of any impact around Hogwarts and Hogsmeade. I warned Amelia to do the same for other locations, as Hogwarts might not have been the only target – which, as it turns out, it wasn't. Then, as I knew that at least an atomic bomb could destroy the wards along with all the protections wired into them, I went to recover the one thing which should never fall into Voldemort's hands."

"The dark wizard attractant that you were keeping as a lure to You-Know-Who?" Harry couldn't quite keep the bitterness out of his voice.

"Yes. After that, I had a little time remaining, which I used to save all those things entrusted to my care which would be irreplaceable if lost. Your cloak, for instance." He grabbed something from behind the desk and handed it to Harry. "You might as well keep it with you now. Everyone who believes you had it will think it was destroyed along with the school."

The tone of voice put Harry's hairs on end. "What exactly happened to the school?"

The old wizard just shook his head sadly. "As I had feared, they indeed used atomic bombs. All that is left of the castle are smoking ruins now. And with today's magic, we will never be able to rebuild it."

Something in Harry's heart ached. He thought he'd been numb with the pain of the many deaths of the night, and it was only a castle, not a human, but the loss still filled him with a deep sadness for something precious lost, a part of the world permanently gone.

"But..." he protested. "If you had already gone back in time and made preparations, couldn't you stop –"

"No." The Headmaster looked very grave. "I tried, of course. I do not know much about machine-driven missiles, but I managed to detect an incoming object approaching Hogsmeade at an extremely high speed, and, with the help of a reflex-improving charm, succeeded in spiriting it away to a place where it could do little harm. Unfortunately, as my wards were quick to inform me, there was a second missile, striking not a minute later."

Harry swallowed, as he realized the pain the old man must have felt the instant he realized his mistake.

"I noted down the time," the old wizard continued hollowly, "gave what instructions and comfort I could to those fools who had stayed behind in Hogsmeade, and went back another hour. The impact hit the castle directly, probably because it's at the center of the warded area. I have experienced the impact of atomic bombs before, so I knew that the building could not be saved, no matter what protections I placed upon it. Hence I did not waste any time attempting it. Instead, I went into the grounds and cast what spells I could that might at least save the lake and the forest, and thereby the merfolk, centaurs and other creatures who live there. I went back only to restore some of Hogwarts's treasures which I had no time to take earlier, such as those books in the library of which no copy exists. I was in the forest to witness the destruction as the second bomb fell on the castle."

His eyes were so unspeakably sad that Harry shivered. He had only been at Hogwarts for less than a year, and he felt the grief. To Professor Dumbledore, whose long life had largely been centered in Hogwarts – as a student, teacher and finally Headmaster – it must be tremendous.

"So why didn't you come to us then?" he asked. There was no indignation in his voice anymore, his anger had been dampened by the old man's sadness. "Where were you when we were attacked?"

"I had no idea that I might be needed until Cedric Diggory's Patronus alerted me to your predicament." He sighed deeply. "As it was, I was going between what remained of Hogwarts, the Ministry, and several foreign institutions. Most importantly, I've been making emergency arrangements for the House Elves and the creatures living on our grounds. The Elves will remain at Beauxbatons, for the time being. The merfolk and squid will be relocated to a lake in Bulgaria before the radiation affects them too much. The forest dwellers are a larger problem, however. Without the castle's wards, the grounds are no longer protected and Muggles could stray into them – and what is worse, dangerous magical creatures can go out. The last thing we need is for Hagrid's herd of Acromantulas to invade Scotland, although it seems that Hagrid has them under control, at least – he sent a gathering signal to all of the herd and helped them flee to the edges of the wards, so, for now, they are staying by his side. As for the Hippogriffs, Thestrals, Blood-Sucking Bugbears, bowtruckles, Cornish pixies and other creatures... let us say that a speedy relocation is of the utmost importance."

"I see." The centaurs were sentient magical creatures, he knew, proud and independent; not equipped with wands, but adept at poisons. Muggles, afraid of magic, might well try to exterminate the herd. He didn't know much about the merfolk, but from what he had heard, they might well be sentient. There were also said to be highly intelligent wolves, offspring from two transformed werewolves. If you let go of the bias that humans should always be the first priority, then the Headmaster's choice to save the inhabitants of the forest over helping with the evacuation could not be condemned, even without taking into account the risks posed by dangerous creatures.

But he hadn't gone straight to save the centaurs and the merfolk. He had gone for this dark item and saved "Hogwarts's treasures" first; he hadn't even gone to the forest until after he learned that the school would be destroyed.

"How could you wait so long?" he asked, anger seeping back in his voice. "What if you had found that you couldn't go back in time after the impact? What if you failed to stop the first bomb and got yourself killed? You prioritized saving books and portraits and a Sorting Hat over the forest creatures. Did their lives mean so little to you?"

"Their lives meant everything." The voice was ice-cold, now. "But I could not risk being delayed in the grounds. The chance of encountering a contradiction was minimal, as I did everything to avoid witnessing any consequences of a possible impact."

"And yet you went back for the library books rather than helping with the evacuation?"

"I was perfectly aware of the time the bomb would hit, and kept tabs on the number of people still in the school. I knew of the Weasley twins' map, and consequently had every reason to believe that Hermione Granger would not return once everyone was out. As such, I knew as a matter of fact that there was no need for my help. Now, will you sit down? And perhaps stop trying to relieve your own feelings by blaming me, so we can have a civil discussion instead?"

Harry paused. Then he sat down. "Fine. So what's the current status, then?"

The old wizard shrugged helplessly. "I know but a little. Nuclear bombs have fallen on Hogwarts and the British dragon resort, along with normal bombs on the national Quidditch league's competition stadium. All military facilities and army depots in the country have been opened up, and powerful weapons are freely handed out to civilians. Squib soldiers have managed to enter several places which are open to Squibs who know they are there, such as Platform Nine and Three Quarters and the Leaky Cauldron. They have managed to penetrate the wards into Diagon Alley and the magical street in Glasgow, but have retreated since. Other large magical areas, such as the Ministry and St Mungo's, have not been attacked, but nearby Muggle buildings are being evacuated, which signals a strong intention to change that situation in the future. On the positive side, the timely warning allowed most witches, wizards and dragons to reach safety before any harm was done. Only the Hogwarts delegation was attacked afterwards."

Harry nodded thoughtfully. He'd known most of this already, but Professor McGonagall hadn't mentioned the stadium. "Was the Quidditch stadium destroyed? Or are ordinary wards good enough to hold out against non-atomic bombs?"

"The bomb took down the wards, but was sufficiently weakened that the stadium is only partially destroyed. I suspect they refrained from nuclear weaponry there either to test the effects of less destructive weaponry, or simply because the place was closer to inhabited areas than Hogwarts. That, or the people responsible for this have a greater personal stake in not offending the people of Wales than of Scotland."

"Dad said it probably wasn't the government who did it," Harry spoke quietly. "He suggested it might have been someone in the military."

"Someone not directly accountable to the public," Dumbledore nodded. "Or more likely, someone placed under the Imperius Curse, although I cannot think why Voldemort would do such a thing. Were today's events not exactly what you believed he was trying to avoid?"

"Not quite. He is trying to avoid nuclear annihilation," Harry explained. "A war on wizards, no matter how brutal, isn't going to cause that. What happened today was... horrible, to say the least, with children dying and an irreplaceable historical site just being flattened, and it will definitely cause a pretty powerful rage against all things Muggle and against nuclear weapons in particular, but wizards aren't going to respond by destroying the entire country. We still have to live here, after all."

The old wizard frowned. "After today, there will certainly be some of our kind who would not mind destroying the country and all those who live within. But in this, ability is more important than will: magic cannot easily achieve such a feat, and those powerful enough to wreak the greatest havoc will be the most hesitant to perform it."

"I see," Harry said. "And what about the men who attacked us? Have you interrogated them to see how they found us, and why they attacked us?"

"Alastor is interrogating them at the moment, although the first responses seem to indicate that they are merely normal people – albeit aggressive and motivated by fear and hate of the unknown – who were informed by acquaintances about a peculiar disturbance at a particular place in the forest of Dean. So far, it seems that the signal originates from a military base, which was also the source of many of the weapons, in particular the tear gas and gas masks, but it is not clear how they found out. A group of Aurors and Unspeakables have gone back in time to see whether they can trace the source, for it is absolutely essential to understand how those vigilantes came to learn of your location. It is possible that an eager Muggle saw Miss Granger arriving with the first group of students and notified their military, but it is unlikely. The forest is mostly void of humans and it would have meant an extraordinary stroke of bad luck to draw the attention of a person evil enough to drum up a mob after seeing a large number of school children arrive. I suspect that this, too, was perpetrated by our old friend Voldemort, who carried the news and allowed events to take their natural course from there. If we can prove that much, it might quell the inevitable bout of fury towards Muggles that will break out nationally and internationally when our kind learn of tonight's bloodshed. I fear it will not be enough, however, for it is undeniable that the Muggles did act of their own will."

Harry looked at the table. "I can't wrap my mind around him doing that," he said quietly.

"Oh?" the old wizard asked. "It seems entirely in line with the motives you projected for him, and is a far more obvious explanation than anything else I have been able to come up with."

"No, I realize that," Harry agreed. "But... I could have died. Almost did die, in fact, there was this guy who held a gun to my head... I was so sure he wanted me to rule the country, why would he take that risk?"

"Ah," the old wizard nodded. "Perhaps I can shed some light on that point. Do you not remember what he did on Monday?"

"Euhm," Harry said, searching his mind in confusion, "which part of it do you mean?"

"The precaution he took," Dumbledore answered. "Remember that after hearing the message, no one could go further back in time than four hours. And I have since been informed that a young Muggleborn student from Beauxbatons, Marielle Dutant, never returned from the Easter Holidays. She had a Time-Turner, so it seems all too clear what is going on. He is acting on future information." He sighed. "The Time-Turner is locked to her use, of course, so I daresay she still lives. I suspect he has a servant who will test for specific conditions, and then sends the girl back in time with those answers, never knowing whether he executed the plan or not. If he merely chooses not to carry through with the plan if your continued survival cannot be confirmed, the plan is risk-free at least in this regard."

"I see," Harry said slowly. "So if my mother hadn't been there to save my life, the whole attack would never have happened in the first place."

"Correct, I think," the old wizard nodded sadly.

The solution is simple then, Slytherin suggested with a snigger. Next time you find yourself in one of his dangerous plots, just get killed. If you make a strong precommitment to do so, he can't do anything like this anymore.

I think, Ravenclaw pointed out, that if we do in fact find ourselves in such a situation, we are not actually going to follow through with that plan, no matter how sensible it would be in theory.

"Is there a way to stop him from finding out? Anti-scrying spells?"

"A clever thought," the old wizard answered after a slight pause, the hint of a smile on his lips. "I feel the fool for not seeing it before. Yes: if you are beyond discovery in the six hours following any disaster, it will be impossible to guarantee your survival. Such spells do exist, although Voldemort might possess magics which I am unaware of, which could penetrate my best defenses to at least discover that you live, if not where. That being said, there is nothing to lose by trying. I will cast my strongest spells on you when we are done here, and in addition I would urge you to hide under your cloak for six full hours after any disaster that you might have been hurt in."

"I will do so," Harry nodded, although the resolution being taken, it would most likely never be necessary to actually do it.

"With that settled," Dumbledore said after a brief silence. "There is something else I would speak to you about. Have you not wondered what it is that I went to retrieve tonight?"

"Well yeah," Harry shrugged. "But it seemed obvious that you weren't going to tell me, and I figured it might be some dark magical object or something."

The old wizard almost smiled. "Not quite, but you were right that I was deliberately withholding the information from you. Now, however, I believe the time has come to share the secret with you, as my objections were mooted yesterday. The item in question is something which Voldemort would desire above all, a device of ancient lore, which might survive a nuclear explosion, even as the wards protecting it would not. Do I have your word not to speak of what I am about to tell you?"

Harry considered this.

"You have my word not to speak of it unless there is a really good reason to go back on that. I shall be responsible with whatever knowledge you give me."

"I suppose that will have to do." Dumbledore's hand dipped into a pocket of his robes, and retrieved a black stone.

"The Philosopher's Stone. The only one in existence."

Harry's brain ran into a brick wall.

"I see that you are speechless. I suppose you have found out about this device in your many library sessions?"

"Well, yeah..." In their attempts to go through the library in an alphabetical order and at least make an index, he and Hermione had gone through most of the letter A, and therefore had found out about alchemy. And you couldn't read more than 10 lines about alchemy before running into the central goal of the whole thing, the search for the philosopher's stone. Alchemical research had led to the invention of medications against magical diseases, to the discovery of the Animagus Potion and much more, but most alchemists wasted their time trying to create some mythical device that supposedly turned base metals into gold and produced the Elixir of Life, which indefinitely prolonged the youth and health of the user. "I just thought it was obviously false."

"Oh?" Professor Dumbledore smiled briefly, although it didn't reach his eyes. "I shall mention that to Nicolas Flamel when I next visit him. His 665th birthday is next week. Although under the circumstances I suspect there will not be a party."

Had he really, actually read about a real, existing device to gain immortality and just ignored it? Harry's stomach gave a little lurch.

"But it makes no sense," he protested. "Why would one device be able to transmute lead to gold and produce an elixir that kept someone young? Those things have nothing to do with each other besides being desirable! That's why I figured that the Philosopher's Stone is supposed to create unlimited gold and eternal life, not because there's a single magical discovery that actually produces both of those effects, but because someone made up a story about a super-device that never existed."

The Headmaster just smiled that sad smile again. "Tell me, Mr. Potter. What originally made gold so valuable?"

"Euhm... I don't know? It's shiny? And I guess it might also be because gold never changes. It's resistant to corrosion, so it always keeps its shi– oh."

"Indeed. There is a connection, you see."

"But that's tenuous at best! And if someone actually made one of those, why aren't whole countries kidnapping him to force the secret out of him?"

"Because it is no secret. The method of creating a Philosopher's Stone has been well-known since before the time of Merlin. It's just very, very hard to achieve. There is, however, the problem that the stone itself might be stolen. Nicolas has managed to keep it safe for centuries, but Voldemort poses a real threat, especially since we do not know whether Nicolas's wards can keep out spirits."

"So how does it work?" Harry asked. He wasn't about to get distracted with irrelevant concerns like Voldemort while there was an actual immortality device right in front of him. "Does it heal age-related physical issues, like gene loss or accumulated waste?"

"No," Professor Dumbledore said, surprised. "Magic does that. The Elixir or Life, when charged with the right spells, increases the drinker's pool of life force."

Harry frowned, thinking. He'd come across the phrase "life force" a few times in books, most notably when referring to the Patronus Charm, but he had taken it to mean something like physical energy, which matched his exhaustion after letting the True Patronus Charm go out of control. This didn't sound quite like it, though. "Can you elaborate on that, please?"

The old man smiled wryly. "A Ravenclaw as always, I see. Well then, as there is little time for a beginner's course in Healing, let me explain it with a parallel. You know, of course, how getting tired works. You can only expend so much energy at once before your body rebels and needs rest, but after having rested, you are as strong as before. There is a clear limit to your energy: no matter how much you rest, you will not be able to sprint for half an hour on end, although by training your body you can push this limit upwards significantly. Regardless of that training, however, your limit is also subject to natural change with age. Your energy – physical strength – grows stronger at first and weaker after a certain age. So let us say that there is a pool, your physical energy, whose shape alters as you age following a standard pattern. You can tap the pool for activities, and its emptiness affects you, but it will simply replenish itself afterwards."

Harry nodded slowly. This was a very mystical way to speak about muscles and blood vessels, but he supposed it was a reasonable way of looking at it if you had no idea of the underlying biological systems.

"As you may have already learned, your so-called magical core works in much the same way," the old man continued. "And just like you have a magical core which grows as you age, plateaus, and then slowly starts degenerating towards the end of your first century, so you have a pool of life force which grows at first and starts declining later in life until it finally dwindles down to nothingness. In a witch or wizard, this process takes longer, as your body's magic prevents and later slows the decline. Even in Squibs – who do possess a magical core, but one which does not grow after birth – this effect is noticeable, although it is generally not enough to add more than a decade or so. The Elixir of Life increases the size of the pool – to a limit. The Elixir of Sorcery, which can also be made using the stone, similarly increases the size of your pool of magic "

"I see..." Harry said slowly, considering the Patronus Charm in light of this new information. "What happens when you use up all your life force?"

"You die," Dumbledore said simply. "Life force is needed for your body to keep functioning. It is, however, not easy to use up all your life force, certainly not in the prime of your life. There are spells which burn it, and your body steadily consumes it while you are awake, but the loss of life force usually happens slowly enough that you are rendered unconscious before you can spend the last drops. If you survive such a spending, the pool will simply replenish itself over time. Phoenix tears can speed up that process, although they cannot increase the size of the pool."

"And when you grow old, you have less life force, so you tire more quickly?"

"When there is less life force available, your body gradually adapts to using it less, yes. This means you grow brittle, and become more susceptible to minor illnesses, although your magic will still be able to fight off most diseases even at an advanced age. That is why most magic users die peacefully of old age rather than disease, their pool of life force simply fading to be so small that it cannot sustain their bodies' continued functioning any longer."

Harry nodded. "So what does all that have to do with lead turning into gold? The same potion that helps increment a mysterious biological force affects the number of protons and electrons in a collection of atoms?"

The Headmaster smiled. "Not the same potion – merely the same source. The philosopher's stone can be used to create three elixirs: Elixir of Life, Sorcery and Nobility, each following a different method. You must understand that gold is more than mere metal, as is silver. Why do you think those are used as our currency? There is a magical component to the noble metals which transfigurations – free or permanent – cannot emulate. Unfortunately I do not know many details, as treaties with the goblins forbid any magical experimentation with these metals, but this much is well-known."

Harry filed that away for future notice. Perhaps he should have a good look over the exact formulation of those treaties before trying his gold and silver trick.

"But in short," he summarized. "There actually is a device that grants immortality. You have it. You hid it in Hogwarts. And you didn't tell me before that such a thing exists. In fact," he added after a thought, "you deliberately hid it from me, talking of 'the thing he wants'."

The old wizard bowed his head. "Yes, I did. It was not my secret to give away, and aside from that that, I must confess that I feared you. I believe now that I was wrong about that, however." The blue eyes pierced Harry's. "You do not fear death in the way Dark Wizards do."

"I fully intend to make Death fear me," Harry answered.

The Headmaster nodded. "I visited Nicolas last Monday, in the hope that he could learn your spell. He could not, at the time, but he said that he understood the meaning very well. Yesterday, he contacted me again and proclaimed that he had finally succeeded, and that the charm had touched him on some level he hadn't felt in centuries. He also told me that if you had invented this spell, then it would be safe to tell you about the Stone. He added that you might be one of the few people able to make another, although I would personally advise against trying."

"Why? Surely even wizards don't casually overlook the implications of a device that grants immortality?"

"It doesn't grant immortality! It merely gives eternal youth. It would not have stopped today's deaths." He sighed deeply, as though he was carrying the burden of the world on his shoulders. "Nor would it save those who succumb to a magical disease. And to answer your question, I would advise against it, because even those who follow the instructions perfectly – which is extremely hard to do, and will take years of intense work – tend to die when casting the final spells to complete the process. Nicolas Flamel is the only known wizard who has ever survived these last steps. There might have been more in the days of Atlantis, as someone must have developed the recipe from which Nicolas worked, but if any survived its fall, Merlin did not know of them."

"But why don't wizards who are on the verge of death try to make one?"

"Because it wouldn't work. The spells require such an extreme investment of both magic and life force, that you can only do it in the prime of your life, when you are likely to still have a century ahead of you. Even then, you must be exceedingly powerful to even have a chance, and be extremely fortunate to boot. I know of hundreds who have tried it, and only one who has succeeded."

"Ah."

From a purely utilitarian point of view it might make sense to take that chance. If there was a 99% chance of dying in the process, and a 1% chance of immortality, then the expected gain from trying was 0.99 * -100 + 0.01 * infinite, so still infinite. Or, if you assumed that the universe would continue to expand and eventually no longer support life, it was about 0.99 * -100 + 0.01 * 10^10, which was still pretty near infinite. You'd probably need some extra precautions to stop dying from other sources, like atomic bombs, gamma rays or other mistakes, but if you could do that, the maths was pretty clear.

Would I do it?

It was a painful question, and he didn't know the answer. Sometimes, expected value wasn't the only thing of importance, because that which you lost would weigh much higher than that which you might gain...

It was moot anyway. Harry was probably going to find a better path to immortality long before the time came to make a philosopher's stone.

"I suppose I can see your point," he said, carefully keeping his voice neutral. "But in all fairness, how do you know that this Nicolas is the only one who succeeded? If others had, would you have heard of it? It sounds like there's a strong motive for secrecy, if you have a device that gives infinite life and money and which can be stolen."

"A good point," the old wizard nodded. "But you should not forget that it requires immense magical power to do this, and knowledge of certain spells which are not typically shared lightly. The Interdict of Merlin guarantees that we know of all who might have attempted it, and the deaths of powerful wizards and witches tend to be well-documented."

Unless someone got the spells from an alchemist and then killed him and made it look like an accident, Harry didn't say out loud.

"So why does Nicolas seem to think I have a better chance than others of learning?"

"Because you don't want to avoid dying; you merely want to keep living."

"Erm... Headmaster, forgive me for pointing out the obvious, but that's exactly the same thing."

"Not quite. How should I put this? I suppose you don't want to die, not because you fear death, but because you enjoy life. And you think that no matter how long you live, you will continue to enjoy it so much that you'll want to go on doing it."

"Yes. That is a pretty accurate summary."

"And that is where you differ from most of those who seek immortality."

Doubtful, Harry thought. But perhaps in the magical world, where trying to avoid death is seen as dark, and people don't even consider the possibility that eternal life might be a good and bright thing because it is so internalized as the kind of thing bad people want, it is true.

"So what made Nicolas different?"

Dumbledore shrugged helplessly.

"Nicolas never truly sought immortality for himself. You see, early in life he married a Muggle woman, Perenelle. Despite the difference in status, he loved her his entire life, and desired more than anything to grow old with her. This wish, of course, was not to be. With her not possessing any magic of her own, and having suffered various Muggle illnesses during childhood – illnesses which had left her body weakened and permanently damaged her life force pool – she could never expect to live more than seventy years, even with all the magical healing he could offer."

Harry nodded. He'd wondered about mixed marriages before.

"Fearing the day when she would die before him, Nicolas studied alchemy. His father had left him a sufficient fortune so he would never need to work, which allowed him to focus on his research without ever neglecting his wife. And when Perenelle was old and weakening in age, he performed the final spells. He tells me that the crucial thing was that he wanted to live, forever, with her. He did not mind the chance of dying, for without her, life would not be worth living. For what he tells me, the spell resonated with him on some powerful level; he sensed that his motivations mattered. He aged about seventy years in a minute as a large chunk of his life force and magic were ripped out of him, but he survived, and the stone was made."

"Wait." Harry was thinking rapidly. "You can use the stone on multiple people? But that changes everything!"

"Let me finish. The stone generates enough Elixir to sustain life and magic for one person at the level of a moderately powerful 40-year-old, with some left to create a modest bit of gold. It was never his intention to use the stone in this way. At first, he gave all the Elixir to Perenelle, which finally healed her life core and returned her youth. He found that he could sustain her with only a bit over half the Elixir. Unfortunately, this did not leave enough for himself, all the more so as he needed to sustain his magic as well as his life. Being now old himself, it seemed that Perenelle, and not he, might end up being the survivor. As you might imagine, however, she would not stand for that."

The old man smiled fondly. "They compromised. Rather than having one of them live forever and the other one die, they chose to simply live a long life together. Perenelle aged as Nicolas grew younger, until they were physically roughly the same age. Thus it was that they learned that it takes less Elixir of Life to sustain an eighty-year old than a forty-year old. They could live together as somewhat elderly people, but in good health and with sufficient energy for a quiet life, while still having some use of the stone to spare on Elixir of Sorcery, to preserve Nicolas's magic. Unfortunately, it still wasn't enough, so his magic dwindled over the next century, then plateaued. Even without further sustenance from the stone, his magic did not degenerate beyond that; he is roughly as powerful as an average fifth-year child, now."

"That's still pretty good," Harry observed.

"Yes; it is enough to handle health problems for himself and Perenelle, and to slow the natural loss of life force, which allows him to save up some more of the Elixir. It is certainly sufficient for daily use. However, you must take into account that he was a very powerful wizard before, and most of the greater magics are now well beyond him."

"I see... But he can still teach powerful spells, such as the spells to make the stone."

"Yes." Dumbledore waved his wand. "In fact, when he finds someone he trusts, that person might just learn a lot of spells and alchemical potion recipes almost forgotten these days. After learning your variant of the Patronus spell, he said he would be happy for you to study with him, once you graduate Hogwarts. It might be an offer worth considering."

Harry blinked. "Yes, definitely." Learning some powerful six hundred year old magic lore was an offer not to be sneezed at, and a chance to study the philosopher's stone and learn more about the arts of immortality might be invaluable too. Although the Elixir of Life seemed to be more about aging than actual immortality, and wouldn't bring back Mum or any of the others.

Well, actually...

"What exactly happens when we die?" That feeling when his mother had died had not been physical, but it might just have something to do with life force.

If Dumbledore was surprised at the non-sequitur, he didn't show it. "Death is the separation of body, soul, life and magic – although I am not certain whether the soul and the magic separate or stay together; there are theories that these two parts are inextricably tied."

"If a person died from non-magical wounds, can the body be cured – well, brought back to perfect condition – with magic?"

The Headmaster raised an eyebrow. "I suppose it may be possible, although it would be a lot harder than curing a living body. May I ask where you are going with these questions?"

"Well... What happens when you give Elixir of Life to a corpse?"

"Nothing," the old wizard spoke sadly. "Nicolas has tried it, but his efforts were fruitless. Once the soul has moved on, the life force has nothing to latch on to."

That, or he didn't know about CPR, Harry thought. Or perhaps it worked, but the person immediately died again because the Elixir only increases the size of the life pool, but doesn't fill it. That could be circumvented by having them in the presence of the True Patronus Charm when they're revived.

Ravenclaw cleared her throat. Do we even know whether this whole life force explanation is an established medical fact? This is Dumbledore talking.

We can ask Madam Pomfrey about it? Hufflepuff suggested. We don't need to make all the plans immediately, but this certainly seems like an enormously important avenue to investigate further. Especially after today.

"I don't suppose your friend Nicolas has some Elixir to spare, does he?"

"He does, in fact," the old wizard nodded. "When they found that his magic was no longer changing, Nicolas and Perenelle were quite settled in the life they had lived for a hundred years, and had neither wish nor inclination to have more energy. His vast magical lore and aptitude with potions secured a steady income, which removed the need for any gold, too – and I do believe the goblins at Gringotts give him some very good deals on his banking if he refrains from creating any. As a result, he has been storing the remaining Elixir for well over three hundred years. He makes occasional use of the storage – for example, he has used some of the spare Elixir to heal acquaintances suffering from a damaged life core like Perenelle first did – but mostly he keeps it for experiments, emergency healing, and for the contingency that the stone is stolen or destroyed. I believe he currently has enough saved up to last him and Perenelle for thirty years."

"I can think of some experiments," Harry said pointedly. "When we are done here, you are going back in time to the battle, and then you will cast your anti-decomposition charm on every child in that forest – and McGonagall and Vector too – the instant they die. And then we'll see what a combination of immortality juice, the True Patronus Charm, Muggle doctors and who knows what more together can do."

"There is no point, Harry, their soul has moved on! I understand that you're hurt, but no good will come from pinning your hopes on –"

"Just. Do. It."

The old wizard sighed. "I cannot go back in time that far anymore, I have used too many turns already today. But if you insist, I shall ask Alastor Moody to do so once he returns from his current assignment."

He looked at his watch. "We have only ten minutes left before I should return, so let us move on. I brought you here not merely to inform you, but also to seek your advice. With its protections gone, the question that I have feared all year has presented itself: whether the stone ought to be destroyed."

Harry opened his mouth in shock and then shut it again. He stared at the old wizard in complete non-understanding.

"No! Of course not! You don't just throw away immortality, that's... that's..."

The Headmaster held up a hand. "I had expected this response from you, all the more so now that you have a use for the Elixir in mind, futile though I am certain it will prove to be. Yet I ask you to consider the question for a moment, before dismissing the idea altogether. Nicolas and Perenelle themselves say they are prepared to do it, if it will prevent disaster from striking the world – but if disaster is unavoidable, or we can avoid it without destroying the stone, they would rather not resort to that. As it is, without the defenses of Hogwarts, I do not know whether I will be able to protect the stone. The wards in these chambers were crafted by Merlin himself, but they are not as versatile as the Hogwarts wards were. This office was never meant to hide objects beyond retrieval, and besides holding the stone on my person, it is the only option I have left. The consequence of allowing the Philosopher's Stone to remain in existence will likely be that, eventually, Voldemort will take possession of it. If not destroying the stone, what else is there I can do to keep it from him? You know his mind better than any, do you see a way?"

"Why would he want it?" Harry asked logically. "He's already immortal, I thought we established that point."

"He is immortal only in the sense that his soul cannot be forced to move on from this realm either by death or exorcism, not in the sense that he doesn't age! To combat the effects of a degenerating body, his only recourse without the stone is to die and trust his servants to create a new body. There is a ritual that creates a body to perfectly match a spirit's magic, but it requires permanent sacrifice: in order to create the body, a sufficiently large amount of bone from a near ancestor is required, and in order to imbue it with life force both a willing servant and an unwilling enemy must sacrifice half of theirs – in total, life force is said to be lost permanently. This is not a ritual that can be repeated infinitely often, if only because there can only be so many near ancestors whose bone to take."

"What about possession?" Harry asked. "Can't he simply keep taking over other people's bodies?"

"He could, but his magic would be weaker by having to be channeled through another's body. What is more, such a possession cannot last long, as it places a great stress on the body, which needs to hold two souls at once. I believe that this is what we have seen with Quirinius Quirrell, although I did not recognize it for what it was at the time."

Harry raised his eyebrows. "I'm going to pattern-match this talk about souls and ask what happens if a spirit possesses a victim of the Dementor's Kiss."

"A good question," the old wizard nodded. "These bodies are deprived of soul and magic, but retain their life force, and therefore would most likely make perfect targets for possession. This has not come up in recent years, as it has been the practice to destroy the bodies of Dementor victims for centuries, but there are certain old tales which suggest that the method has been deliberately used in the past to create human hulls amenable to possession, as they 'do not fight', as the phrase was. Even in such cases, though, the possession was said not to have lasted more than two decades, and even without soul-conflicts, possessing a foreign body still weakens the magic. But in the long run, this, at least, is not a problem, as there will be no Dementor-victims past this generation."

"No," Harry agreed with a swallow, thinking back to the many empty-looking yet still living bodies he had witnessed last week. "But I bet he's possessing such a body now."

"True," the old wizard spoke. "But above all these things, there is one price that the stone gives, which neither rituals nor possession can offer."

Harry considered. "Magic?"

"Magic," Dumbledore stated. "There are no tales, none at all, of wizards who survived their deaths, yet lived beyond their third century. Voldemort might leave his body behind and craft himself a new one. He might succeed in crafting a young body, if he chooses a servant and enemy both in their primes or youth. However, I have never heard of any spell or ritual that allows part of a magical core to be stolen, or given. It is my suspicion, however – although I confess I am not certain – that there is simply no magic known to man, no matter how horrific, that will stop the degeneration of magic with age. Nothing, besides the Philosopher's Stone."

"What about blood sacrifices, like you said Grindelwald was getting?"

The old man frowned deeply. "Human sacrifice can be used to refill both life and magic cores, and even to overcharge them, but not to alter their size. If not used, the spare magic and life drain away, and while some of the life can be used to retain the magic for longer, the process is very lossy. Grindelwald had people killed by the thousands, which included enough Squibs and occasionally magic users to increase his power beyond challenge, but it would never be sustainable in the long run. Certainly this approach would not suffice to combat the effects of age. Voldemort would want to preserve as much power as he wields now, so that few would have a chance to defeat him. Yet such power can come only by sacrificing wizards or witches, likely three to five each day, or over a hundred Squibs."

"That does not seem unsustainable," Harry explained patiently. "You just kill witches above childbearing age. Crank up the fertility rate a little by giving exemptions to families with sufficiently many magical children, and within a century even the British Isles alone could produce the 1500 or so blood sacrifices each year. And since Squibs can be used, you can even avoid wizarding protests about the system just by getting a group of male Death Eaters to routinely impregnate a warehouse of Muggle women. You said Squib cores simply don't grow, so you can get the full effect by killing them as babies."

Dumbledore was staring at him in wide-eyed horror. Harry sighed.

"This is like sharpening Hufflepuff bones into weapons again, isn't it? Look, I don't think he particularly wants to do that. I'm just saying that if he wants to avoid dying, he has other options. And honestly, if the alternative option is him setting up that kind of system, I'd say give him the stone."

A pained expression crossed the old wizard's face. "You would choose to give Voldemort the means to rise more terrible even than before, to become an immortal dictator, whom none could challenge even two hundred years from now?"

"No," Harry said softly. "I would not. But we don't know what the future will bring. Since you asked my opinion, I would recommend not destroying the Stone. We might still need it, and right now I cannot see its destruction achieving anything other than the deaths of your friends Nicolas and Perenelle."

Dumbledore appeared to consider this, and then nodded his gray head slowly.

"Very well. I shall follow your advice for now."

He stood up.

"And now it is time to get back to the forest of Dean, and protect the children sleeping there."

"That, and send Mad-Eye Moody back in time to protect the bodies."

The former Headmaster grimaced sadly. "Yes, I shall do that too."

Harry nodded. "Excellent. Before you take me back, do you have a convenient place where I may have been sleeping for the past six hours?"

Chapter 108: The Muggle War, Pt 6

Wednesday April 29th 1992, 6:03pm.

Harry was sitting in his new office, scribbling on a piece of parchment. The office was a simple stone affair, deep in the recesses of the Ministry, in the corridor leading to the Wizengamot Hall. The chambers here were not used much, these days, as most witches and wizards preferred rooms with a window and easy access to the other services higher up in the buildings. But these rooms were secure from eavesdropping, Apparating and various other hostile possibilities, and would withstand a lot of force. In the event of an attack on the Ministry, they were the safest place to be.

Pius Thicknesse – the man who had proposed that Harry could use House Vows – had arranged it. The man's first order of business had been to swear service to the Potter House and request to be included in the negotiations as the representative of the Ministry. Then he'd set up the room, haggled with Amelia Bones to have a trio of competent Aurors placed outside the door, and left to formulate a contract for the representatives of the Wizengamot to sign, which would guarantee that the results of Harry's negotiations would be followed, and could not be revoked for the duration of a year, except by near-unanimous agreement.

Pius Thicknesse, apparently, was quite tired of the political scene as it had been for almost ten years. The Senior Secretary to the Minister of Magic, he was essentially a bureaucrat, the pencil-pusher who handled most of the administrative work for the Ministry. Corruption appalled him and as a result he held a severe dislike for Malfoy, but considered Dumbledore to be hopelessly naive. The promise of a new powerful player in the political scene gave him hope, so now he leaped at the opportunity to prove himself useful and secure his position for the future – an intention he was entirely honest about.

Thicknesse had explained the exact mechanics of the House Vow. Much simpler than the Unbreakable Vow, the spell merely created a bond between the Lord or Lady of a Noble House and the "servant", allowing the former to kill the latter or to destroy their magic simply by choosing to do so. In addition, possibly to cater to the more squeamish masters who might not wish to be directly responsible for their servant's death, the master could give a binding order, and should they learn that it had been violated, punishment would be immediate without the need for a conscious decision. The bond caused a small drain on the master's magic to preserve, but the amount was unlikely to be noticeable even with a child's magic, and the drain lasted only until the bond was broken. In the event of the master's death, the bond would be passed to the new Lord or Lady of the House, provided a magical inheritance contract was in place, as was the case for the Potters. The existence of the bond could be magically verified if the master willed it, but its absence could not be confirmed, even by the servant; the bond could only be broken with the consent of the master.

While the spell itself was already bad enough, in Harry's opinion, the law added to it. It was absolutely forbidden to use the spell without a formal servitude contract in place, witnessed by a member of the Ministry. While this may have been meant as a legal protection to stop people being tricked into accepting the spell, it meant that in practice, the spell could not be used without also signing up to a host of legal arrangements. It was explicitly legal to kill, torture (although not with the Cruciatus curse) or otherwise punish a sworn servant, and a servant could never file a criminal lawsuit against their master. It was possible for the master to cancel the servitude contract, but while that came with the legal obligation to also release the magical bond, there was no easy way to confirm that the latter had been done. It was entirely possible for the Lord of a Noble House to cancel a servitude contract but keep the bond in place, unknown even to the servant, and kill them at will years later.

When questioned why he would submit to such a Vow, Thicknesse had shrugged and observed that it would not reflect well on the new Lord Potter to abuse the privileges granted by the spell to needlessly kill or hurt his servant, or to extend the servitude longer than a few days given the circumstances under which it was agreed. Moreover, Harry had little to gain in illegally preserving the bond once the contract was revoked. Thicknesse had always refrained from learning Occlumency – being able to have the truth of his words magically verified seemed to him a greater advantage than the ability to protect his mind – so he would not be able to hide it, willingly or otherwise, if Harry told him that the bond was still in place. If Harry kept the bond without telling Thicknesse, it would be a constant drain on his magic for little gain, as Thicknesse was not at all likely to be more useful to him dead than alive.

Then Thicknesse had sat down to discuss Harry's security. He had observed that there were a few people – Bartemius Crouch, for instance – who were none too pleased with Harry's proposals or his appointment as negotiator, and that some of those might seek to remove the problem. That was why he arranged the Aurors before leaving, and promised to make sure to put certain safeguards in the Wizengamot's contract.

A knock on the door announced the arrival of a visitor. Harry blanked the parchment he was writing on with a tap of his wand, sat up straighter and said: "Come in!"

Lucius Malfoy opened the door and stepped inside. He would have been checked for polyjuice and had his wand confiscated by the Aurors, of course.

"Lord Malfoy," Harry said formally, activating the privacy wards in the office with a quick move of his wand.

"Lord Potter," Lucius Malfoy nodded. "I have come to swear servitude to your House, and request to be included in the peace negotiations."

Harry stared at him. Has he gone mad, or what? The Lord of Malfoy, surely, would be able to pay someone to serve as a binder for the Unbreakable Vow...

"I would be glad to have you accompany me in whatever peace negotiations we settle on," he replied, just managing to keep the surprise out of his voice. "But are you sure you would submit to a House Vow?"

"Yes. An Unbreakable Vow is impractical," Lucius Malfoy spoke calmly. "It is too rigid, defining an exact set of conditions to be met. If the negotiations turn out differently from the way we expect, it would deprive me from the ability to improvise. In the case of a House Vow, improvising would merely place my death at your discretion."

"I suppose it would," Harry said, "But as I understand it, there is absolutely no way to guarantee that I will release you afterwards. Are you not concerned about this?"

"Not at all," Lord Malfoy stated with a slight smile. "For I am not asking you to release me afterwards. Releasing the contract would be politically prudent, perhaps, but I do not mind if the bond itself remains in place."

Harry blinked. What?

"You seem surprised," Lucius Malfoy observed.

"Well, yes," Harry answered. "I am struggling to comprehend why you would be willing to enslave yourself."

"There are few people who truly comprehend the power of servitude, Lord Potter."

Harry nodded slowly, thinking through the implications. The House Vow was a powerful way to achieve trust: when someone can kill you at will, you are very unlikely to betray them. The Vow left some wiggle room – a sworn servant could betray their Lord provided the Lord never found out – but it was too dangerous to be used lightly. A master, on the other hand, had reason not to abuse the privilege: it would be in his interest to preserve the servant's loyalty, and to not push them towards betrayal or substandard performance. To Harry, the Lord Malfoy could be an extremely useful ally, if he could have the guarantee that the man wasn't going to stab him in the back. And to Lucius, the bond would create opportunities to make suggestions expedient to him. Lucius had taken willing servitude to Lord Voldemort in the last war, and for all Harry could see, had profited from the arrangement: at the very least he had come out with all his power intact, and it was likely that many of his political opponents had been killed in the war. He had lost his wife, but for that he blamed Dumbledore, not Voldemort.

And yet, something still felt wrong. He should probably just allow the man to swear servitude and be done with it, but he had the feeling there was some deeper motive behind the man's professions.

"You must know that I do not share some ideas which are very important to you."

The man before him grimaced briefly.

"Do you believe that I agreed with the Dark Lord's ideas? No. I am well aware that our values are not fully aligned, Lord Potter. Even if my son had not told me of your beliefs, your statements with regards to the negotiations made that clear: you seek to live together in peace, not to subjugate. But in cases of importance, one must prioritize. There are two things which matter more to me than anything else in the world. The power of House Malfoy. And my son, Draco."

He paused for a few moments, but Harry didn't speak, so he continued: "You are powerful, Lord Potter. Or will be, in the near future. Anyone with any sense at all would see that. With the support of the country behind you, I have little doubt that you will resolve the current crisis to general satisfaction, a feat that will gain you a large following. I helped your rise to power by not obstructing your appointment today, but even without my help, you would have got there eventually."

"And what has this to do with your son and your House?"

"I know well that you have little reason to ally yourself with me. In the last war... well. And only this month, I had your friend sent to Azkaban – unjustly, as it turns out. My son tells me that you do not care to take sides, but I suspect that you are a lot more sympathetic to Dumbledore's causes than mine. If you continue to think of me as a potential enemy, the power of House Malfoy might fall." He shrugged. "Yet you call Draco friend. I do not ask for any favors, but I hope you will remember him, in your future plans."

Ah. "I think I can safely promise that."

"Will you allow me to swear?"

Something still felt off. No matter how plausible the explanation sounded with all that Harry knew of the man, it was still hard to believe that the Lord of House Malfoy would willingly swear himself into the service of house and submit to the whims of a child his son's age. But there didn't seem to be a good reason to refuse, so Harry nodded, canceled the privacy charms and rang the little bell on his desk, which had been enchanted to cause a ringing sound outside the door. One of the Aurors immediately came in to perform the spell and witness the oath of servitude that would seal the legal contract.

"I, Harry James Potter, Lord of House Potter, declare that I will release Lord Lucius Malfoy from our servitude contract within one week after the negotiations with the Muggle government end," Harry declared. It was the same promise he had made for Thicknesse.

The Auror nodded. "I witness this promise."

The silk-robed, white-haired killer nodded solemnly, then sank down on his knees to follow the common form prescribed by law. Harry had to fight to keep his face straight as the noble lord, without any trace of irony, looked up in subjugation to an eleven-year old child. Harry stepped in front of the desk, held out his wand, as he had been instructed, and let Lucius take the other end.

"Upon my life and magic," the Lord of Malfoy recited, "I swear service to the House of Potter, to obey its Master or Mistress, and stand at their right hand, and fight at their command, and follow where they go, at their choice or until the day I die."

Harry swallowed. "I, Harry, Lord of the House of Potter, accept your service."

"Servuro," the Auror cast. A golden band sprang from his wand, and twisted itself around Harry's and Lucius's wands. Something inside Harry tugged and Harry, mentally accepting the bond, saw the golden band sink into both their hands as Lucius did the same.

"It is done." Lucius Malfoy stood up. "Send for me, and I will appear by your side."

"Thank you." Harry didn't really know what else to say. Lucius had chosen this of his own free will, but Harry still felt guilty for accepting. Even if he ended the contract the moment the negotiations were over, Lucius Malfoy would never know for certain whether the bond was gone, since unlike with Thicknesse, Harry would have a powerful motive to keep it in place. The man would never truly be free anymore. Or had he planned something against that?

His servant bowed deeply, and left the room together with the Auror.

Wednesday April 29th 1992, 7:27pm.

"You too?" Harry asked.

"I will swear," Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore nodded, "if you will let me. I hope I am still in time to join your negotiation unit."

Harry nodded. "You're only the third. Aren't you afraid of what I might do if you give me the power to kill you with just a thought?"

"I trust you," the old wizard said simply.

Well, at least that makes one of us.

Harry considered the old man. It would definitely be a good idea to have someone as powerful as Dumbledore by his side; he was the only one who might have a chance to save the day if Riddle should end up interfering. Unfortunately, Dumbledore knew him. Dumbledore would know that Harry might hesitate to kill him or take his magic if he spoke out of turn. And he was not at all afraid of death; if Harry's proposals shocked him enough, the man might decide that the risk was worth it. Harry could avoid that by precommitting to a punishment under given conditions, but this would only work for very straightforward conditions. It would lose the important flexibility advantage Lucius had spoken of.

Would he risk an all-out war by messing up and possibly dying during negotiations?

Unlikely. Dumbledore was even willing to go along with Voldemort if it meant an end to the bloodshed. He would not take the risk of interfering with Harry unless the very fate of the world was at stake. And what was more: thinking back, he'd been treating Harry as an adult, even followed his commands, ever since he'd offered to relinquish command of the Order. Ever since Harry had told him that he didn't like his methods... Perhaps Harry should have noticed that before.

"You hesitate?" The old wizard asked.

Harry nodded. "Thinking about it. I'm not sure it really adds any value if you swear..."

Professor Dumbledore shook his head. "It would significantly compromise your neutrality if I you allowed me to join the negotiations without being sworn to you. Lucius would never accept it."

Harry nodded. He wasn't going to be stupid enough to reject Albus Dumbledore's offer anyway. And yet...

"Professor –" Harry asked, his mouth dry. "I need to know. Did you burn Narcissa Malfoy to death?" In this room, in this context of trust, with all the privacy wards activated, there could be no harm in telling him.

The old man remained silent for long seconds, a hard-to-read expression on his face. Then, he bowed his head.

"I did."

He looked up into Harry's eyes. "I did not make her suffer – not pain, at least, only fear. I used an anesthetic spell on her first – it was the only grace I could bestow. But kill her I did. It has haunted me ever since."

Harry nodded, a lump in his throat. He wasn't sure whether the formulation of his pledge to Draco quite covered this case, but the spirit of his conditions to take Dumbledore as an enemy had not been met. And without any doubt, the support of the great hero Albus Dumbledore, Chief Warlock and Supreme Mugwump, would be instrumental into securing the loyalty of a certain camp of politicians, which might be essential after the fallout from parts of the political spectrum following the negotiations. He could not afford to alienate the man any further than he already had, nor was there a good reason to.

He canceled the privacy protections, rung the little bell and held out his wand. The old man smiled somewhat sadly, knelt, and took it.

"Upon my life and magic –"

Harry thought he felt it, now. A small fraction of his magic set aside to maintain the three bonds, unavailable for other magic. It wasn't much – it probably wouldn't interfere with his usual spell casting – but still.

I should probably not do many more of these.

Although for that matter, another portion of his magic was constantly used to maintain the transfigured gem in his ring, and if magical power should become an issue...

"Professor?" he asked, as the ancient wizard stood up and the Auror had left. "Can I ask why you told me to carry around my father's rock?"

There was a slight smile, at that, although Harry did not see any twinkle in the eyes.

"Because there was absolutely no reason why you would," he answered. "Unless on some level, you trusted me implicitly."

Ah, Harry thought, glancing at the ring still around his finger.

"Even when I seemed insane to you, even when people tried to drive a wedge between us, you chose to go to a lot of effort to do something just because I might have had a reason to ask. While you did so, I knew that you still valued my counsel."

Harry frowned. Had the man been right? He hadn't really reconsidered the question whether it made sense to keep his father's rock around, recently; maintaining the transfiguration had become such a force of habit that he didn't really do it consciously anymore for most of the time, or associate the gem with Dumbledore – or even think about the stupidity of the whole arrangement at all. And yet, if he had decided that Dumbledore might mean him harm, and consciously reevaluated everything the man had told him, then he would not have continued wearing that ring. In truth, even though he had taken 'first steps" to making Dumbledore his enemy, at an emotional level he did still trust the old man, his heart if not his mind.

"That really is all?" Harry asked, removing the ring. If there was no point in sustaining the transfiguration, he might as well reserve his magic for better uses.

"There were side effects," Dumbledore replied. "While you worked on permanently sustaining a transfiguration despite your age, keeping the magic active even in your sleep, your magical strength in that direction grew – and Transfiguration is one of the most powerful and versatile magics to be adept with. I don't know in how far my nudge sparked your interest in that field, but I hope it helped a little, at least. I myself spent most of my school years sustaining a variety of transfigurations as a matter of course. However, I confess I could likely have achieved that effect simply by asking Minerva to suggest the possibility to you." His face clouded over at the mention of Minerva McGonagall.

Harry just nodded, putting the twinge of grief aside. That reasoning, at least, was remarkably rational. "Was there any similar kind of reason for the chicken?"

"Not really," Albus Dumbledore smiled. "I have long been doing things like that. You see, many people look up to me. See me as their god, in some cases. It can be relaxing to act a little strange towards children, in cases when my actions do not affect the lives of other people for once. As for why I acted that way to you –" he smiled wanly. "The hero cannot come to rely too much on others' judgment. I would have you trust me, but think for yourself. Although in hindsight I have realized that this act was not necessary in your case."

Harry nodded. He thought low enough of the former Headmaster's judgment without the help.

"Thank you, Professor."

The old wizard nodded. "I suppose I'd better get back to my work on the nation's traces. I fear I have a long night ahead."

Wednesday April 29th 1992, 8:44pm.

"Professor Snape?"

The greasy man carefully closed the door behind him.

"I have come to swear to you, Lord Potter."

Harry stared at him. "You want to join the negotiations?"

The Potions Master shook his head. "No. I wish to swear service to your House, permanently."

Harry was entirely lost for words.

"I confess that it will be distasteful, being sworn to the House of Potter," the man spoke after a while, "but I suppose it cannot be helped."

"Why?" Harry asked. "What do you stand to gain by surrendering your freedom?"

"I never have been free," the Potions Master said, almost angrily. "I have served others for all my adult life. Both of my masters treated me with some kindness, and yet –" he waved his hand irritably. "I would take the chance to serve a better master now."

"Why not just live for yourself?"

"I am not ready to live without a master. I might never be. Although as you may guess, there is more to this." He met Harry's eyes. "You realized the weakness in the mark, so to you, I can speak somewhat freely. Can you guess, Harry Potter?"

Harry thought about it. "The dark mark... does it work like the House Vow?"

"Not precisely."

"But partially? It allows him to kill you on command, without even having to point a wand at you?"

The Potions Master nodded, his mouth a thin line. "If he commands me, I must obey, or I will die. Indeed, I expect that he understands that I am not loyal to him – but his recent actions make it abundantly clear that he is unlikely to disapprove of loyalty to you. I believe he will not punish me for swearing to you. Yet having two masters provides a certain protection."

Harry considered this. "You think he will not order you to work against me?"

"There would be no point, as it would give you no choice but to kill me – and as he has nothing to gain from my death, I believe he will not try. Similarly, he stands nothing to win from giving me orders contradictory to yours, unless your commands are detrimental to him."

"Ah. So swearing to me liberates you from his control."

"In a sense, yes."

"Do you think that this reasoning played a role for Lucius too?"

"I don't know." Snape stared into space. "Albus has initially spoken very clearly of his beliefs on the Defense Professor's identity, and even though he was not taken seriously at the time, Lucius will certainly have heard the tale. He might not know what to think of it, as I also would not, given only what little information the Headmaster could divulge. However, he will certainly have taken the possibility into account, and will have noted that in his guise as Professor Quirrell, the man was pushing for you to gain influence. Whether, if he believes it plausible, he would prefer simply to follow our old master's guidance or to have some measure of protection against him I could not say for sure, although I would suspect the former is more probable than the latter."

Harry nodded. "Well. I suppose protection from a dark lord is as good as a reason as any for signing yourself into slavery. You just want me to keep the bond active, and forbid you from doing a number of things you definitely don't want to do?"

The older wizard shook his head. "I can do a lot more if you let me. I'm a moderately powerful wizard, Potter. I know you have plans to reshape the country, and I'll gladly help you bring them about."

Harry paused. He wants to actually serve me? What is this, Dark Lord Harry day?

"I know next to nothing about you, Professor," he said carefully. "You seem to think that I would be a better master than Dumbledore, and you seem to take this servitude thing a lot more serious than I have, so far – but to what purpose? What is it you hope to achieve?"

"Many things." He closed his eyes. "I was a good man once, or moderately good at least. Lily always brought out the best in me. I... I was weak, I tagged along with the other Slytherins. got intrigued by dark magic. But she always pulled me back. The way she preached about what Slytherin House was, what it ought to be –" There was a note of pain in the Potions Master's voice that sounded alien to it; it was hard to imagine it being the same acid voice that instructed children not to stir one more time unless they liked their wrists getting blown off. "I was a fool then, and I lost her respect. But it has shaped my later perceptions of the House, what it should be, and the painful reality of what it was. That's one of the things I wanted to do, to help bring back honor to the noble House of Slytherin, and since I have become more... perceptive, recently, it has become clear to me that the Headmaster has lost all hope. But you and Miss Granger were trying to do something, and you managed to bring over Mr. Malfoy and Miss Greengrass..." He shook his head sadly. "It is moot now, of course. The school is gone. But it is one of several things that persuaded me that your dreams are much like your mother's, even if slightly more ambitious."

Realization hit Harry as he parsed this information. "It was you who sent those notes to Hermione!"

Severus Snape nodded. "She was willing to do something, and I helped. I sent those notes. I pierced Jaime Astorga's shields, and watched to make sure they survived their following battles, although Miss Tonks's help made further assistance unnecessary. I had planned to use the final ambush as the perfect moment to make a vision of the ghost of Salazar Slytherin appear, but –" he shrugged helplessly. "That plan failed. And then, of course, the Headmaster asked me to protect the girl in the only way he saw, which put everything back to the status quo again."

Harry nodded. "And... forgive me for asking, but you mentioned my mother... surely you do not still love her?"

"I will always love her." His expression darkened. "I know she had her faults. Nobody is perfect, and it was foolish to put her on a pedestal for so long. But I still esteem her, and the things she believed in. She wasn't as shallow as you said, you know – she was more willing to put aside prejudices than most, even if she was sometimes too quick to jump to conclusions. When I insulted her, it wasn't the first time I betrayed our friendship, and she had always forgiven me before – but showing contempt for Muggleborns was the straw that finally broke the camel's back. She might have come to forgive me, in time, if I had shown her that I could be a better man. But I did not. Without her influence, I sank deeper into the dark arts, went along with some extremely misguided ideas, and became everything she had always told me not to be. And James – he improved." The pain in the voice was strong, now, and Harry thought that the man might be about to cry, impossible though that might seem, if his tears had not been cried out a long time ago.

"However it may be," the man continued. "I let my grief overshadow all other feelings. I followed Albus, because I thought that's what she would have wanted. I never even considered other women with feelings besides contempt. But in all that I did, I did not give one thought to what would be right for me to do."

"And what would that be?"

"I don't know, not exactly. When I was young, before everything went wrong, Lily and I spoke of many things. The war, politics, justice and compassion... She dreamed of a world without war and blood prejudice, where everyone would be treated equally. I dreamed of a world where someone like her and someone like me could be together without all the pressure to break up and go the ways dictated by our separate situations. We both wanted the same, in the end, and twenty years later, I still want to make a world like that – more realistic perhaps, but ultimately that. Unfortunately, I have always been a weak man. I cannot make her dreams, or mine, come true; I wouldn't even know where to begin. But I can pledge my life to someone better than me, who can."

Harry nodded, a lump in his throat, held out his wand, and rang the bell for the Auror.

Wednesday April 29th 1992, 10:44pm.

Nobody had brought him dinner.

Nobody had asked whether he wanted to go home or maybe to some kind of guarded hotel room to sleep.

The Aurors outside the door had changed, but they didn't really talk to him unless he asked them questions.

I guess this is what it means to be an adult. Nobody is supposed to take care of me anymore.

Should he send a Patronus and see whether Professor Snape would come and pick him up? Or maybe ask whether the Aurors would be willing to transfigure him a bed, and check whether Lucius or maybe Snape would be able to go to his parents' house to find a refreshment of clothes? Would there be a bath anywhere in this building?

The door opened slightly, and then closed again. Harry blinked. Then an excited voice squeaked from somewhere near the ground: "Harry Potter, sir!"

Harry stood up so he could look over the desk better. On the ground was a House Elf, dressed in a neat tea towel that did not look like the garment the Hogwarts Elves usually wore.

"Who are you?"

"I is Dobby, sir, Malfoy House Elf. Master is sending me to make sure Mister Harry Potter is comfortable." The Elf seemed to be positively brimming with excitement at the idea of making himself useful. "Master says to apologize for not thinking about it earlier. Does Master's master need anything?" The creature looked up with big, hopeful eyes.

Harry sat back in his chair with a big grin on his face. Goooood minion.

Thursday April 30th 1992, 9:00am.

"My greetings, prime minister."

The Prime Minister of the United Kingdom gasped as a bright silver man appeared before him. All conversation around the table – which had been tiring enough even for the early hour – stopped.

"It seems that our countries are at war," the silver man spoke, "when both sides would much rather have peace. Therefore, on behalf of Lord Harry Potter, who was elected to speak on behalf of all magic users in Britain, I propose a truce. Let us negotiate. Starting at noon, no one in Britain should use any magic that will affect non-magic users, other than in self-defense. In four hours time I will return, and ask whether you would be willing to set a time and conditions for a meeting. Naturally, the conditions are all yours to propose."

The glowing silver man bowed deeply, and moved sideways out of sight.

"I still don't see why you didn't want to give him a chance to answer immediately!" Cornelius Fudge exclaimed.

"He might feel overwhelmed, and therefore more easily reject our proposal outright if we put him on the spot," Harry Potter explained.

Lesath felt like he was soaring with pride to be part of this. This morning, he and the other temporary inhabitants of Number 12 Grimmauld Place had woken up to a letter delivered by Ministry owl, which informed them that absolutely no magic was allowed to be performed until further notice. After the initial shock, Professor Snape had explained what was happening at the Ministry, and Lesath had persuaded his Head of House to deliver him there, where he might also swear servitude to the new Lord Potter. His master had refused the servitude, however: Harry Potter insisted that Lesath could not take the contract until he was at least seventeen years old, even though he had already sworn, a vow of character as binding as any magical contract. But then, he had allowed Lesath to be of some immediate use instead: his Patronus had a more adult voice than Harry's own, so, after he managed to shape it like an adult man, had been the perfect messenger.

"And why did you tell him the conditions are all his?" The Minister for Magic was objecting. "That seems to be going a little far!"

"It establishes some measure of trust, by allowing them control. We can pose our own requests for modifications later – there is very little we need to ask for anyway."

"Should you not have at least asked for a meeting before the eyes of the country?" Professor Dumbledore asked. "That is what you suggested before the Wizengamot, is it not?"

"If I insist on that, they're going to assume that we can do something to enchant everyone who watches the events on television or something like that – which would be really interesting if we could pull it off, actually, but let's not go there. I'll suggest the possibility later, but don't want to give him the idea that it's too important. The chance that they'll go for a live broadcast to avoid deception is pretty high, anyway, and if not, they're bound to transmit the video afterwards if they're comfortable with the result of the negotiations."

Lord Harry Potter turned to Lesath. "Lestrange, thank you for your assistance. Are you available to do that again at one?"

He thought he saw the others in the room cringing at the use of his surname (at least the politicians – the Headmaster had never seemed to care much). There was something intensely satisfying about their discomfort, and Harry Potter's evident approval of him.

"Of course, Lord Potter."

Thursday April 30th 1992, 11:12am.

Harry lay on his back, staring at the ceiling of his office.

Calm. Planned. In complete control. That was the face he had to show to the outside world. But with no one there to see, he was allowed to doubt, at least a little.

What if I can't do this?

They'd accepted his expertise. They'd agreed to overlook his age, or even use it to their advantage. He had promised them, and himself, an end to a senseless war that could easily turn into a world war if mismanaged, not country on country but Muggle on Magical.

Just fix the world, Harry. No pressure.

Could it be that he was vastly overestimating himself? What if he only made things worse?

He couldn't be sure what Riddle was planning – he had a rough idea, but bits and pieces didn't add up completely, and it was entirely likely that the man would take offense. Was he just going to get himself and other people killed? And if not, was he going to ruin everything and launch the country into an unstoppable war?

There was no real answer. He had to work from the information he had, and do the best he could, adapting to changing circumstances as they came up.

Someone knocked on the door – probably Thicknesse. Harry drew himself up, sat down in his chair, and took a moment to pull the cold over himself like a mask. "Come in."

Thursday April 30th 1992, 1:00pm.

"Greetings, Prime Minister. Have you decided to meet with us?"

The Prime Minister drew himself up to his full height to address the strange creature. The people he had drummed up had debated all through lunch and although no one could quite agree on their demands, there was a general consensus that at least hearing what this "Lord Harry Potter" had to say might be worthwhile. He didn't trust that all the people in the debate were entirely on the same side – given the possibility of magical impersonification it would be insane to assume that everyone was themselves – but the decision had felt natural enough, at least, and he thought he himself believed it was a good idea. (It was very hard not to get paranoid in the presence of a magical enemy, however.)

"What exactly is it you want to discuss in that meeting?"

The glowing man disappeared briefly, and then returned. "How to achieve peace between our people. It will be much easier to speak face-to-face than using magical intermediates."

"But we wouldn't be safe if we met you face-to-face! We demand a video conference."

The glowing man disappeared, and reappeared again a minute later.

"Those terms are acceptable to us. Take whichever precautions you wish. Choose a room for the negotiations. Install cameras there. Submit the footing either only to your confederates, or to the entire world, as you wish. Allow an audience or ambassadors if you want. We only ask that you give us a few minutes before the meeting to guard the room against outside magical interference, and that you do not bring in more than forty people."

The Prime Minister looked at the others around the table. "How do we know that you will not trick us into accepting your proposals? Or subvert the cameras and make us seem to have agreed to an arrangement we have no intention of making?"

"We want peace, Prime Minister. Trickery is hardly likely to achieve that, especially since your people would likely see through it, and not accept any treaty that might result from such a meeting. Make whatever checks you deem necessary."

"Very well then." He glanced around, and saw nods around the room. "Tomorrow afternoon, at 2pm. Send this... thing to us an hour beforehand, and we will tell you the location."

The glowing man left and returned. "Thank you, Prime Minister." Then he bowed deeply, and disappeared.

Thursday April 30th 1992, 3:39pm.

"Another spell at Gloucester! Chopping hex."

"Damn it, probably just another person cooking. One day, is that so much to ask? We even listed Apparition spots to get cheap food and other commodities! Bahry, take your team over there."

Amelia Bones noted down the time and location and put it on the stack. Every 45 minutes, one of her Aurors would take the notes back in time to the special team, who invisibly investigated the disturbances just beforehand, and left an instant before the normal Aurors arrived.

"Sparkling charm down Liverpool! We have an attack!"

"Komodo, Butnaru, Goryanof! Get over there!"

"Can't!" Komodo yelled an instant later. "Blocked apparition!"

"Johnson! Do you have an exact location on that one?"

"Yes!" The Auror ran in from the alarm room with a piece of paper and flung it into Komodo's hands, just as Auror Dimitriov yelled "Illegal Apparition in Keith! Unregistered person!"

It was going to be a long day.

Thursday April 30th 1992, 6:43pm.

"My spies report that the building the Muggles will most likely use is here," Lucius Malfoy said, indicating a place on a large projected map of London. "It looks like they are ready to receive us in style. It's a palace."

"Windsor Castle," Harry nodded. "That's pretty impressive. And given its importance and location, that probably means they aren't planning to employ any weapons of mass-destruction on the area while we're there."

"Have you assembled your team yet?"

"Yes. You, Albus Dumbledore and Pius Thicknesse have all agreed to come, and taken House Vows to ensure non-interference. Two others have inquired whether further members were needed, but with Mr. Thicknesse representing the Ministry and you and the Chief Warlock representing the Wizengamot, I believe this is already fairly spread around, and we cannot bring too many who do not serve an obvious purpose. With the three of you working together and a team of Aurors on Apparition standby, I think we should be safe from Muggle attacks, especially if we check for mines or other weaponry beforehand. We should also prepare for the possibility that any wizards who do not agree with the solution we might reach choose to attack us, however. If the Muggles broadcast the negotiations live to the entire country, as I expect they will, other wizards will immediately know what is going on."

"We will employ all available resources of the Ministry to protect the castle," Cornelius Fudge instantly brought forward.

"We do not know for sure whether it's going to be there," Harry pointed out. "And the Muggles would be very put out if they got any hint of us interfering with the location beforehand."

"Well, I'm sure that we can do some decent protections at a moment's notice too..."

"I shall count on that," Harry nodded. "With one constraint: if you're setting up anti-Apparition wards, I want Lord Malfoy and Mr. Thicknesse to be able to either bypass them, alone or with someone else, or to drop the wards altogether to allow Aurors in. If two of the three are unconscious or otherwise incapacitated, they should also drop. Is that doable?"

"Yes," Albus Dumbledore answered.

"Wonderful. And in case the Muggles are brave or silly enough to have us talk with representatives who are physically there, I think it may be a good idea if we can ask Hermione whether she wants to join." Harry had given this a lot of thought over the last day, and while he didn't like putting her in danger, she was in fact one of the safest people to bring along. Any attack that a person with instant teleportation could not get out of was likely to kill anyone on the spot, and they were guarding the location to the best of the Ministry's abilities. "She will be able to bring the representatives to safety if necessary, while Professor Dumbledore may stay behind to ward off attacks." Which was part of the reason, although mostly he wanted her along because he suspected she might have valuable input. The adults could not interfere inappropriately, but that didn't mean they had to like where he was going, and they wouldn't fully understand the Muggle side of things. Hermione would be able to bring her own ideas to the table, and stop Harry from doing anything overly stupid or evil.

"I would not expect any attacks that would make such precautions necessary, Lord Potter," Lord Malfoy said with a frown. "But if you do bring her, might I suggest also bringing my son, Draco? If you, a child in their eyes, surround yourself with a guard of three adults and one other child, they will conclude the two of you are equals. If two children guard you, you are still central."

And you want your son to be at least equal to Hermione in status, Harry thought. Although the point is probably valid. "I am concerned for your son's safety, Lucius."

"Even assuming your concerns are valid," Lord Malfoy said smoothly, in a tone that suggested in the politest possible way that he didn't give this idea much credit, "we can protect him easily. An emergency portkey, perhaps. That should leave him in no more danger than the Granger girl, and I assume Albus will be shielding our group regardless. I can guarantee that Draco will not unduly interfere – and if you have doubts in that regard, he is young enough for me to silence him wordlessly."

Harry hesitated. It was a stupid risk to take, but perhaps Lucius was right that it wasn't that much more dangerous for Draco than for Hermione. There was a very good reason to include Hermione, but there was a solid political reason for Draco, too: if he wanted to keep Lucius's loyalty, Draco was the key.

"I'll think about it," he said, not wanting to commit immediately. Lucius Malfoy nodded. "I suppose I shall have to be content with that. Now, as for your clothes –"

Thursday April 30th 1992, 8:19pm.

Harry had invited her to his office.

His office.

She trudged through the stone corridors (Xare couldn't bring her to a place she hadn't seen before), through the door she had been directed to.

It was a waiting room. Two Aurors stood guard in front of the inner door, wands already pointing at her.

"I – ah – have an appointment?" she squeaked.

Twenty checking spells later, some prodding with a strange device, and her wand getting confiscated, she was finally ushered through the door.

And there, lying on his stomach on the fluffy red carpet, was harry. He was writing in some kind of notebook.

"Hey Hermione," he said happily when she came in. "Come in and sit down."

She closed the door behind her and plopped down on the carpet beside him. "Why exactly are we on the floor?"

"I got tired of sitting all day. That chair is a little too high for me." He shrugged. "Anyway, we need to talk."

"About how you suddenly seem to be Minister of Magic or something, and everyone is referring to you as 'Lord Potter'?"

"Well, not quite the Minister of Magic. I'm just in charge of negotiations with the Muggle world. I suppose I could use those to put myself in charge, but that's not really the point of all this."

"Harry! What is going on?"

"Well, first of all you should know that the Minister of magic doesn't really have all that much power. The real decisions are made by Lucius Malfoy and Professor Dumbledore, and they can't agree on anything."

"I guess I can see that," she said, thinking back of her first trial.

"Now," Harry continued. "Normally that's not much of a problem – sometimes one of them wins, sometimes the other, life goes on. But right now, we're in a crisis situation, and neither of them has managed to propose a solution that a majority will go along with. Dumbledore told me that they couldn't even propose a solution that made sense to themselves; they were fighting over the direction to look in. And that's not even going into all the chaos with their own backing being split between terror, hatred, contempt or ambiguity towards Muggles."

"So they involved a third party," Hermione said, understanding. Harry nodded. "And naturally," she resumed, "they chose an eleven-year-old child to be that party."

"You know I'm not really eleven, Hermione," he said soberly. "I'm not sure what I am, but the child-label doesn't really apply to me anymore. Even less than to you."

She nodded, knowing perfectly well what he meant. "So what exactly is the arrangement, then?"

"They voted to view me as an adult for the law, so I am now Lord Potter," he ticked off. "I have a seat in the Wizengamot. They followed my suggestions to put the country under a trace to guarantee everyone plays nicely. And they gave me complete rights to negotiate with the Muggle government and make any promises on behalf of the wizarding community of Britain that I deemed necessary. They said they'll stick to it, too."

"Oh." She considered the list. "That's quite a bit. Are you sure they will stick to it?"

"The Minister's Secretary has written a contract on those lines, and then got most of the Wizengamot to sign it. It would take a 90% majority of the Wizengamot to go back on anything agreed upon with the Muggle government in less than a year. Given that it's hard to get the Wizengamot to agree on anything, such a majority is very unlikely to happen, especially since going back on the contract means war, which more than 10% will probably consider a sufficiently terrifying prospect to go along with pretty much anything. And they can't just ignore an agreement sealed in that way without uprooting the foundations of the current government, which includes their own seats of power."

"Right," she nodded. "And this is absolutely not going to end with you putting yourself in charge of the entire country?"

"Would I do that?" He asked innocently.

She felt a feeling of panic rising in her chest. "Harry..."

He grinned. "I take it you don't trust me at all."

"Not on this." She didn't have nightmares about him threatening to kill off half the Wizengamot for her anymore, but that was only because Xare stopped that kind of thing.

"You're probably right about that." He heaved a deep sigh and rolled over on his back. As though by an unspoken command, the lights in the room dimmed to not shine in his eyes. "But I'm not going to do that. I will be responsible for getting a binding deal with the Muggle Ministry that is to the benefit of both our people, though."

Hermione contemplated this, only a little relieved. "That's still an awful lot of responsibility. I wouldn't like to be in that kind of position."

"Well, that's really inconvenient because –" he stopped himself.

"What?"

"Nothing. Well, there is something. I wanted to ask whether you're willing to come along, tomorrow. There are going to be three adults to help me with the political aspects, but none of them are Muggleborn and I think you could have some good feedback. Besides, if it all goes to hell, I think you and Xare may be needed."

"What? Why?"

"Well, for a start, I'm afraid that there's a reasonable chance that Riddle – You-Know-Who – may end up making an appearance. The Aurors are doing anything they can to avoid interference, but, well... In case they fail, I need someone to get any Muggles who may be in the room out of there immediately while Professor Dumbledore keeps him distracted."

A shiver ran through her body. "You want me to face Voldemort?"

He winced as she said the name and she felt the shiver in her own body too, but he didn't mention it.

"You have faced him several times this year, Hermione," he reminded her instead. "You stood up to him in our first Defense class. And later, you and Draco tried to get him to ban traitors."

She looked down. "I still can't really think of him as the same person as... as You-Know-Who."

He snorted sadly. "And you at least always thought he was evil. I have a lot of trouble with it too." He sighed. "But anyway, that's the world we live in. Will you come?"

Her stomach wrenched. It was scary. Terrifying, even. If Voldemort – Quirrell – came, wouldn't she be the single most defenseless person in the room?

No, she realized. That would be the Muggles.

"Fine," she said, hugging her knees. "I'll go. Who else is coming?"

"Professor Dumbledore," he ticked off. "Pius Thicknesse – he's the Minister's Secretary. Lucius Malfoy."

"Lucius Malfoy?" She knew all the stories about the man, and she remembered, the ice-cold voice sending her to Azkaban... "Couldn't you ask for someone else? Anyone else?"

"I chose to include him, actually."

She stared at her best friend. "What in the name of... of I don't even know what, possesses you to choose to bring along Lucius Malfoy?"

He held up his hands. "I know he's evil, Hermione, you don't need to lecture me on that. He's tortured and killed a lot of good people – Dumbledore has done some of that too, mind, but not as much, I suspect. Anyway, the reason I'm bringing Lucius along is that he will be useful. He will bring valuable points which can help us avoid alienating a certain side of the political arena, and just his inclusion will already appease a lot of powerful people. I couldn't just push him by the sidelines without generating heat for the treaty we're going to make. But he's under a charm that enables me to kill him at will, so I don't think he is likely to do anything that would cause problems."

"Would you kill him if he did?" she asked quietly.

There was silence, for some moments.

"Probably not," Harry admitted. "But there's a way to twist the spell so my choice is not required. If he does something out of line, I can order him not to interfere again on pain of death, and then if he does, it will happen even if I don't do anything else – it's entirely his choice between life and death. And I wouldn't necessarily have to kill him; they all swore by their life and magic. I can burn the magic out of them."

She nodded. "That's something at least."

"He also suggested I bring Draco," he added.

"Draco?"

"I'm not sure I want to do it. It just seems like an unnecessary risk – the problem is that to Lucius it doesn't seem that dangerous. With Dumbledore protecting the group, we don't really have much to fear from the side of Muggles, and he doesn't see Riddle as a threat. In fact, he's probably right about that – with regards to Draco, at least. Even if Riddle ends up interfering, we already know from before that he doesn't want Draco dead."

"But why would you bring him in the first place?"

"Partly as balance for you – three children and three adults looks better than two children and three adults, especially if one of the children is the main negotiator. But more importantly, for political reasons. Draco is likely to have some useful ideas to add to the discussion, and if he manages to make a good impression tomorrow, it will really help his future influence. Lucius wants that, of course – and I'll lose some of his support if I exclude Draco while still including you – but I actually agree on the point that it's useful. If I can help putting Draco into a position of future power, would that be worth a relatively small risk, if he himself is willing to take it?"

She shifted against the wall. "You want to put Draco into power?"

He nodded. "He's been trained in politics for all his life. He knows all the machinations and the people, and, by virtue of his birth, automatically comes with a fair bit of support from the older families. In a few years, he'll be perfectly placed to lead Magical Britain."

She felt her heart skip a beat at the prospect. "Harry, I'm not sure this is a good idea." She'd been... conflicted about him, lately. He had been helping her, had actually confessed under Veritaserum that he hadn't been plotting anything sinister. He couldn't be completely bad, and yet... "Do you know what he said – do you have any idea –"

"Yes."

"You don't," she said firmly. "You cannot possible know what he's been telling the other Slytherins he would do to me, given the chance." She hadn't told him, when Daphne had quietly informed her, because it was just too horrible to talk about. But if Harry was really convinced that Draco was a good person, good enough to put in charge of the entire country, she had to warn him, before he made a big mistake.

There was a short pause. Then Harry nodded. "I can make a good guess. Rape?"

She nodded, shaking. "And then Obliviate me, and do it again. He said he'd make it his Christmas Treat."

Harry closed his eyes. "When was this? At the start of the year?"

"I don't know," she said, trembling, as the conversation came back to her. Daphne had told her only after Draco had picked her up from the ground, but the girl hadn't named a period. "Does it matter? Don't say it's because he didn't know me at the time, that he turned nicer when he did, because that makes no difference. If you can think of doing that to someone, whether you know them or not, you're evil, Harry."

"I wasn't going to," he said, scrabbling up to sit next to her so he could put an arm around her and give her a comforting hug. "I know he thought like that at the beginning of the school year. He told me he was planning to do it to – to a ten-year-old girl."

"And you still made friends with him? And want to put him in charge?" Her voice rose to a shriek.

"Hermione, it's not like that. I don't think he changed just because he got to know you, although that certainly helped. I think he just got a lot better and more aware of other people's value over the year. I may have helped a little, of course."

She frowned at him. "You really think you can change someone like that?"

"He was never really a bad person, Hermione. He was just raised to think that, well, that that sort of thing is what the cool kids do when they grow up. He's spent the first eleven years of his life being raised by Death Eaters! Of course he's going to have some twisted ideas. It would've required a supernatural intervention for him to have your morality given his environment –"

Hermione bit her lip. It was such a stupid, such a Harry explanation. The situation was so obvious. If you fantasized and bragged about raping little girls, you were a rotten person inside, plain and simple. It didn't really help if you were from a family of Death Eaters and considered it completely normal that your father regularly murdered people either.

And yet.

Draco had helped her. He'd started working together with her for his own sake, but when he'd caught her on that roof, she'd had to tell him twice to let her go. And then he'd picked her up from the ground, and he had testified under Veritaserum that it hadn't been a plot, he really had just been kind – or at least trying to show the Slytherins a better way, as Harry had told her. And then, in that last trial, he had willingly come to her and Harry's aid, asked for Veritaserum and testified that he believed in her innocence.

"I always thought good and evil were easy," she complained quietly.

Harry laughed. "Yeah, that's probably not entirely true in the real world. But is it really so hard to believe that people can change?"

She sank bank in his comforting arm. "No. I guess not."

They sat in silence for a while. Finally, she got up.

"I had better get back. The whole escape plan in Grimmauld Place is focused around me, so the others feel a lot safer when I'm there. But this office is not phoenix-blocked, is it?" He shook his head. "Good. Just send me your Patronus when you need me."

At the door, she turned around one more time. She couldn't quite put in words everything she wanted to say, all her worries of everything that could go wrong, but she couldn't just leave either. He looked so tired and burdened, this ruler of the country, as he pulled himself up and sat behind his desk to receive whatever important visitor would come next. And yet she knew only she was allowed to see him like that; soon enough he'd be wearing the cool mask again in which he had twice faced down the Wizengamot.

"Take care, Harry," was all she knew how to say.

He watched her go, nervous but determined to do what she could to make things better, the phoenix on her shoulder.

He hadn't told her.

He had wanted to tell her what he'd done to her today. She had the right to know, if anyone. But she couldn't guard her mind, and she might be in mortal danger if anyone of ill intent should find out about the arrangements he made in a private meeting with the manager of Gringotts in the afternoon.

It had taken him only minutes to figure it out, after Lord Malfoy had left: the obvious way to end a House Vow was to end the bloodline. And it was not too long after that when Thicknesse had sought him out to discuss the rather great likelihood that the peace negotiations would take too long to resolve in one go, and the question of what should happen if he died in between sessions. There would always be some who might be less than pleased with his choices in the first session, so the number of people wanting to kill him was likely to go up astronomically.

Both questions had the same solution: naming an heir. If he died, the heir would inherit any magical family effects, such as the bond, and that would work even if it wasn't a blood-heir. Pius Thicknesse would adapt the contract to specify the "Head of House Potter" as negotiator, without specifically giving a name.

Harry had made a list of possible heirs, who would inherit under the circumstance that he would die childless. Amelia Bones was at the top of the list, along with a number of other sensible, powerful witches and wizards, who would likely be able to ward off attacks on their person. He had chosen not to reveal the names on the list; the goblins would reveal the length if anyone should ask, but not the contents. That, hopefully, would stop people from killing him, as his enemies could not hope to get him and all of his potential heirs who might be even worse. Even if they did, it would mean that at least the negotiations would fall to a competent person.

And in his will, he had left every single one of these people a letter, to be given only if they inherited, instructing them to let Hermione Granger take the final decisions, but never to let anyone know about this for the sake of her safety.

There were other things in his will, Open lines of research that he thought should be pursued. Money to be given to his father, Hermione, and to science funds. A wish to be indefinitely preserved under the anti-decomposition charm until they could revive him, even if the possibility of that might depend on the particulars of his death. Once he had started to write things up, there had been a lot of aspects to think of, even though thinking of the possibility was so uncomfortable that he really didn't want to.

Still, he had. He wasn't planning to get himself killed, of course. But he had to be prepared.

Friday May 1st 1992, 2:03am.

Don't be so sure that there will be other choices beyond this one. There is no road-sign set, to mark the place of your last chance to turn back. If you refuse one chance will you not refuse others? It may be that your fate is already sealed, even by doing this one thing.

Harry turned and twisted in his sleep, on the camping bed Dobby had brought him, while a trio of Aurors still stood guard outside his door.

Professor Quirrell is sucking you into the darkness, Harry, he really is.

While he was awake, he could rationalize what he was doing. Promise himself to follow Hermione's morality. Make plans for the future of the world – a good, humane future, with all darkness eventually banished to oblivion.

I wonder whether there will come a day when I regret not killing you when you were in my power, Mr. Potter.

But his half-sleeping mind kept bringing back warnings. Kept reminding him of all his mistakes that might just mark the fork in the road to his becoming a Dark Lord greater and more terrible even than Voldemort.

Upon my life and magic, I swear service to the House of Potter –

Half asleep, half dreaming, Harry's mind played out a vision of the masses bowing down to him, hailing him as their leader.

And he was about to betray them all.

Chapter 110: Negotiations, Pt 2

Hermione tensed, ready to whip out her wand and slow the staff's momentum before it would cause a national riot by breaking Queen Elizabeth's leg, but the precaution was unnecessary. Harry had warned her of this move and so she had been prepared, but looking to the side, it was quite evident that he had not seen fit to inform the others of his plans.

Lucius Malfoy was rapidly moving from wide-eyed shock to seething anger. Pius Thicknesse looked like he'd just had a bucket of cold water dunked over his head. Draco was staring at Harry in absolute horror. Professor Dumbledore did manage to keep smiling genially, but the smile definitely looked a little frozen.

Do not react! came Harry's silent command. And compose yourselves! Remember: there is a whole art form of manipulating others by allowing them to be dominant over you. This is only the start.

You are playing with fire, Potter! Malfoy hissed, but he did recover his stature and acted like nothing out of the ordinary had happened. So did Thicknesse. Only Draco still looked upset, but then, he was the only one who couldn't die on the spot for annoying Harry.

The staff fell on the ground before her feet with a gentle clatter. The Queen's eyes snapped up to the wizards' faces. Shock, anger... only for a brief moment, to be almost instantly replaced by complete calm. Only the other young boy's face still betrayed his consternation. She could almost think she'd been mistaken about the expression on the adults' faces, but she had seen it, and the others must have too.

Could it be that the child was actually in charge? And that he had taken a step of this magnitude without consulting his companions?

No, surely not. The magical government could not be so void of common sense as to put their fate in the hands of a teenager, especially not without putting checks on him. If they had, they would now be very sorry indeed. But it was unlikely. Wizards could take on the appearance of anyone they chose; more than likely the child was a powerful adult mage with a deeper plan. Everything could be an act, and probably was.

No, this surrender was not promising, not under these circumstances. It was too obviously a plot. The question was: who or what was the plot against?

She just stopped her hand from moving towards the amulet that hung over her heart. The amulet her father had passed to her, the reason she had asked the Prime Minister to lead today's mission. The amulet which was supposed to give protection against, and control over, magic users.

If only she had any clue on how to use it.

"So... you... surrender?" the man who had been introduced as John Locker spoke after some long moments of silence. "You will remit all magic users to our custody, and cast the spells we ask you to?"

"I said surrender, sir," Harry said coolly. "Not slavery. As we are all humans – and indeed, most of us are British citizens – we have rights by national and international law, and your own legal code forbids you from discriminating against magic users based solely on their ability. But the Ministry of Magic will come under your authority, and our people shall be required to abide by your laws and courts. We will provide complete transparency as to how our world and magic in general function, except in those cases where the knowledge would be dangerous, as previously explained. You will be able to pass laws restricting magic use, and have our magical law enforcement office at your disposal to enforce them."

Even without a wand, no Muggle jail could ever hold a wizard, Thicknesse observed.

I know, Harry replied. So they'll need our help. That's what I'm counting on.

So you're just giving everything away on the off-chance you'll be able to bargain back basic rights? Draco bit.

Yes, Harry replied acidly. And if it all goes completely to hell, I'm sure your father won't mind shooting me before I sign the treaty. Now will you please stop glowering? You're undermining our credibility..

"As for doing magic on command," he continued as though the brief mental conversation had never taken place. "Slavery is of course out of the question, but I imagine that, if you allow it, willing witches and wizards could offer their services to Muggles for money. To this end, I humbly ask your permission to rebuild our school – which was bombed last week – and use it to teach young magical children how to use magic responsibly, following the laws you impose."

Harry – Dumbledore began, and Hermione's thoughts flashed back to the man's warnings about magic causing widespread poverty in a few generations. Harry didn't respond to Dumbledore, but continued smoothly: "although we may want to talk about those services with various interest groups, and discuss how to set them up without putting people out of jobs, completely wrecking the Muggle economy and turning this into a major political issue."

A woman – Rosaline Munster – bent forward with interest. "What kinds of things can you do?"

Harry beamed brightly. "A fair few. As you already know, there are potions to repair or even regrow limbs and skin; it is entirely possible that our Healers will also be able to assist with other diseases which are currently hard to handle, or at least with diagnostics. We have near-instant travel, and while the magical expenditure increases both with distance and weight transported, I suspect we should still be able to find a way to employ this to drastically reduce reliance on fossil fuels. There are magical ways to force truth, which could be useful in law enforcement – although it would have to be severely restricted for privacy and availability reasons. We can ward important government officials from magical attacks or impersonification. And, of course, it would be most intriguing to see what phoenixes can do for the British Space Program."

He held up a hand. "However. There are not many of us. Thousands to your millions, and the number of qualified Healers, Potioneers and Aurors is but a fraction of that. We cannot solve all the problems in the Muggle world, not even a small part, no matter how much we would like to. I have a list here –" he retrieved a scroll of parchment from his robes, "– with a number of proposals to limit these issues."

John Locker grimaced. "This is starting to sound a lot less like surrender."

Given that you did not see fit to show us this list beforehand, Malfoy growled, I suppose it does not contain an independent magical government?

"These proposals are in your interest, sir," Harry said politely, ignoring Draco's father altogether. "If we allow capitalism to take its natural course, it would soon cause wealth to flow to a select elite of magic users, wrecking your economy and creating enormous friction between those who so happen to be born with the talent and those who are not. What is more, if too many magical Healers are drawn away to healing Muggle ailments, then wizards can no longer be guaranteed magical treatment – which will have disastrous consequences for people's willingness to perform important but dangerous jobs like guarding dragons or growing magical plants, never mind the consequences for potentially lethal magical diseases like Glowpox or Spattergroit. Hence the suggestion that a council of experts from both our worlds should approve any potions given to, or spells performed on, Muggles. For example, for magical healing on someone hurt by strictly non-magical causes, I would propose a 900% tax, which is automatically invested into open research for non-magical cures for the same issue. If magical solutions actually manage to cause a significant reduction in the need for oil, then the cost saving should be invested into the development of sustainable, preferably magic-free, energy, and this should be done in close collaboration with the countries and companies who now mine oil and gas, so nobody loses their job. And truth-potions should be treated with at least the same caution as fingerprint evidence."

John Locker snorted. "Reading between the lines there, you want to put a close check on any magic that actually gets performed for us, and you want a 'council' – presumably your own government – to approve any changes. Surrender in name, but no real changes, is that your idea?"

"Not quite. None of the items on this list are demands," Harry responded, unfazed. "They are suggestions, to avoid a public outcry, a mass exodus of magic users, or a treaty that seems good but ends up accidentally flinging the country back into the Middle Ages or destroying the planet. You can simply tell us all to leave your country or never use magic here again, although if you want witches and wizards to actually enforce this, you will have to make at least some allowances. What I am proposing is simply a solid debate on how to carry on without destroying both our societies." And yes, you guys will get to talk there. "In the end, there probably just aren't enough of us to systemically provide object-level improvements, like healing potions or instant transportation. We want to look at where magic can achieve the most good, and this optimal use will most likely be in, or in combination with, scientific research. Magical techniques and the knowledge we take for granted might for instance be used to build a space elevator, find a way to deal with nuclear radiation, figure out how the human body works in order to fix aging, discover the gaps in the laws of physics and hopefully even figure out how magic works..."

He trailed off. Hermione, looking sideways, saw his eyes widen, and her wand snapped into her hand almost instantly. She had already jumped up when he yelled: "Get out! Hermione! Draco!"

She dashed towards the Muggles, yelled "Catena Magnus!" as had been drilled into her for the last four days. Waiting only just long enough for the shimmering blue chain to appear and bind the Muggles, she grabbed the Queen's arm and burned them all to the Department of Magical Law Enforcement.

They arrived in the luxurious room in the DMLE amidst screams and outbursts of "What?" and "How dare you –".

"I'm sorry!" Hermione exclaimed. "I think he was coming! I had to get you out!"

"The agreement was no magic on us!" John Locker shouted, even as Hillary Toney asked "who was coming?"

Hermione stepped back, pushing down her panic, trying to find words to explain. Of course they wouldn't understand, they didn't know... "The dark wizard, the one Harry talked about, he was coming. I had to get you away, it was my duty."

"You knew he might attack us?"

"I demand to be brought back!"

"No!" She yelled. "He'll kill you!" She had just abducted the Queen and several high-level diplomats. It could be enough to cause a war, if handled badly, but how could she make them see that it had been absolute necessary?

The Queen made a calming gesture with her hand.

"How old are you, child?"

"T-twelve."

"And how did a young girl like you get roped into this war?"

"I'm a friend of Harry's," she answered. "I mean, Lord Potter. And there's only two people in the country with a phoenix, and so I had to come, so I could get any Muggle representatives out if You-Know-W- I mean, the dark wizard, should find out what Harry was doing and take offense."

Before the Queen could ask anything else, a woman had appeared in the doorway.

"Ah, Miss Granger," she said briskly. "I'm glad you got them all out, the man cast anti-Apparition and anti-Phoenix spells only moments after. Your Majesty –" she curtsied to the Queen, "– honorable representatives, we do apologize for the inconvenience."

"And who are you?" John Locker asked warily.

"I am Emmeline Vance, an Auror – you might say senior police officer. The dark wizard Lord Potter spoke of has attacked Windsor Palace. That's an extraordinary risk for him to take; as we speak, our people are guarding the palace with our strongest wards to stop him escaping, and he will have to get past the most powerful wizard in the world to get out. We hope to have the situation under control within the hour, and then, if you are still willing, we might be able to resume peace negotiations without interference from a powerful madman bent on causing chaos. In the meantime, can I offer you some refreshments?"

She waved her wand, and four long sofas appeared, as well as a grand, throne-like but soft, one-person couch and a child-sized cushioned chair.

"Thank you, I should like some black tea," the Queen answered calmly, sitting down. "With a piece of lemon, please."

Emmeline Vance nodded, and left the room. Hermione had her doubts about the amount of confidence the Senior Auror radiated in the presence of their Muggle guests, but it was calming. The woman returned within a minute, floating in three large tea pots, several slices of lemon, sugar cubes, and ten crystal teacups.

"Director Bones says that we can channel the television broadcast to this room," she offered. "It will take a minute to set up or so, but we've got one of our technical people on it. I need to go now, but ring the bell if you need anything else, we'll have someone over immediately."

"Wait!" John Locker exclaimed, as the woman made to leave. "Are we prisoners here?"

"Of course not, sir," Emmeline responded. "You may leave any time you want. Miss Granger here will take you wherever you want to go." At that, she turned and left. Aurors probably had something more important to do than entertaining Muggles, now that Voldemort was almost in their hands.

"You can take us anywhere?" Hillary Toney asked Hermione.

"Any place I know," Hermione corrected. "I need to at least have a photograph. But that's one of the things phoenixes can do."

"Can they go to the moon?" Edward Smith asked with interest.

"Well, I haven't tried, but I don't see why they couldn't –"

His eyes lit up. "We will have to try that. Screw the Americans and their space program, with instant inter-planetary travel we could start colonizing other planets in a decade! That's what this Lord Potter boy suggested, wasn't it?"

"Well, I'm not sure it's wise to go quite that fast –"

She was interrupted by Harry's voice as, on the wall, a high-resolution TV projection appeared.

"– figure out how the human body works in order to fix aging, discover the gaps in the laws of physics and hopefully even how magic works... Get out! Hermione! Draco!"

"– figure out how the human body works in order to fix aging, discover the gaps in the laws of physics and hopefully even how magic works..." He trailed off, his heart sinking as the familiar sense came over him.

A feeling of doom.

"Get out!" He yelled desperately. Hermione was already jumping up. "Hermione! Draco!"

In a blur of movement Hermione jumped to the Queen as, on his other side, a confused Draco fumbled with his portkey ring, the wizards behind him sprang to their feet and behind the representatives, a man appeared. The feeling of doom intensified, just as the Muggles and Hermione disappeared and Draco gasped in shock.

The Asian man in black robes was young, and did not look like Professor Quirrell, but it was him alright. He shouldn't have been able to get through the wards, not without at least triggering a warning that someone was casting magic, but perhaps he had been there all along? The Aurors had set up wards to guarantee that, aside from the six-man negotiation committee and a number of Aurors checked with Thieves Downfall, no one magical entered within a one-mile radius of the palace, but perhaps a snake hidden in a magical pouch, handbag or other assortment from one of the representatives could have bypassed those tests... The Muggles had been sitting far enough away from the wizards that Harry would not have sensed the doom. Damn it, why didn't we test for magical items?

"Hello Tom," Professor Dumbledore spoke wearily, wand in hand.

"I'm not here for you," the man said dismissively, raising his own. "Harry Potter."

Let me talk, please, Harry asked. Draco, can't you get out? Lucius?

Apparition is blocked, Malfoy spoke grimly. As are portkeys.

"Lucius, protect Draco and maybe see about getting out of here," Harry commanded out loud as he stepped forward towards the enemy, biting back against the powerful sense of doom. Lucius couldn't help him against his old master, but after Snape had spelled it out for him, he at least had some idea on how to keep the man from using Lucius against him. "But on your life, do not interfere!" He turned to face the former Defense Professor, who regarded him coldly. "Hello Professor."

So are phoenix and time travel, Dumbledore added.

And don't move further, or you won't be in my shield.

"This is not," the man spoke in menacing tones, "what I had in mind when I taught you how to lose, Mr. Potter."

"I know it looks bad," Harry replied, "but ultimately it makes little difference. Muggles understand how much magic can offer them, and will easily grant liberties in exchange for the protection, healing and insights into the workings of the universe that we can offer. And if it doesn't work out for us, we can just find another country."

The cameras are still running, Dumbledore warned him.

"What is more," Harry resumed, "this course of action seems to be the best way to achieve lasting peace, not just between Muggle and Magical but also hopefully world peace. If we can combine magic with science to figure out how nature really works, we can collectively transition to a post-scarcity society all the sooner. And then –"

"You haven't got a clue," Riddle interrupted. "Yet you meddle in things far above your head. And what makes you even think I care?"

Harry blinked. He'd been working from the belief that Riddle cared a whole lot about the world not getting blown up in a nuclear war. He had hoped the Auror protections would manage to keep the man out long enough to get to the arrangements he might approve of, but apparently, it wouldn't have mattered.

"You speak passionately of secrets not meant to be shared," the man spoke, his ice-cold black eyes boring into Harry's. "You have seen, a mere week and a half ago, the consequences of sharing dangerous knowledge with those who cannot protect their minds. Five days ago, you have witnessed the results of allowing power to slip into the hands of those who have not survived the lesser trials. And yet you deem it wise to allow naive idiots, tied into ideals of openness and institutional structures based around publishing results for the world to see, to analyze magic? You would squander our safety for some misguided ideal of progress. Do you wish to bring about the end of the world? For you could hardly be more efficient if you tried!"

His wand whipped up, pointed at Harry's heart. "Avada Kedavra."

Before Harry could fully realize what was happening, he was forcefully pushed aside and fell over to the ground. Someone – Dumbledore or Thicknesse – must have rushed to his defense, but Riddle hadn't been aiming at him. At the last moment, his wand had twisted upwards and the green light hit Fawkes. The fire-bird was engulfed in flames, then fell to the floor as a little chick, small, wrinkled and flightless.

There was hardly even time to think. Dumbledore was already shouting a terrible incantation and Pius shot a Stunning Charm at Riddle, who half-jumped half-rolled away from where he'd been standing, and suddenly the room lit up with a massive white flash. A giant white-golden bird sprung from Dumbledore's wand and flung itself at Riddle, but he waved his wand and five bright green snakes appeared, grabbing and biting at the magical bird. He aimed his wand at Pius, and suddenly the man's expression changed and two killing curses buried themselves in the ground to Harry's left and right. Dumbledore turned and blasted Pius away, and in the opening Riddle threw something at the three of them and an enormous explosion tore through the air and through Dumbledore's group shield. Dumbledore stood his ground but Harry was blown backwards by the force. Something else hit him in the side, and before he could respond, heat and pain exploded inside him. He was burning, thrown off his feet, his skin ripped away. He crashed into a wall and fell down in a crumpled heap, on top of his right leg which snapped beneath him.

"Gaaah! Aguamenti!" But there was no response, the magic failing him. He looked down at his hand, blackened and broken, holding the shattered remains of his holly-and-phoenix-feather wand.

A splash of water from Dumbledore dowsed the fire from his robes. Riddle paused briefly, apparently surveying the damage he'd managed to do. Fawkes and Thicknesse were out of the fight, Harry was wounded and magicless, and Malfoy, under orders of non-interference, had crawled into a distant corner where he protected Draco with his own body. Dumbledore stepped in front and a little to the right of Harry, his wand ready. Riddle smirked.

"Let's keep this between you and I, shall we, Albus? It's been a while since I had a decent duel."

"I hope you enjoy it," Albus Dumbledore said coldly. "For it will be your last one, Tom."

"Oh will it?" The dark-robed man smiled pleasantly, as though they were having a friendly conversation over dinner rather than a duel to the death. "You are not as young and sprightly as you once were, old man. Can you still pull twenty hours, do you think? And can you spare the energy to defend others as well as yourself?"

Chapter 111: Negotiations, Pt 3

Shouts rent the air in the DMLE survey room as the dark-cloaked wizard appeared. "Hello Tom," Albus's voice spoke on the screen.

"It's him!" Amelia yelled. "Scrimgeour, surround the castle. Get any Muggles out of the way, but do not hurt them. We are not going to let the bastard get away this time! Emmeline, handle the Muggles with Granger before they get upset. Shacklebolt, get me the status on those wards! Komodo, stand ready to break in!"

Everyone jumped into movement except for Moody, who kept surveying the screens. The main one showed the view from four of the Muggle cameras, while three screens on each side of the room detailed each of the scrying wards. The Muggle ones were better positioned to give an overview of everything that was going on – and more importantly, they showed what the Muggles were most likely seeing – which was why they'd brought in Muggleborn Maria Ackerley to tap some of them and channel their output to the DMLE.

It didn't take long for Kingsley Shacklebolt to return with his report. "Looks like he caused a magical disturbance the moment he appeared, and the magic interfered with our anti-Apparition and anti-portkey wards, which caused them to fall back to the basics, losing the exceptions. That's why Malfoy could not get out, but Granger could – there were no anti-phoenix wards yet, so his magic didn't affect them. We got the control back now and reopened the exceptions, but he's already added complete wards of his own."

"Can we stop him from dropping our wards?" She asked.

"Should be, Madam. He could interfere with them, but that only made them stronger. Removing them altogether or even punching through would require a lot of power, and we've got thirty Aurors reinforcing those wards. With Dumbledore fighting him, I can't see it happening."

"Excellent. See about piercing his wards, but keep ours up." She stared viciously at the figure on the screen. This will be your last mistake, Voldemort.

A white blast lit up the screens, and then all four Muggle camera views dulled.

"That must have been deliberate," Ackerley observed, trembling. "He doesn't want Muggles to see what he's doing."

"I concur. But the Muggle broadcast has a delay, doesn't it?" Amelia asked, thoughtfully. It was perhaps not top priority, but she had already set her people on the important tasks, and there were consequences to everything. Keeping the Muggles in the dark was not likely to be in their interest now.

"About five minutes," Maria nodded. "I suspect they didn't want to submit it live so they can shift between camera views, and perhaps give warnings if their representatives are unexpectedly killed."

Emmeline Vance rushed in from the next room, where the girl would have taken the Queen and representatives. "I think I calmed them down, but they're not happy. Can we send the footage there?"

"Not now," Amelia snapped. "Maria, can you send our own view back over those camera connections?" Maria nodded, sweating, and already started muttering enchantments. A witch living primarily in the Muggle world, the woman had been known to the DMLE only as a miscreant who had received a formal reprimand for enchanting Muggle artifacts a few years back. Fortunately, it seemed that from her Muggle job she was at least a little used to working under pressure. "Use the Dumbledore, Malfoy, Potter and Granger views – the last one so they can see their Queen is safe. The technical Muggles can figure out what to do with those images."

She turned to Emmeline. "We'll set up a delayed screen for the representatives once that is accomplished. Are you almost done? I may need you."

"I promised them tea, but that shouldn't take long. Granger can take it from there."

"Shoo, then."

Blasts of lights in all colors flew around the room. The white-golden bird Dumbledore had conjured snatched up another one of the snakes, as Dumbledore's spell just missed Riddle and harmlessly exploded against an overthrown socket, with a gong-like sound. Harry himself lay in a corner, protected by a shield from Dumbledore, trying to get his thoughts straight despite the pains in various parts of his body.

What is Riddle doing?

A burst of magic struck three feet away from him, collapsing the shield and blasting him further against the wall. Blood trickled down his face, even as a quick charm from Dumbledore's wand healed the wound and numbed the pain. Riddle hadn't aimed a spell at him, he still couldn't, but he'd thrown some kind of magical item.

It would appear, Slytherin suggested dryly, that he is trying to kill us.

Didn't we believe that that was completely against his plans? Hufflepuff asked timidly.

We believed many things, Ravenclaw pointed out. Perhaps it is time to reevaluate them.

(Riddle pointed his wand at a chair near Harry, which suddenly evaporated. Almost instantly, Harry's head was surrounded by a Bubblehead Charm. A transfigured gas?)

All right, Harry thought. He had believed that Riddle feared another world war. Using nuclear weapons, Muggles could destroy the earth and drag wizards down in their demise. Riddle, however, acted as though this was not a concern to him. Perhaps it was a ploy, but now that Harry actually thought about it...

If you're a rational person at the height of the cold war, wondering how to stop global thermonuclear warfare, the obvious solution is not to execute a convoluted plan where you set up a villain, create a hero for everyone to follow, conquer the world and have everyone live peacefully ever after. You would definitely not continue to drag your feet on this project for twenty years while every single day can bring the wholesale destruction of the earth.

(Draco yelped as his father flung the two of them out of the way of a ray of green light that had been shot in their direction.)

It was amazing how obvious that one was in hindsight. Harry had actually considered sending Muggleborns around military bases to avoid nuclear weapons getting launched; if he could think of that, someone like Quirrell had either done it several decades ago, or come up with something better. Precautions like that might be discovered after a single nuclear test that he didn't know about in advance, but since a wizard of Dumbledore's caliber was demonstrably able to divert a nuclear missile, it might be enough to set up a warning system to at least know when and where missiles were about to strike. Or for that matter, if you wanted to avoid discovery, you could put an Imperius Curse on all the people responsible for launching those things. Due to democratic processes the actual leaders would change regularly, but the people on the ground might not. It would be entirely natural for Riddle to place someone like Stanislav Petrov under the Imperius – in fact, it was completely plausible that he had.

(The shield around Harry was broken again, and Harry felt a sharp sting as his shoulder was hit by an ordinary bullet.)

So where does this put us? Slytherin questioned as Harry bit back against the pain.

He had the war under control, but he still had other fears, Ravenclaw suggested. There are quite a few ways to destroy the earth, or at least humanity. Pollution, malevolent AI, genetically engineered bacteria ending up in the food supply, not to mention the lump sum of "everything else we wouldn't even think about". There's just no telling what scientists are going to do.

He needed to throttle innovation, Slytherin nodded thoughtfully. Or at least to push new developments into the right direction, and make sure they were done by people who understand how to manage power. Given that this is the exact opposite of what we just proposed doing, he may have concluded that we are a lousy pawn.

(The ceiling shook and cracked, and then the wall Harry was resting against half-collapsed. He tried to push himself aside but he was too weak; he had no hope of succeeding. Stones fell all over his body and legs, cutting and bruising, but at least bounced off the Bubblehead.)

I still think we don't have the complete picture here, Ravenclaw observed.

In case you haven't noticed, we're dying, Harry's common sense snapped. Perhaps we should get to the finer points of the twenty-year plan after we do something about that?

Another flash of white light completely obscured their vision on the screens. The battle was every bit as spectacular as the legendary duel between Dumbledore and Grindelwald was said to have been, so Amelia had had to ban everyone who wasn't actually useful from the DMLE premises where they tried to watch. They would get to see it afterwards anyway, even without judicious copying of omni-oculars: the Muggles had unquestioningly accepted the wizard coverage of the event, and she had learned, in the past two weeks, about such things as video recorders. Although they might not get to see it to the end; the scrying wards on Thicknesse and Potter had already failed, and Granger's weren't very useful.

"What's the update on the wards?" she barked into her mirror.

"We can get through them," a sweaty Kingsley reported. "but it will take time. Which ones should we focus on first?"

Phoenix, portkey, Apparition or Time-Turner... Time-Turners were too fickle, she couldn't risk that, and if they took down portkey or Apparition they'd have to drop their own wards to allow a team through. But if they breached the phoenix wards...

"Phoenix," she ordered. Dumbledore wouldn't be able to use it – his phoenix would take at least a day to recover far enough to transport people – but another phoenix user could bring in reinforcements and get the boy out. The old meddler was obviously stretched too far, trying to protect the child as well as fighting his powerful opponent, but he was clearly not willing to sacrifice the boy for a greater chance at victory.

Should she ask Granger to get ready? Or were there other phoenix users available? The situation was far too dangerous to consciously send a first-year child into, and she didn't want to risk losing both British phoenixes in one day. Besides, the girl wouldn't have the magical strength to summon Potter if necessary.

"Is Barnok still around?" she asked. None of the foreign phoenix casters had been willing to interfere too much in a domestic dispute between wizards and Muggles and risk the responsibility of dragging their own countries into it, but this was a little different. And the Ethiopian wizard, coming from a land with no magical schools or authorities at all, was the most unconstrained of the phoenix owners.

Emmeline jumped up. "I'll get Lesath to contact him."

Harry wondered whether the fight would last long enough for him to die a natural death. He was still losing blood, and the agony of his wounds was starting to get less, which was probably not a good sign. He was also getting a bit whoozy in the head.

Think, he ordered himself. Think, think!

He had no way of getting out and reaching a healer without help. Fawkes was chirping sadly under a pile of rubble somewhere, and should be counted out of the fight. Hermione had only been instructed to keep the Muggles safe; if she was going to come back for him, she probably would have already. Dumbledore was a little too preoccupied to heal him. If he asked Malfoy to help, his old master would kill him on the spot, so it would have to be a winning move to be worth the sacrifice.

Another blast was stopped just in front of his face as Riddle danced around the battleground. Harry could hardly understand all that he was seeing – the duel was so far above his head that it was difficult to keep track of. An army of Aurors could not have touched either fighter as they danced around, shot powerful spells at each other and the room, summoned creatures to help, broke the rules of transfiguration, flung objects around... Two of the walls were down. Parts of the ceiling had caved in.

Yet he could see that Dumbledore was losing. The old wizard was fighting defensively most of the time, as he had to defend both himself and Harry. His shields could take almost anything, but the shields he wrapped around Harry could not, and he couldn't safely position himself at places where dodging a Killing Curse might get Draco or Harry hit instead. The only saving grace was that Riddle could not directly attack Harry with magic, but the former Defense Professor seemed to have brought a large supply of weapons – both magical and Muggle – to hurl at him.

If he couldn't get out, the only way to survive was to win. He couldn't win on power, and he probably couldn't win on brains either, but perhaps he had a chance by doing something completely unexpected?

Managing to do anything at all in our current state would be unexpected, Slytherin pointed out.

He still had the communication pin, and since it used the magic of the speaker to work, Riddle might not be able to intercept that. If he asked Dumbledore to lift him with magic and use him as a shield... what would happen?

Interacting with Riddle's magic would likely kill them both. The resulting explosion from their magics spinning out of control might collapse the castle as well, kill Dumbledore, Lucius and Draco, but would hopefully stop short of turning London into a large crater in the ground.

Would that be worth it? Riddle intended to save the world – quite possibly had saved the world already, maybe even more than once – but his goals clashed with Harry's values. If Harry was going to die regardless, was it sensible to try dragging Riddle along?

No. He can't die.

But if that was true, why was he fighting at all? Why didn't he just drop a massive bomb and kill them all? Why wasn't he at least sending Killing Curse after Killing Curse at Harry? If this was just a body he was possessing, like Quirrell's had been, why wouldn't he sacrifice it?

I notice that I am confused.

The answer came to him immediately. He isn't trying to kill me. If he was, I'd be dead.

It was a ruse, it had to be. Riddle could kill them all any moment he liked – but he didn't want to kill Harry. He had a deeper plan.

Was the plan to get Harry to "kill" him, as he'd intended to do all along? Unlikely: if it was, he would have needed to leave Harry able to actually do something, not hurl him into a wall and break his wand in the first move. It also seemed implausible that Riddle would still trust Harry's judgment.

Perhaps he intended to steal Harry away and keep him around under some permanent unconsciousness spell as a horcrux? Or more likely, he might still have plans for his traitorous pawn. Would it be possible to get full control over Harry's body, negotiate in his place and get him to make a few convenient changes to the planned treaty that the Wizengamot had already committed to accepting?

Polyjuice Potion, Ravenclaw suggested. The Imperius Curse won't work, but maybe Legilimency? Moody did say he was an extraordinary Legilimens, he could probably get past our shields.

Not without our magics interacting, Slytherin contradicted. But there may be other ways, darker rituals. Or he could get someone else to use Legilimency on us – Moody almost got through our shields in less than a minute, and he is supposedly not anywhere near Riddle's league.

That would take time, however, Ravenclaw pointed out. Even if he manages to get past Dumbledore, half the DMLE is on us, someone is going to break through eventually.

But he had a Time-Turner, didn't he? All Riddle had to do was abduct Harry, force him to take them both back in time six hours, and use the time to get control over Harry. Then he could bring him back the moment they left, set off a massive explosion that Harry miraculously survived – or indeed, something that Harry would be credited for – and continue the negotiations. After his old mentor aired his objections to Harry's plans on national television, the controlled Harry would have reason to specifically add more precautions and steer away from too much science in magic, and Riddle could get his plans back on track. It would require a lot more oversight in the long run than the original plan of letting Harry grow into it, and the people around Harry were bound to notice the changes, but it could be made to work.

Dumbledore will not let that happen, Gryffindor pointed out. Riddle may well take out the cameras, scrying and the Malfoys, but if he abducts us, even briefly, Dumbledore will notice, and he'll tell everyone. Remember that he has the elder wand, so his shields should be pretty much impenetrable. It's not easy to get him out of the way. The Aurors probably will not leave Riddle enough time for Dumbledore to fall over in exhaustion.

There is one obvious way to kill Dumbledore, Slytherin pointed out. Which conveniently coincides with getting control over us. How long do you think we can hold out under torture, to prevent ourselves from using the House Vow bond to take his life? Perhaps even Legilimency suffices. And we can't drop that bond without a working wand.

Harry swallowed, and blinked some of the blood out of his eyes, trying to see what was going on. The two wizards were still fighting their epic duel. Dumbledore seemed more powerful, but Riddle was more ingenuous, and Dumbledore was heavily handicapped by having to defend Harry.

Harry tried to clear his head, getting his conclusions straight. He was starting to feel dizzy, and it wasn't helping.

In summary, he decided, he isn't trying to kill me. He's putting up a show, to make Dumbledore and the Aurors believe that he is trying to kill me. When the opportunity arises, he's going to take out the scrying wards, kill or stun Draco and then abduct me – the Aurors' wards have an exception for me, so he can just throw me a portkey. Then he'll blow up the building, break all the wards, escape his host body and join me. We'll go back in time, he or his servants spend six hours getting control over me, or they just use Polyjuice. In the unlikely event that Dumbledore survives the explosion, they'll torture or manipulate me into killing him anyway, and then I get portkeyed back, or maybe stay where I am and claim I just managed to use an emergency portkey before the explosion. The negotiations continue, now with a slightly more cowed and cautious Harry, and he'll plan from there.

Those are a lot of assumptions, Slytherin put forth. There are ridiculously many parts we could be wrong about.

It's one explanation for what could be going on, Ravenclaw replied. There may be many more. What we know for certain is that he isn't fighting all-out, which may suggest that his goal is not to kill us. We can also postulate with high probability that if he has a dastardly plan, he probably wants to execute it without being seen by the entire DMLE, which means he has to take out the scrying. So we plan accordingly.

Is the answer that we ought to die? Gryffindor wondered. For the sake of the world?

And then what? Slytherin bit. Don't you think he's taken that possibility into account? Several of those attacks could have killed us already, and if he doesn't hurry up we'll be dead from blood loss. He prefers not to kill us, but I don't think it's a necessity. If we die, the negotiations carry on with Amelia – he probably doesn't know that, but he knows there's going to be someone – and he picks up the pieces. If he sets his mind to it, he should be able to kill any heir he doesn't like within a few days. Maybe not Dumbledore, but he is not on the list, and Riddle is hoping to kill him today. If that doesn't work, he Imperios the Muggles instead. The treaty becomes more harmless, and although he doesn't have his puppet to rule the world anymore, he'll just start over. Perhaps he'll even use Hermione – in fact, given that she does have a somewhat obedient nature, she may not be able to resist the Imperius Curse. That, or he could possess her. And thus the wizarding world gets united behind a strong leader after all.

Harry groaned at the mental image of Hermione being forced to become a puppet dictator.

Should we lose? Hufflepuff wondered. If this is what's going to happen with his backup plan, is the original better?

Don't you dare, his inner Hermione protested. He is evil, and so are his plans.

His values are not aligned with ours, Gryffindor agreed. He would stall progress and turn Muggles subservient. But maybe there's a way to win? Dumbledore is failing because he expends too much effort protecting us; if he stops doing that, he may be able to kill the body, at least.

This is Professor Quirrell, Slytherin answered. He always has a fallback. He knows Dumbledore is powerful, and yet he sought a direct confrontation. He wouldn't do that if he minds dying. Even if Riddle is superior – which isn't obvious – Dumbledore could get a lucky shot in. But it probably wouldn't be very hard to trigger some magical effect at the point of your death. If that effect touches us, it will cause an explosion that will kill us, and probably take out Dumbledore and the Malfoys as well. Just how impenetrable do we think Dumbledore's shields are? They probably couldn't withstand the force of an atomic bomb – can they really take the worst Riddle can dish out?

There was only way to stop the disaster, and to at least save Hermione and Draco. Riddle had to be gone. Permanently. Preferably without setting off any triggers.

How do you kill someone who is immortal?

Were there any Dementors left in the world? If he could get a message to the outside world, could someone go back in time and spend six hours searching the world for a Dementor, and then get it here in time?

Unlikely. Governments of all countries had already spent more than a week searching for left-over Dementors, without finding any. If there were any Dementors left in the world, they wouldn't be easy to find.

If he broke the Time-Turner, would it cause strange happenings that could buy him time?

Unpredictable. What was more, if Riddle saw him mess with the Time-Turner's shell, he would interfere, quite possibly by killing everyone on the spot.

Was there any way to create Dementors?

He didn't know. There were so many facts in his possession, so many books he had read, that his brain would never be able to sort through them in time. But there was one person who might be able to.

With a deep breath, Harry plunged himself into his dark side.

The crystal clarity came over him, ignoring the pain and everything around him, as the drowsiness in his head departed. Rapidly, the cold started browsing over everything he knew, coolly considering the problem at face value.

It was his dark side, after all, no matter who it might originally have belonged to.

Find out a way to go back in time to before Dementors were destroyed? Unlikely to work.

Search Britain for depressing places? Most of the searching had been done elsewhere, but the Birmingham Dementor showed that the British Isles had not been entirely Dementor-free. He filed that notion away for future reference.

Was there anything said about Dementors that might be relevant? He considered all he remembered, but nothing came up.

What magical knowledge did he have about death?

Ah.

It was only one idea, but it fit. Fit so well that he immediately knew that he was right.

Dumbledore danced in front of him again. Harry screwed up his eyes, and spoke with a quiet mental voice: I have an idea. I think I can speak without being intercepted, but if you cannot, do not respond.

He will not hear, came the answer, two blasts later.

Do you know of a ritual that involves a rope and a sword, and is used to summon death?

I have heard of it, the old wizard's mental voice replied after some moments. Ah. I see. Do you think – ?

Do what you can to get someone to execute it, Harry said urgently.

Are you sure?

Quite. Also, beware: he isn't really trying to kill me. He may transport me away. He will likely take out the scrying first. Sacrifice me if you must. Don't make it obvious that you suspect. Kill me yourself if it's the only way to stop him from taking me.

There was a long silence, with three more spells falling and Dumbledore both rolling out of the way of a killing curse and deflecting a projectile thrown at Harry, and then he replied. All right.

To Amelia's side, Mad-Eye Moody gasped. She turned.

"Amelia, I need a Time-Turner right now."

The Queen startled as on the screen, the battle began. The young girl – Hermione – winced as she saw her friend hurled into a wall and set on fire. She'd gone completely white after the "Avada Kedavra". Elizabeth couldn't help it. Her fingers found the amulet, warm and comforting beneath her dress.

Do I trust these people?

Of course not. The battle might easily be a setup, staged for the benefit of the audience. The child-king "Lord Potter" was hardly believable. And yet, she found herself touched by the young girl, an instinctive trust that this person, at least, was genuine. Perhaps it was a foolish mistake, but she had to choose some side.

She made her decision. She had no idea how to use her amulet, but perhaps the wizards did.

"This is not looking well," she observed calmly.

"No," the girl said with a slight tremble in her voice. "And this is on a time delay, so it's been going on for a few minutes already. For all we know, it might already have ended."

A sobering thought. The Queen pulled the amulet out of her dress, the blue sapphire glowing with power.

"I have inherited this from my ancestors – it's supposed to give the monarch of England both power and control over witches and wizards. I don't suppose I could help?"

The girl stared at the sapphire with wide eyes, then fumbled for her wand. "Expecto Patronum."

"Yes, Albus conjured an invisible message in the air," Moody said irritably. "I have to go to Flamel, persuade him to teach me a ritual, and then get over there as soon as possible."

"But we can't get you there!" Amelia exclaimed. "We still haven't taken down the anti-phoenix wards."

"Then I suggest you hurry up," the pock-marked man snarled.

A glowing silver woman appeared in the air and spoke in Hermione Granger's voice: "Madam Bones, the Queen has a device to give 'protection from and control over' wizards. Do you know what it does? Mr. Thicknesse mentioned something like this."

Emmeline appeared with a crack. "Here's the Time-Turner, lock-free!" Moody snatched it from her fingers.

"Set some bloody good historians on this, Mad-Eye!" She yelled. He nodded grimly and Apparated away.

Harry felt like he was slipping into the darkness, but he forced himself to remain alert, to watch the battle. How long had it been? Five minutes since the start of the fighting? Ten? Long enough to put on a show, certainly.

Now that he knew what to look for, he recognized the signs of the subterfuge. Riddle kept attacking him, but the attempts were half-hearted; Dumbledore could block them all, although the efforts left himself open to attacks and with few opportunities for his own attacks. Dumbledore was the intended target, or perhaps just his scrying knob. Riddle flung the occasional Killing Curse at the old man, but attempted nothing that would be absorbed by his shields; instead, he relied on blinding lights, shock waves, gases, transfiguration.

Then suddenly, Dumbledore was flung sideways, apparently without any conscious decision of his own, and a ray of green light buried itself into the wall behind him. Harry's head snapped to the source and he saw Lucius Malfoy, standing upright now, eyes full of hatred, sending another Killing Curse at the back of his ally and lifelong enemy.

Without his will or conscious decision, Harry's magic reacted, and he felt it lash out over the bond of the House Vow. The noble lord gasped, then collapsed onto the floor, killed by Harry's command.

WHAM! An enormous explosion drew his eyes back to the ancient wizard. Lucius's attack had done its damage. In the moments of distraction, Riddle had hit the old wizard, or the ground beneath him, and the man was flung across the room, landing hard against a wall. Still his shields protected him, but a thin line of blood trickled down his face.

Alastor hadn't been gone a second when he returned, a thin man in tow. "Barnok!" He barked. "Get ready!"

A woman burst through the door, carrying a paper. "Here's the requested data, Madam Bones. But it's really obscure, I couldn't find anything more recent than eight centuries, and even then it was highly restricted knowledge."

Amelia snatched the paper from her hand and read it. Then read it again to be sure she hadn't misunderstood.

The crowned Monarch of England, apparently, was the official ruler of both the Muggle and magical side of the country. Merlin himself had created a device to encourage compliance and given it to King Arthur. No magics could be wielded against a monarch wearing the amulet, and a simple incantation could strip a witch or wizard of half their magic while they remained inside England. The boundaries of "England" weren't very clear, but Amelia hoped that at least London would count.

It was the perfect solution, if the Queen would cooperate. The man fighting Dumbledore was insanely powerful, but with half his magic gone, the tide of the battle was likely to turn. There was just one downside. If the Queen realized what power she held; if they asked her to use it, it would be close to reinstating her authority. There was no going back: they would have to follow through with Potter's plans for surrender.

Gasps in the room revealed something important had happened. Looking up, all the screens had gone blank.

Amelia made a snap decision. She turned to the human Patronus, which was still waiting for her answer. "The Queen must hold the amulet and say: 'gehæftan Voldemort dwolcræft'. Then do the same with 'Tom Riddle' instead of 'Voldemort', just in case."

She ignored the gasps around her as she said the name. "Reinforce the portkey, Apparition and Time-Turner wards, and pour everything we can into breaking his anti-phoenix ones! Barnok, be ready! Bring those two in, get the children out, and then get back here for reinforcements!"

I'll be damned if I let this bastard get away.

Albus Dumbledore desperately lifted himself to his feet. He had survived, and Harry still lived, but Malfoy's attack had caused unrepairable damage: his scrying ward was gone. Without a doubt, Malfoy had taken his own and his son's as well. This was what Harry had warned him for, the moment Riddle would strike.

He flung another shield in front of Harry, surreptitiously anchoring him to the ground, but it wouldn't hold for long, and Voldemort would notice. He had to do something more, but he wasn't ready. The Aurors had laid the ground work of taking down the wards, but Voldemort was powerful, and the man was right, he had grown old. He could maybe take down those wards, but breaking through well-cast wards took far more power than keeping them up; it would expend all his power, and it might not be enough. If he failed, he was dead. But then, if he didn't try, they would lose too, wouldn't they?

There was no choice. He had to hope Alastor and Hermione were ready, and that his contributions would be enough.

Voldemort stumbled.

Albus didn't hesitate. Not wasting any time to wonder what was going on, he slammed everything he had into the anti-phoenix wards.

With a burst of flame, three men appeared.

A phoenix fluttered over to Harry, as he saw the African wizard dash towards Draco. The two men – Remus Lupin and Mad-Eye Moody – were chanting in a strange language Harry did not recognize.

Riddle had fallen to his knees, but he was already jumping up, wand pointed at the newcomers, his face turned snakelike in fury. "Avada –"

"Morturi!" Lupin completed, and something burst through him, a wound, a hole in the world, darkening and expanding. Even as Remus Lupin fell down and the green light from Riddle's wand buried itself in the wall behind him, Moody yelled "Parma!" and the thing threw itself at Riddle.

"No!" he shouted, backing away, but all the anti-Apparition charms were still active. "Avada Kedavra!" Harry just saw the green death rushing towards him, then planting itself in the wall beside him as Moody summoned him out of the way. Riddle's eyes widened in fear as he fell over, shaking, and the Dementor grabbed his arms.

"Go to Bacon's tree!" he yelled, just before the Dementor closed itself over his mouth and with a sucking sound ended his life.

What? Harry thought.

Lupin's wand flew up from the ground and hovered before him. "A Patronus, Potter!" Mad-Eye Moody shouted.

No time to think. He snatched the wand out of the air, emptied his mind, brought up the image of the stars, and promised himself he would save everyone. "Expecto Patronum!"

It felt wrong.

He had just asked his allies to create a Dementor, and had willingly caused a man to die. Could he still believe in saving everyone, in ending death, after making that choice? Would he ever be able to cast a Patronus again?

As the Dementor, alerted by his cry, flew towards him, the answer seemed an obvious no.

And then another young boy's voice cried "Expecto Patronum!"

"Draco, I'm going to die."

The voice emanated from what seemed to be the person holding the camera. The magical screen which had been set up for them had been limited to single viewpoint, from a slightly moving source at a far end of the room. Hermione had had her suspicions about that, but she had kept them to herself.

The young boy's face looked anxious, as a hand stroked his forehead and removed the little knob. "No father! Just stay here, we'll be fine."

"I will not be." The voice from the perspective sounded pained. "I have been commanded to strike or die. No matter what I do, I will be dead in two minutes."

"No, father, there has to be a way!"

"There isn't. Son, listen to me. Forget what I said before. You are the next Lord Malfoy, and you will be the greatest one who ever lived. Follow your heart and your mind, and don't repeat my mistakes. I was wrong... in so many ways. I know that you will do better. I love you, son."

"I – I love you too, father." The boy was crying now, and Hermione felt a lump in her throat. She had neither really known nor liked Lord Malfoy, but he obviously cared for his son.

"Don't cry, Draco," the voice spoke. "I am free to do as I wish at last. And now –" his voice took on a bitter tone "– I will avenge your mother. Stupefy."

The boy sunk backwards, unconscious. Within moments, the angle of view had turned around at the battle and was moving towards it. One, two shots with roaring incantations, both missed. And then a strangled sound, right before the screen went black.

There was silence, for a time.

"It seems to be going rather badly," the Queen said, after a while. "Do you know whether my amulet had any effect?"

"I don't know," Hermione answered helplessly, still wiping away her tears. "I could ask Madam Bones, but she's probably very busy. Professor Dumbledore is really powerful, though, so they may already have won, but –"

"But so is the other guy, yes. Well, Hermione – that is your name, isn't it?" She nodded. "Our people are not entirely helpless either. I would appreciate if you could tell us a few things, if Lord Potter hasn't sworn you to secrecy."

"Anything you want to know, Your Majesty," she answered. "Actually, he isn't my lord, just my friend, and I think you are formally the ruler of Magical Britain anyway. That's why you had that amulet."

"Am I? That is convenient." The Queen smiled, a gentle, grandmotherly smile. "Then please start by telling me all that you know about this dark wizard."

Draco stood, crying both in grief and in joy, by his father's body, as his Patronus shielded the Boy-Who-Lived and the others.

It was the first time he'd managed to do this version of the spell. He had tried over and over, first on that Monday and later in his own room. But for all his lessons from Harry, for all his attempts, the spell hadn't worked for him. He'd asked Padma about it, and Rianne Felthorne and even Cedric, and they'd all said much the same, some mumbo-jumbo about defeating death. He'd sort of got the idea, but he didn't really see the point. And then finally, he'd gone so far as to ask Lesath Lestrange, who had simply said "the darkness can be broken". And that made sense, with Harry's unique view on the world, but Draco still hadn't been able to do it; he couldn't make himself believe in Harry's dream-visions.

Not until his father had told him that he believed in him, and that he should follow his own ideas.

He held the thought, struggling as his Patronus wavered. It was a near thing, he knew, and it was taking all his effort to not make it go out, but it was all that was standing between his allies and the darkness, so he held on.

Harry scrabbled up with some help from Barnok. Most of his wounds were gone now, although his ribs still felt cracked, and his leg was broken. Phoenixes really were marvelous creatures.

He stared at Draco, trembling in a corner, maintaining his hold on a True Patronus with obvious difficulty, his father's corpse by his side. Harry's heart wrenched at the sight. His order to Malfoy, and his own magic, had orphaned the boy – it hadn't been his intention, and even now Harry couldn't see a way in which he could have avoided it, but he felt the responsibility all the same – and despite this, Draco could find it in his heart to protect Harry.

Moody was already casting spells over Riddle's body. Lupin lay dead. Barnok and his phoenix hovered near Harry.

"I'm okay," he told the African wizard. "But I'm not sure Draco is, and I can't cast a Patronus at the moment. Can you get Hermione or Lesath, just in case? They should both be in the DMLE."

Barnok eyed him over, then conjured up a walking stick, pushed it into Harry's hands, and disappeared.

"Open the floodgates, Draco."

Draco turned to find Harry standing next to him. He shook his head. "I can't."

"You can," Harry said gently, but with conviction. "This may be the only chance you'll ever have. Believe it, and you can do it."

Draco swallowed, and screwed up his eyes, concentrating. He just heard the sound of the phoenix's reappearance, probably with someone else to help. But this, he would do himself.

The Patronus waxed, slowly but certainly, as Draco let the brightness fill him.

We shall see each other again in the afterlife, father, he promised silently. But until then, nobody shall ever die unless they're ready. Not if I have anything to say about it.

"It is gone," Barnok whispered. "Well done, boy."

"Thank you, Draco," Harry whispered. "And I'm sorry. I'm so sorry."

Draco nodded. He had better be.

Harry dragged himself over to where Dumbledore was gazing sadly at Lupin's corpse.

"I never meant to kill anyone else," Harry said guiltily.

"Remus was always a brave man," the former Headmaster observed. "Didn't you know that the ritual has a significant chance of killing either caster, if the sacrifices used are too old?"

"No," Harry said softly. "Quirrell didn't mention that part."

Dumbledore glanced at him. "He was the one who told you about this?"

"I daresay he didn't understand the relevance at the time," Harry shrugged. "I only just figured out the Dementor thing."

Dumbledore caught his eyes. "Only just? What would you have done if you were wrong?"

Harry was silent for a while. It had been so obvious that he hadn't really thought about the possibility that the ritual did anything else. But if he had been wrong... Would the True Patronus Charm have helped against whatever representation of Death the ritual summoned?

"I see," the old wizard said calmly after some moments. "We have been very fortunate today, but I must say that I shall be considerably more restrained following your instructions in the future."

Harry nodded. "Did you cast the anti-decomposition charm on Lupin and Malfoy?"

The old wizard sighed, and started casting.

"Come on, boy, get outta here so the Aurors can fix the place, and the medi-wizards can fix you."

Harry was staring at the lifeless body of Tom Riddle. There was no intellect in it anymore, the life was gone, and yet the body was still breathing.

What had he meant with his final words, about Bacon's tree?

"Don't worry," Moody's voice growled behind him. "I'm not mad enough to let anyone kill him. We'll put the body in prison. Just in case."

"That's not – never mind."

"You're new to this, aren't ye?" The man spoke more gently now. "Never been in a fight to the death before."

"Not like this. I never had to decide to kill someone."

Alastor Moody nodded and put a hand on his shoulder. "You'll get over it. It's not a pleasant thing, but you're still alive, and that's what matters." He tried to steer Harry away.

"No. Wait."

Harry limped towards the breathing corpse. There was not the slightest feeling of doom about it, even as he touched the hand and carefully took the ebony wand out of it.

He didn't feel anything. The dark lord was supposed to have his brother wand, as Ollivander had said, but this was not the one. Riddle had fought with a wand that was not his own. He had known that his body might die, and prepared for it.

"Let's go, sonny, and get you patched up. The day is not over yet. Not by far."

Emmeline Vance Apparated back to the DMLE to give the diplomats the news. It had been only fifteen minutes since the duel had come to its end, and her head was still spinning, but she'd been ordered to move swiftly. Amelia had given her a quick rundown of what seemed to have happened and told her to get going; it was essential not to leave the Muggles hanging for too long. Not just for the sake of politeness, and not only because these were the people – or at least connected to the people – with their hands on the massive Hogwarts-destroying explosives. But also because, as her Director had impressed upon her with a strained face, the Queen was undeniably their ruler now, and she held the power to create a lot of trouble if they got on her wrong side.

Emmeline quietly opened the door.

"– battles were really educative, although I suppose you might say in hindsight –" The girl stopped mid-sentence as she heard the door opening and jumped up. "Auror Vance! What's happening?"

"Good news," she quickly said. "We won. Voldemort is dead, and Albus Dumbledore and Harry Potter have survived." She saw the child slump with relief, but still looking anxious, so she quickly added: "So did Draco Malfoy and Pius Thicknesse. The only other ones who died today were Lord Malfoy and Remus Lupin." She felt a lurch of sadness with that last name, but this was not the time to mourn.

Hermione Granger's eyes went wide. "Mr. Lupin?"

"You knew him?" Who would have let a werewolf near a Muggleborn child – oh, Albus, of course. "I'm glad that some people will remember him." Her fellow member of the Order of the Phoenix had deserved much better than the series of tragedies life had given him. But at least he had died a true Gryffindor's death, giving his life to pave the way for peace.

She turned to the Queen. "Your Majesty. On behalf of our world, I would like to express our gratitude for your interference."

"The amulet helped, then?"

Emmeline took a deep breath. "We can't really be sure." Amelia had gambled her career on this; the Wizengamot would not lightly forgive the head of the DMLE for telling the Queen how to exercise power over magic users. And for all they had achieved today, they might never find out whether the choice had been necessary. "We will need a recording of the Pensieve memories to string together exactly what happened. But for what I understand, Albus Dumbledore took the moment after you used the amulet to break through the anti-phoenix wards, which allowed some of our people to get in and finish him off. Albus could probably have succeeded even if Voldemort's powers were unhampered, but that isn't certain, and the sudden loss of power distracted Voldemort for the crucial seconds it took for the ritual to complete. I suspect that, even if we could have won without your help, you definitely saved several lives, most importantly Harry Potter and Albus Dumbledore. So for that, we are in your debt. The director says she hopes that this will be the beginning of a good friendship between our people."

The Queen smiled and inclined her head. "Indeed. But if it is safe now, we should return to the palace. We were supposed to remain in contact with parliament, and the people may be concerned over our disappearance."

"They know you're fine," Emmeline smiled. "The Scrying Charm on Miss Granger is still active, and Madam Bones has ordered it sent to the Muggle television station. I suspect they are even now broadcasting everything that has happened in this room since you arrived." Although in hindsight, perhaps it would have been polite to mention that before...

"I suppose that was a sensible precaution," the Queen responded after a moment's glance at the others. "Nevertheless, our communication devices do not seem to work here. Let us return now."

With a burst of flame, Xare brought Hermione and the nine representatives back to the wrecked sitting room of the palace. They had seen it on screen already, but the destruction was all the more evident up close. A large part of the castle had been destroyed, not just the one room, and the air was full with the smell of dust, and something more – blood? But already a magical team was working on the restoration. There were no other Muggles in sight, but they were probably kept outside to avoid magical accidents.

One of the representatives, John Locker, looked around and heaved a deep sigh. "I suppose that's it for the day. We might as well go home now."

"Aye," Hillary Toney agreed. "There's plenty to do here, but not much where we'd be useful. Could you lead us outside?"

Hermione bit her lip. This hadn't gone well at all. True, Voldemort had been defeated – apparently, she still needed to hear the finer points of that – but the main goal of the day had not been achieved.

She knew what was at stake, why the Ministry had been pushing so hard to get around the table with the Muggle leaders as soon as possible, why they'd even gone so far as to appoint Harry. They had to stop the war. If a solution was not found quickly, the fighting would continue to escalate until there was no stopping it anymore. The announcement of negotiations, and the harsh Auror response to any out-of-bounds magic had helped, but what the television would have shown today was a very short discussion session, an informal surrender that obviously wasn't supported by the majority of the magical negotiation committee, and then a massive duel. Would that be enough to stall the fighting until a good resolution could be reached?

From the Muggle side, probably. They'd be confused now, not knowing what to think, so hopefully the majority would hesitate to act until the session was followed up. But from the wizard side... Harry had just done the unthinkable: he had surrendered to Muggle authority. He was going to shape the conversation to a deal that wizards could live with, but he hadn't gotten around to those parts. Lucius Malfoy had been livid even when Harry's angle became clear, and he surely wouldn't be the only one. Many witches and wizards would be terrified that they'd be forced to give up their magic, or even become slaves to the Muggles – Harry had explicitly stated that he wouldn't accept that, but she knew that it was easy to stop thinking and listening right after you heard something bad...

If a large faction of wizards decided to rebel against what seemed to them to be a very disagreeable deal, would there ever be a chance to finish the discussions? Or if violent groups decided to make a treaty impossible by stepping up attacks on Muggles, would the DMLE be able to keep it in hand? Would they have enough people? How many Aurors had been upset by the proposals?

"Perhaps –" she started hesitatingly, then stopped herself and stood a little straighter. "Your Majesty, I propose that we continue the discussions."

The representative of the United Nations stared. "The building is in ruins, our communication is disrupted, and your negotiator is in hospital."

Show no doubt. "I'm sure not the whole building is destroyed, and the DMLE is already forwarding everything I see to the TV – if cameras are hard to arrange, I can ask someone to set up more Scrying Charms to simulate them. And I am officially a part of the negotiation committee. Harry is the only one who can sign the treaty, but I think I have a pretty good idea of what he wants." They were all sending her skeptical glances now. So far, she'd been the harmless child in charge of getting people out in case of emergencies. She was breaking that role badly by suddenly assuming command and offering to continue peace negotiations on her own. Still, it couldn't be that much stranger than an eleven-year old leading the committee, and they'd accepted that, so she pushed on. "We could get the basic ideas hammered out, and then finish when Harry is released from hospital. I think it could be really important to reach some kind of resolution quickly." She didn't try to keep the urgency out of her voice; it could only help if they realized that giving up now would have negative consequences.

The Queen glanced at her companions, who looked uncertain, but some of them gave slight nods.

"Very well then," she decided. "I propose a thirty minute recess, in which we shall restore our communication with parliament. After that, I suppose, we will speak further."

Within half an hour, a small room in the castle which had not been touched by the destruction was equipped with video cameras, and the nine representatives of government returned with new earpieces, the old ones needing a check-over after having been exposed to the high amount of magic in the DMLE. Discrete messages were sent to the Boy-Who-Lived and other members of the negotiating committee, but the only one not currently in hospital was in mourning, and quite obviously not in the mood. Hermione boldly went in by herself, although she was quickly joined by Emmeline Vance, supposedly for her protection, although it was unlikely that anyone would object if the Muggleborn witch should happen to ask the pureblood Auror some background questions.

Before the cameras and the critical questioning of the nine Muggles, Hermione explained Harry's goals, as she had understood them: to create peace, keep the lives of most wizards and witches – at least those who weren't looking for change – and also most Muggles roughly unaffected, but create possibilities for trade and shared research to improve everyone's quality of life. She did immediately relate Dumbledore's worries, and included his tale of how the Statute of Secrecy had allowed science to flourish. The representatives were skeptical of the insurmountability of this problem, although they did agree that they had to be careful with planning, because various industries might not be too pleased with the shortcuts magic offered, and could end up opposing the treaty unnecessarily. She told them the details of the recently added trace, and how they had been told it would be enforced. She even explained the nature of Harry's current power over the government, and the potential for refusal if a 90% majority of the Wizengamot rejected the treaty – or the simple possibility for all or most wizards to leave the country and seek their fate elsewhere, leaving the Muggles without realistic enforcement methods against magic users. She wasn't entirely sure whether it was good politics to throw all of their cards on the table like that, but (a) she didn't have Harry's manipulative streak, (b) no one expected her to try tricking them, and (c) the representatives responded well to someone simply being honest about their intentions.

There were many questions. Hermione elaborated on Harry's warnings about sharing knowledge by explaining the things Professor Quirrell had said in his lecture for Muggleborns, a lecture that had been specifically designed for people not familiar with the wizarding world. She explained – with a lot of help from Emmeline Vance – how the Wizengamot functioned. The two of them together spoke of blood prejudice, of the war, Lucius's and Dumbledore's role in it, the general trauma in the wizarding world, and how Harry had mysteriously ended it the last time. She also noted the many things purebloods took for granted, and would not appreciate losing in any kind of arrangement.

When pressed for more background, Hermione told them more about the things "Professor Quirrell" had done, and Emmeline urged her to include certain recent events regarding her own part. They even spoke of Grindelwald, and all the other wizarding interference which had been hidden in plain sight for all those years. Hermione really hoped that the other countries wouldn't take offense at her revelations (which were undoubtedly broadcasted worldwide even as she spoke), because one brief stay in prison had been quite enough, but she wasn't going to let that consideration stop her from breaking the International Statute of Secrecy all over the place.

It was almost 5pm when Harry finally stepped into the small room. He was completely cured, and even his robes were as good as new.

One of the women drew in a breath. "We have got to learn how to do that."

"Lord Potter," the Queen greeted him with a gentle nod. "Your friend and fellow negotiator has given us some of the background of today's events. It was fascinating, although if I am indeed your ruler now, I do believe I am going to have to put my foot down about putting children into adult prisons. For the rest, I am happy to delegate the authority to the elected representatives of the people."

"That is a decision I can fully agree with, Your Majesty," Harry said with a bow.

"Very well," the Queen said. "I believe we have a lot to discuss regarding the conditions of your surrender. Miss Granger and Auror Vance here have given us an important overview of your desires for this treaty, and we are overall in agreement that it is in everyone's interest to find an satisfactory arrangement to all parties. Given the absence so far of anyone with final authority on your side we have focused on the larger picture rather than the details, but with your presence we may start finalizing the most urgent points. For example, I understand that witches and wizards commonly use magic to remove the tedium of common tasks like cooking, for which I suspect you will want to discuss permission."

"Indeed," Harry confirmed. "Although I am just a first-year student raised by Muggles, and do not know all that can be done, or is commonly done. That was really why I had those adults with me. Well, one of the reasons."

"I can help," Emmeline Vance offered. "I was surprised by your... negotiating style at first, but I think I can see the logic. If we cannot live in secrecy, this is a good alternative. If you can accept my help without a Vow?"

Harry grimaced. "Yes, that part was a little too dangerous for comfort anyway. Thank you." He turned to the Muggles. "So, what have you got so far?"

Chapter 112: Negotiations, Pt 4 – Aftermaths

In the hour that followed, the Muggle government representatives and Harry, Hermione and Emmeline put their heads together to iron out the details for the first proposals to put to parliament.

At six, Pius Thicknesse returned from St. Mungo's, accompanied by two members of the Wizengamot whom he identified as progressive thinkers with a solid understanding of the economic and cultural foundations of their world. As Pius explained, little though they liked the situation of the surrender, they understood that it was improbable that they could block it – a 90% majority against Potter's treaty was unlikely, even not counting the Queen's formal and real power over magic users – and therefore they were grudgingly willing to go along with the situation, provided they could mitigate the damage somewhat. Professor Dumbledore, physically and magically exhausted, did not return, nor did Draco.

With the six of them and the nine Muggles, the first beginnings of a treaty were crafted, based on the wishes of both sides. The Muggles made no promises but simply wrote up the ideas which were agreed upon to bring back to their superiors, who would have to formally approve the draft. The core of the treaty allowed both sides limiting control on magic. On the one hand, a Muggle group – most likely a new non-magical side to the Ministry of Magic, elected by the general public – would be able to dictate which magics could be used under which circumstances, using the tracing system for enforcement. On the other hand, the Wizengamot would have the same control, which most importantly implied that they would have to approve any magic given to Muggles. The few elected positions in the magical side of the Ministry could only be voted for by magic users.

The wizards were assured that clearing the common spells they had described would mostly be a formality, as would full functioning of St. Mungo's and other essential features of the wizarding world. Despite weak protestations of one of the Wizengamot members, they agreed with Harry that memory charms should not be permitted without explicit permission of the target, and even then only in very specific circumstances, to be cleared by a committee on an individual basis. Love potions and other questionable items sold for "fun" were also not going to be allowed in the near future, but there was a good chance for the approval of potentially dangerous spells within the boundaries of a magical household.

The Muggles were very interested in all the possibilities magic offered, and suggested suitable areas of land that could be assigned to use as resorts for magical creatures or to grow magical plants, which could help to counteract scarcity issues for several potions. The idea of magical research in radio-activity – a necessity to reuse the Hogwarts grounds – was met with great enthusiasm, not just because of how much safer it would make nuclear power plants, but also because of the potential, since Thicknesse suggested in perfect seriousness that magic might be able to use all that energy. The Muggle representatives agreed – in some cases quite reluctantly – not to make any decisions on healing charms, potions and transportation before discussing the matter with a variety of interest groups.

Dinner was brought by Thicknesse's House Elf, which caused a small riot where Harry had to frantically explain that the Elves honestly liked their slavery and the Muggles insisted (with Hermione's backing) that ethicists would have an input on their future treatment, and that a statement of House Elf rights should be drafted. This led to discussions on other magical creatures, and the decision to send a delegation of Muggles to goblin representatives and include them in the rest of the negotiations. The status of centaurs and mermen was discussed at length. Other questions came up as well, of international relations, political structures and currency, until Harry was dead tired, bored to the bone, and silently vowed never to go anywhere near politics again.

At long last, the negotiations were over.

When the Queen had observed that the children looked like it was well past their bedtime, the discussions had been wrapped up for the day. Hermione had taken Harry back to Grimmauld Place, where Snape had arranged a separate room for the two of them and woken up Dumbledore to allow two trusted Auror trios into the wards to stand guard outside their door. The old wizard had also silently passed Harry a mahogany wand; his father's, apparently. It worked, somewhat – better than Lupin's wand, certainly – but Harry knew he'd have to visit Ollivander's soon if he was going to get into any situation where he really needed his magic.

So now, he lay on his bed, listening to Hermione's soft breathing from the other side of the room. The day had been tiring, but he couldn't yet sleep, so he just stared at the dark ceiling above.

And he remembered the stars.

Perfect points of light against total blackness. The feeling of being bodiless, alone in the night sky, far away from all the darkness and cruelty of earth. The enormousness and the beauty of the image.

It was the most personal thing he and the Defense Professor had shared.

The man he had known as the Defense Professor was, almost certainly, dead. Gone. Ceased to be. They would never watch the stars together again. In fact, Harry might have lost the chance to ever relive the experience at all, even alone or with others, for all of Slytherin's lost magic had been destroyed along with the man.

Harry felt lonely.

Despite everything, there had been a bond between them. The man who had stood beside him underneath the stars – somehow, Harry felt sure that that was the real Tom Riddle, not a face he put up. His first mentor, the only person in the entire world whom Harry could truly look up to. A murderer, who had so truly lost faith in humanity that he would happily choose the certainty of killing millions of people over the uncertain prospect of total annihilation by Muggle hands. A friend, who had made him stronger and understood him on a level no one else ever had, or might ever do again.

Gone now. Harry had killed him. Not by his own hands, perhaps, but by intent and choice all the same.

Was it definite?

Harry had promised himself that he would learn to undo death. Had sworn it over and over only a week and a half ago, on the day that would go down in history as Dark Monday. Had ignored all his other feelings and just forced himself to believe it as well as he could. He had continued the insistence after the Battle of Hogwarts, and done all in his power to make the step of resurrection easier, at least for those near and dear people who died by his side. But now, the belief that it could be done did not come so easily anymore.

The notion of death was not as simple as it had seemed before. The strange sense in the air when Mum had died... it had happened after her heart stopped, but before her brain would have died. And then there was the whole "spirit" thing. Tom Riddle had apparently managed to survive the death of his body somehow, and continued to possess a body which surely would have had a different brain. So what, then, was life?

Harry had managed to make predictions about the way spirits, possession and Dementors behaved by pattern-matching on the notion of a soul, and the outcomes seemed to match reality. Could it be that he'd been wrong all along? Was it possible that there actually was a soul, which lived on in some other world after death?

We have no strong evidence one way or another, the voice of Ravenclaw pointed out. Perhaps we should reevaluate our beliefs. It seems that it's possible to keep thinking without a brain, as demonstrated by the existence of both spirits and Animagi – at least for people with magic. This means that our model of the universe, where the brain is what a person is, is inconsistent with reality. Taking that into account, why couldn't there be something magical in sentient life that might as well be called a soul?

Wouldn't it be wonderful? Hufflepuff sighed. We already know from potions that magic has a sort of fairness which isn't present in the Muggle part of science. Maybe the true universe is not is as harsh as it seems to be. Maybe souls live on in some kind of meaningful afterlife, maybe nobody ever really died.

And I suppose you've forgotten, Slytherin coldly said, just how many people have died to Dementors?

There was no response from Hufflepuff, only a terrible feeling of sadness.

All we know, Ravenclaw pointed out, is that we don't really know anything. Reality probably isn't like we imagined it to be. That doesn't mean it has to be worse. What do we know?

He knew that Dementors supposedly destroyed souls – and yet, if Dementors were just a magical representation of death in the world, could they be worse than the real thing? He knew that people – even Muggles, or at least Squibs – caused some kind of feeling of release in the air when they died, which might be magic, life, the soul or perhaps even something different altogether. He knew that wizards, who surely must know about this feeling, did not universally take the existence of a soul for granted.

How could a soul preserve what a person was when a stick through the brain could completely change your personality? But then, if there was a soul, it didn't necessarily follow that it contained all that a person was. Perhaps it was just some kind of cosmic spark, something that gave you sentience and disappeared again when you died. It might not need to contain your personality and memories at all; those would be stored in your body – or your magic, in the case of spirits and Animagi.

Does it even make sense, he wondered, to assume a soul that departs on death, if people have been revived long after their heart stopped beating?

How long afterwards? Ravenclaw asked. More than six hours?

... okay, so perhaps that did make sense. Perhaps a soul, cosmic energy or what departed when your body died and the universe knew it wouldn't be fixed soon enough. And if that was the case, then even if he could find a way to break the laws of time and go back down history and backup every sentient creature that ever lived, it wouldn't be enough. Without their "soul", was there any chance of reviving people as the same person they had been?

We don't know, Ravenclaw repeated. There is only one way to find out the answers to such questions. We should exp-

Internally, Hufflepuff and Gryffindor recoiled in horror.

-ertly do a literature study, Ravenclaw finished meekly. Perhaps we should involve Dumbledore. He may be biased on this issue, but if we ask the right questions, he will be able to point to the right places for answers. Or even better, could we get Nicolas Flamel? Dumbledore did say he wanted to teach us, and since he was able to cast the True Patronus Charm, he probably does not suffer from Dumbledore's biases.

I will also register, Gryffindor piped up, that there is no reason to despair of our success. The first plan might not work for any number of reasons, but we can make others. The possible existence of souls could turn out to be a very good thing. We don't have all the answers yet, but some day, we will. For now, the important thing is to keep more people from dying. Once we get there, we shall learn how to undo it for others. If there is any way to fix reality, we will.

And, Hufflepuff added quietly, perhaps even if there are souls and Dementors eat them, our destruction of all Dementors might have undone that effect. Even for those people who died last week, and in all the previous battles involving Dementors, there is hope. Even Quirrell might yet live. Especially since at least one part of his soul is still safe.

Harry slowly stood up from the bed, and looked ahead. The voice of Professor Quirrell echoed in his head.

Sometimes, when this world seems unusually hateful, I wonder whether there might be some other place where I should have been. But the stars are so very, very far away, and I wonder what I would dream about, if I slept for a long, long time.

"Sleep well, Professor," he whispered. "I will be there when you wake up."

He held on to these thoughts, taking the mahogany wand in his hand.

"Expecto Patronum."

The light came slowly, this time. But it came.

The manor was the image of grandeur. Built to accommodate the entire extended Malfoy family in better times, it had been largely unused already during Abraxas's life. Now, with nothing left of the once-great family but an orphan boy and a single House Elf, the place just felt daunting and very, very empty.

The one remaining scion of Malfoy sat alone in the large, empty kitchen, holding a cup of pumpkin juice but not drinking. It was late in the evening and perhaps he should go to bed, but he'd slept and cried for a good part of the day, and he wasn't in the mood. There were things to organize – many of them! – but he couldn't bear the thought of doing anything at all. Earlier today he'd managed to find hope, somehow, but now, the world just felt as empty as the house.

"Master, sir?"

"What?" He snapped at the House Elf who had quietly shuffled in.

"Professor Snape is wanting to talk to you, master."

Draco wanted to tell him to get lost, but what would be the point? He wasn't really doing anything anyway. So he sighed, pushed himself up and stepped into the visiting room.

Snape's head lay in the fireplace, looking him over calmly. "May I come in?"

"Sure," Draco shrugged. Within seconds, the Potions Master stepped into the room.

"They told me you left St. Mungo's on your own, unsupervised."

"There was nothing wrong with me," Draco shrugged.

Snape just gave him a look. "Be that as it may, you are too young to live on your own."

"Who else have I got?" He snapped. The only close relative who was alive and not in Azkaban was aunt Andromeda, and she'd been kicked out of the Black family for being a Blood Traitor.

"I admit that, with everything that happened, it took us a long time to realize your situation, but by law and custom, you are a ward of the school."

"What school?"

"Conveniently, the law does not specify that a building needs to exist."

Horror dawned on Draco. "I don't want to be in Dumbledore's power!"

"The Headmaster understands that. He said he's willing to pass your custody to me, or to any other responsible adult you wish to name. I propose that you join me and your fellow students in the Black House, and somewhere during the weekend we will arrange your finances and other matters together."

Draco looked up at the Potions Master, who seemed unusually sincere. Responsible adult? He could almost believe it, the way the man acted now. And going along did sound marginally better than sticking in the empty manor with only Dobby for company. It wasn't much, but some of the hollow feeling in his chest left him.

"Come on, Draco, let's go. You don't have to deal with this alone."

On Saturday afternoon, there really wasn't much left to do but cleaning, reading, and talking politics. In Windsor Castle, officials from both worlds were still discussing a variety of formal aspects of the treaty, but in that, there was little need for children, no matter how precocious. Hermione and Harry had attended the formal lunch, but Dumbledore had suggested that they might wish to fill their leisure time more productively than being bored out of their skulls with endless discussions on politics and economy. Even the Queen wasn't sticking around; having finalized the initial relations, it was time for the lawyers to take over. And that meant that Hermione really didn't have much of an excuse to continue putting off the visit she had – if she were entirely honest with herself – been putting off for most of the last week.

With a burst of flame, she appeared in her bedroom. She gently placed Xare on the bed – the fire bird would be by her side with a thought, but she didn't want to draw attention to her familiar now – and went out into the hall.

There were voices downstairs. Hermione tiptoed down the stairs and peeked into the living room. Both her parents were there, glued to the television, which showed the negotiations that were still being transmitted live. There didn't seem to be anyone else around.

She stepped inside. "Hey mum. Hey dad. I'm home."

"Well, Lord Potter," Albus Dumbledore spoke formally. "The Muggle government have agreed to the creation of 'magic-zones' like you suggested, where the specific spells on this list –" he held up three A4s, "– are permitted without alarm. They say that in the future the list could be expanded or turned into an 'all except' list, provided we take care that Muggles are not allowed on those premises without their explicit consent, and a paper trail exists that would allow the government to trace disappearances. In addition, I have taken the liberty to suggest amendments for Squib children, and sufficiently protected research labs. We have agreed on fixed cost and taxation of healing potions and services, and those services are currently restricted to injuries where Muggle treatment cannot provide a complete cure. There has been significant debate as to which new treatments the NHS should cover, but we have generally agreed that this is not a direct concern for the service providers; this is something the Muggles can debate without our input. The Muggle governments have designated large areas of land for magical purposes –" he held up another paper "– with an open application to interested undertakers who wish to rent and use the land. The goblins have agreed to send a team of representatives to join tomorrow's negotiations. If you could study and approve these agreements –" many papers were shoved in his direction "– that would be wonderful. You have my word that there is no trick or small print, and that I believe that this contract corresponds to the ideas you posed yesterday."

Harry nodded. He'd mostly been kept out of the discussions today, which he had accepted because a short session demonstrated just how little he had to add. Moreover, Dumbledore had strongly urged him not to show his face in the Wizengamot for the time being, as "the inevitable recriminations would only serve to stall any semblance of progress". Nevertheless, the votes to immediately halt negotiations had failed, and Dumbledore seemed to fully back Harry's plans.

"Professor..." He asked hesitantly. "Are you actually in favor of all this? Or are you just going along because you have to?"

The old wizard smiled grimly. "I do not value my life so highly that I would not speak out against your proposals if I felt they were wrong, Harry. Nor do I think you would kill me for giving my opinion. This move is frightening to our kind, certainly, but I suspect it will turn out for the best in the long run."

"I'm not even sure of that."

"Ah, but you see... I have some extra information."

Albus Dumbledore put both hands into a pocket of his robes, and carefully retrieved the Pensieve from it.

"You see, in the very first week of this school year, Professor Trelawney made a prophecy –"

His wand prodded the silvery substance in the basin, and a figure rose up out of its depths.

"HE IS COMING. THE ONE WHO WILL TEAR APART THE VERY STRUCTURE OF OUR WORLD. HE WILL ENSLAVE US. YET HE WILL SAVE US ALL."

Harry stared as the figure sank back down into the Pensieve.

"Is that – do you think that was about me?"

"I have wondered about this for a long time. I estimated that the prophecy could either refer to you, or to Lord Voldemort. I feared that it meant the rise of a new dark lord, or perhaps even a light lord. Your description of Voldemort's plans for the world, and for you, seemed frighteningly accurate." He folded his hands. "However, I believe it has been fulfilled rather than averted today. Certainly you have successfully enslaved us all."

"But I was here all along," Harry protested. "And I didn't exactly save everyone, did I?"

"You were not that person then," Dumbledore replied simply, "now, I daresay you are. As for the word 'save', in prophecies it can mean a great many things. You might have saved us from Voldemort's plans, from steady stagnation, or from the corruption that was slowly devolving our world. Perhaps it even refers to a future achievement you have not yet come to."

Such as defeating death, Harry thought. Making people not die would certainly count as saving them.

"As it is," the old wizard continued, "you have many enemies right now.. We are fortunate that your idea caused Voldemort's defeat for the eyes of the nation – Amelia has taken the liberty to supply the Muggles with a recording of my memories, to mend any holes in the video coverage of the event. It is likely that your public victory over the greatest dark lord who ever lived will give you enough popular support to overcome at least some of the hatred for relinquishing our autonomy."

Like Riddle intended. Although I probably won't be ruling any time soon. Placing the nation under Muggle authority is quite a disadvantage to have to overcome.

"Are we entirely sure he is dead, by the way?" Harry asked. "I've been thinking about it, and while it would make a lot of sense with the whole notion of a soul, I didn't get the idea that we actually know enough about the way horcruxes work to be completely convinced. Not to mention, Draco actually destroyed the Dementor. There wasn't much of a choice, since we couldn't exactly keep it around, but that might have made a difference."

"You are right to hesitate," the old wizard spoke soberly. "But the signs are positive, at least. Neither Alastor nor I saw a spirit escape, and it is important to realize that the Dementor's Kiss does not just take the soul, but also drains the magic. Even if the soul survived somehow, a spirit cannot function without its magic. Besides, Riddle seemed to fear the Dementor – if that was merely an act, he at least intends us to believe that he is gone now, which should give us another reprieve. That, along with the fact that Severus's mark has faded, is a hopeful sign, although I confess the mark is not fully gone." He sighed. "We may never have complete certainty, but for the time being, it seems that you have won your war."

Harry looked down. "It doesn't feel like victory," he complained. "Far too many have died."

"Ah yes," the old wizard said with a tone of understanding. "Such is the price of war. The winner gets to tell the tale afterwards, and so there is some victory, but it is always hard-bought."

"Professor –" Harry looked up at the old wizard. "There are a few things I wanted to ask you about death and souls."

"Ah? You no longer believe you have all the answers?"

"I'm not so sure anymore. You know that feeling of outpouring in the air when someone dies?" The old wizard nodded. "What is that?"

"It is the soul passing on, of course."

Harry nodded. "I thought you would say that. Do Muggles have it? Not Squibs, they are still able to see magical items and so on, but actual Muggles?"

The old wizard shook his head. "You cannot sense it for them. The outpouring is much stronger when a witch or wizard dies than a Squib – I believe because it is the magic that allows us to feel it."

"Or the feeling is nothing more than the magic leaving when someone dies."

The old man looked uncomfortable. "I suppose that is possible, but then, the magic does not carry the essence of a person. You would not experience the feeling of all that they were, if it was merely their magic."

"Perhaps," Harry sighed. "Okay, next question. Have you ever known someone with brain damage, like the Longbottoms, to die and become a ghost? Does the ghost maintain the damaged state, or are they healed somehow?"

The old man frowned. "I have never known someone like that to become a ghost, but to become a ghost is a rare event anyway, and wizards do not obtain brain damage as easily as Muggles seem to."

So, uncertain. Not that ghosts were necessarily a good indication of what a soul was or what happened to it anyway.

"And if someone dies by a Dementor, and you kill the body... do they give that feeling?"

"No," the old wizard said quietly.

"Thank you, Professor." He stared at the table for a few moments.

"You are grieving," the old wizard said carefully.

"I'm not grieving," Harry corrected. "I'm planning. Professor, can you put me in touch with Nicolas Flamel? I don't want to offend you, but perhaps he has answers that I can accept."

"Nicolas... is not very pleased with either you or me at the moment, I'm afraid," the old wizard spoke gravely.

Harry blinked. "Why not? Didn't we just secure the safety of his stone?"

"Like many, he prefers to die over being complicit in the potential destruction of the earth." The old wizard sighed deeply. "Despite his misgivings, he gave Alastor and Remus the instructions for the ritual because I had asked. He trusted my judgment. And I, foolishly, trusted yours. Since you asked for the ritual, which I had never told you about, I assumed that you knew more than you really did. I should not have forgotten that you are only eleven, and raised by Muggles besides. The fault is truly mine. I suspect my own desires played a significant role in this folly."

Harry's mouth was dry. "But I was right about what it did. Besides, even if the ritual hadn't summoned a Dementor, I'm pretty sure the True Patronus Charm would have worked against it."

"Do you truly not comprehend the gravity of our offense, Mr. Potter?" The ancient wizard looked into his eyes long and hard. "When the fate of the world is at stake, pretty sure does not suffice! If there was a one in a thousand chance that the ritual did not do what you expected, that it might have summoned an unstoppable horror that could have ended all human life, then you should not have even considered it. All turned out for the best yesterday, but what will happen the next time you make such a gamble?"

Harry looked down at the table. "I see the point. I guess this is exactly why Riddle doesn't like Muggle scientists."

"If they would take similar risks, then I imagine he has reason, yes."

"Could that be why Riddle allowed himself to be caught in that situation?" Harry wondered aloud. "That it was unthinkable to him that I would do something like that? But then, he knows I was raised by Muggles, and he's called me terms like 'extraordinary idiot' and 'witless dunce' on multiple occasions."

"Since he was the one who told you about the ritual," Dumbledore observed, "I would imagine the possibility of your using it against him did not slip his mind. However, the timing may have surprised him. Had you realized the implications before and told me of your suspicions, I would have deterred you from this course. In the unlikely event that you had managed to persuade me or others, it seems probable that we would have brought the components with us – something he may have tested for early on. Even as it was, the plan would not have worked without the Queen's timely interference. Without the few seconds distraction her use of the amulet provided, Riddle could have halted the ritual before its completion, restored the anti-phoenix wards before Barnok took you away, and, with all my powers expended, finished whatever plans he had without further obstacles."

Harry nodded. In the end, even a worst-case planner with a veritable pack full of backups could be surprised by reality.

"I believe Nicolas will forgive us eventually," Dumbledore said quietly. "He has a great heart, after all, and he has not betrayed my confession of how little I knew to the world at large. For the moment, however, it does not seem wise to press the point. Perhaps as a penance, you might wish to follow that course on caution with power that you placed on your list as a condition for Muggle scientists to work with magic. I shall of course take it to heart as well."

Harry smirked. "Thank you, I will definitely do that. But for a different topic, I don't suppose you have any books on Dementors? I know that no one's really sure how they work, but I wouldn't mind learning the dominant theories and the available evidence for each of them. I'm also willing to personally sponsor medical research on exactly what is wrong with the Dementor victims who are still alive. I know it wouldn't be safe to use Riddle's last body for that, but some others must have been delivered to hospitals by now."

"I can bring up the point and state your intentions to the Muggle representatives. There might even be some victims in Britain to work with. However –" Dumbledore fixed him with another one of his piercing looks. "Am I right to conclude that you are feeling guilty over Tom Riddle's fate?"

"He's not the only one who was Kissed recently," Harry bit.

"He is not," the former Headmaster conceded. "But it surprises me that you would ask about Dementor-victims before speaking of the corpses you had me protect with the anti-decomposition charm, which leads me to suspect that it is a matter of particular urgency in your mind."

Harry looked down, escaping the gaze. "I killed him."

"Remus and Alastor did," the former Headmaster pointed out.

"By my instructions. That makes it my responsibility as much as if I had struck a pole through his heart myself. Well, more, since that wouldn't have killed him, technically. He died by my hand, Professor."

"I suppose that that is true." The old wizard looked sympathetic, as though he understood completely what Harry was feeling despite having desired this death for many years. "But Harry, he chose this demise. He chose to split his soul, and kill so many people as to leave you no other option!"

"There's always another option!" Harry growled. "Maybe if I were smarter, or knew the whole picture or had other abilities, I would have seen a better way. And it's not just him! What about all those other people I led to their deaths? Lucius was a good father, Remus a good instructor and kind friend. And all those people on Dark Monday, do you think they would have been Kissed if I hadn't screwed up and given Riddle all the information he needed?"

"Your responsibility in those deaths was very small, Harry," the old wizard spoke sternly. "Your allies knew what they were risking, and they chose to follow you regardless. And as for the others who died – yes, it was a tragedy, and it might not have happened if you had never figured out how to destroy Dementors, but Voldemort would simply have struck elsewhere, and over the years, those Dementors have caused more harm than in the day you and your friends destroyed them. I will not tell you not to blame yourself, Harry – I know how pointless that would be – but be reasonable."

"I am entirely reasonable," Harry answered. "It is reasonable to regret their deaths, and to look for any possibilities to undo as many of those as possible."

The old wizard just shook his head sadly. "You should fight for the living, Harry, not obsess over those who have passed away. I will support you in enabling non-magical medical experiments, if only to promote your peace of mind, but I beg you: do not waste your life on a fool's errand."

"You don't know it's a fool's errand," Harry said wearily. "I have no idea whether anyone has ever tried to resurrect people before – I guess they probably have, it's just stupid not to when there's magic in the world – but with Muggle science I have a lot more tools at my disposal than those who have tried before. And don't give me that look. Must we really have this discussion again? I don't intend to die, or for anyone else to die, and I don't intend to let people stay dead either."

"I knew how you felt, Harry," the old wizard said slowly. "I can even appreciate wanting to stop people from dying while they don't yet want to go – in fact, I told myself that even if the goal of your quest is misguided, it might yet lead you to find great healing methods, or magical defenses like the Elder Wand. If your Patronus is any example of what can be achieved by rejecting death, I am eager to see more. But resurrection, Harry, that is a different matter. If you focus on the dead, you will achieve no good for the living! What is more, when you seek a way to undo death, the prospect of failure will only become worse as you grow older, while for mere immortality, the idea will become less daunting over time."

Harry gazed back at him. There was some sense in the words, he had to admit. At least in parts of them.

"I understand what you're saying, Professor," he said eventually. "And I'm not stupid. I won't become a hermit and throw away my life on a single project that might turn out to be a dead end. I understand that the laws of the universe might make resurrection a fundamentally impossible venture. I will do what I can immediately with the bodies of the people who have the greatest chance of being saved, though. I'm not about to give up without at least having tried. I also fully intend to encourage people to do what they can to preserve or save life – or preserve the chance of future recovery as well as possible." He shrugged. "But I'll prioritize working on immortality for the people who didn't die in the first place, and also don't mind taking some time out of my schedule to see about world peace and the other minor issues."

Dumbledore chuckled. Harry fixed him with a firm look.

"However," he added, "as for me being misguided, I am not so sure that you are talking to the right person. Honestly, I think you're lying to yourself. Lying on such a fundamental level that you don't even realize it."

The man's eyes widened only slightly.

"Can you consider," Harry asked seriously, "and I mean actually consider for five full minutes the scenario that you're wrong? That there isn't an afterlife; you just cease to be when you die, that every death is like a Dementor's Kiss. And then suppose that there is a way that wizards and Muggles might find, that gives you the ability to live forever... wouldn't you take that?"

There was silence, for some time.

"Poppy told me this morning," the old wizard spoke eventually, "that she longed to see a twinkle in my eye again. And I daresay that in time, she will, for great things have happened in the last two days, and as the days pass by, there will surely be small diversions and innocent laughter again."

"What does that –"

"But regardless," the old wizard pressed on, "I have still lived through all these things. Three wars, Harry, not counting Muggle wars that I was not involved in. I have lost too many. So many friends. All of my family. Some died to age or accident, some to my follies, some even died by my own hand. And there are others, whom I killed or let die, some evil perhaps, some not. All precious. And no matter what else may happen, I will always carry that grief, that guilt, in my heart. So no, I do not wish to live with that grief forever, even if the alternative is the Dementor's Kiss. I shall carry on while I am still needed, but when death comes, I shall not resist it. Or if my dying would serve a greater purpose than my living, well..." He smiled weakly. "You already know that answer."

Harry nodded, a lump in his throat.

For a while, neither of them spoke. Finally, Harry broke the silence.

"There's something else I wanted to talk about, too."

The old wizard sat back and folded his hands. "Go ahead."

"Do you speak Latin? Or do you know of a reliable person who does, and who has some time available? I know you're a busy man, especially since I kind of set your schedule."

"The time for what, exactly?"

From his pouch, Harry retrieved the diary of Francis Bacon.

"The Defense Professor gave me this, months ago. He told me he stole it, but he didn't say who from and he wasn't going to put it back. We should probably return it, if there's a way to figure out the owner, but I'd reaeaeaeaeaeally like a copy first. It's the diary of Roger Bacon, you see."

This failed to produce the desired response.

"He's a key figure in the history of science," Harry explained with an internal grumble of having expected a wizard to understand. "Apparently he was a Muggleborn wizard, born in the middle ages. This could be really important, and is absolutely, undeniably, really really interesting. It's a priceless historical artifact."

"And you expect that it will say something about a tree," Dumbledore concluded.

"Yes. Perhaps the location of a favorite tree where he used to daydream or something. Riddle would have read it before giving it to me, and he might have used a specific place to hide some clue for me. He used his last breath to tell me about it," Harry pointed out. "It's bound to be important."

"To him, yes." The old wizard carefully took the diary in his hands and rifled through it. "I shall read this tonight – I should be able to find the time. But I urge you to be very wary. Whatever we find might well be a trap to kill you after all."

"To what purpose?" Harry shrugged. "If we are right, he's dead. He doesn't benefit from killing me anymore." Or from anything else I might do, for that matter. Considering that, it was strange that he might try to reach beyond the grave.

"Oh?" The old wizard raised an eyebrow. "Do you fully understand his motives, then?"

"I think I do." Harry stared ahead. He had had a whole day to think about it, after all. "Although there's a lot to it. He's been adapting his plans with every new bit of information."

The former Headmaster quirked an eyebrow and put the diary aside. "I should like to hear about it."

"He was afraid of death," Harry said simply. "In the end you were right about that part. He was so afraid of death that it possessed his being, that he would consider any alternative over dying." Before falling asleep, he had remembered the feeling when he had asked his dark side's opinion on death, in the sombre corridors of Azkaban. Riddle, if the part of his personality that resided in Harry was anything to go by, was absolutely terrified of non-existence. "And I can completely agree with that, but he didn't care about other people's existence; just his own."

The old wizard nodded.

"So he made his Horcruxes," Harry continued. "But it wasn't enough. Even making a round dozen and sending some of them out to space would never be enough. Not while there was a risk of the complete annihilation of earth. It's great being immortal, but you need to have somewhere to live too, and I don't think he really fancied being a wandering spirit stuck on a dead pile of rubble forever floating through space."

"So he feared Muggles," Dumbledore nodded. "Like you concluded before."

"Yes. But it wasn't war he feared, I should have realized that. His vehement response about nuclear weapons was merely an example, a case of Muggle stupidity he encountered in his formative years, but ultimately not the main issue. Complete nuclear annihilation was a known risk, something a powerful wizard like he could control. I'm pretty sure he at least had warning spells on existing missiles, probably along with some well-placed Imperiuses. Nor was there ever much risk in a war between wizards and Muggles: there would be heavy casualties, but wizards could hide out. What he feared was all the unknowns of scientific development. There are so many ways people could blow up human society by accident... There wasn't really an immediate danger, but then, even reading scientific journals he might not pick up on a new existential risk in time to do something about it."

The old wizard looked considering. "Which is why he wanted to rule the world."

"Yes. I doubt he really cared much about ruling, but he wanted there to be a world. So he did the obvious thing: he created a terrible dark threat, so wizards would put aside their squabbling and unite against the common enemy. And for the dark wizard he took a platform that the most irrational people, the greatest losers, could unite behind. He was setting the blood supremacists up to be defeated, which would have created the best opportunity to build a rational, undivided government afterwards."

"But that didn't work out," Dumbledore concluded.

"No," Harry agreed. "It didn't. Turns out it's actually very hard to get people to unite. A common enemy is a good first step, but people will drag their feet on acting as long as it seems they'll get away with it. People weren't going to unite behind David Monroe, so he retired him and made the dark lord threat worse, so a new hero could rise."

"Which would be you?"

"No. I think it was meant to be you, actually."

Dumbledore blinked.

"Strength flows from powerful wizards and their followers, that's what he told me. What he wanted was a strong leader. When Yermy Wibble called for a draft, it actually got pretty close to what Riddle wanted, but he would never have been a strong enough leader. So the dark lord 'set an example', to discourage weak people from stepping into shoes they could never fill. A powerful wizard would not be so easily cowed. And indeed, in the end a very powerful wizard did step up to lead the war efforts, when it became clear that no one else would. Unfortunately, the wizard in question did not call for a draft, or institute a light mark."

"I never sought to rule," Dumbledore breathed. "Not since I was young, not after Gellert –" He shook his head.

"He might have hoped he could fix that," Harry shrugged. "Didn't the war teach you to weigh your pieces for their value, to make the rational rather than the emotional choice? You thought he was being cruel for cruelty's sake, but in reality he was shaping you into a better leader."

Dumbledore shut his eyes, grief covering his face.

"But that didn't work either," Harry said quietly. "Truth be told, you're a bit of a hopeless case. You started out with powerful ideals, and even if you had to compromise them out of need, you'll never give them up completely. I think Riddle understands people very well overall, but he has trouble with people who genuinely care about others and try to do what is right for altruistic reasons. He can't predict people like Hermione, or like you, as accurately as others."

"But surely he could never have thought that I would come to subjugate Muggles?"

"You wouldn't need to," Harry explained. "Just change the pattern of the world. He was handing you Britain on a silver platter. If you were willing to compromise more, destroy your enemies and show your strength – if you had forced, manipulated or even actively encouraged people to join the fight, or done something brutal but effective like forcing all Hogwarts students to declare under Veritaserum that they were not aware of their family being involved with the Death Eaters – you could have appealed to the Slytherin side of the population as well as the Gryffindors who already sing you as their hero. It would have been easy for you to unite the country and become dictator in practice if not in name. With the blood purist side heavily discredited, you could have made massive reforms and led the country into an era of peace and prosperity. However, you're old. Eventually, you would have died – quite possibly with some help – and that would leave a power gap. The road would be open for a new dictator to take over, since the example was already there. And Riddle would have made sure he moved into that gap, and then he could have set his further plans in motion."

The old wizard breathed deeply. "But that didn't happen."

"No," Harry agreed. "You weren't cooperating. But then something unexpected happened: a new hero was prophesied. I'm still not sure whether that was real or he faked it, but in the end I don't think it matters much. He made his move to fulfill the prophecy one way, and to be seen to fulfill it the other way. He turned the child who would be his nemesis into a horcrux and then set off some magical effect that killed him and gave me that scar. The wizarding world got its miracle and could rebuild, while a ready-made hero was there to grow into the future leader."

Dumbledore's eyes had widened and his mouth was open.

"Hermione came up with the horcrux idea," Harry clarified. "It seemed to fit with the story you found of the child possessed by an ambulatory wizard. But I don't know whether it's accurate." He shrugged. "This part is really guesswork; I just don't know enough about horcruxes, souls and possession to make a prediction I'd be remotely sure about. But there are multiple theories that would fit the data. For a start, you said that a painting horcrux would reflect the intelligence and personality of the owner, so it seems plausible that a human horcrux would create a permanent kind of possession by the intelligence in the horcrux. However, I would have needed to convincingly act like a child for ten years, so perhaps he only copied his personality, not his memories. Or he Obliviated me afterwards, if that was possible without magical interference. He arranged for a high probability that I would grow up in similar circumstances as he had."

Dumbledore just kept staring, his face horrified.

"That also didn't work out," Harry said simply, but he didn't meet the old wizard's gaze, as he wasn't entirely sure how he felt about this particular theory. "Perhaps because I was too young: I was a growing child, my brain was going through massive developments at the time. I suspect my consciousness ended up absorbing his, and my mind became my own. His influence is still there, but it cannot control me unless I get angry, or recently only when I let it. It does sort of feel like a separate entity, but it doesn't have a mind of its own and it cannot possess me; it's simply a different way I sometimes am."

Dumbledore shook himself. "I admit this is a much better explanation than the one I had before, although it is... concerning. Are you comfortable with this?"

Harry grimaced. "It's not like I can change it. I am who I am. I do hope you're not going to kill me?" Perhaps he shouldn't have told the man about this possibility, but it was entirely likely that he would eventually figure it out regardless. Better to break the news now, while the man was still under his power, and after reminding the old wizard of his ideals and telling him that Voldemort's plans involved turning him into a killer.

The old man shook his head. "I can't see it helping much, especially since it seems he was quite prepared to kill you himself."

"True," Harry nodded. "Even if he's still around, he undoubtedly has too many horcruxes for any individual one to matter."

Dumbledore nodded. "So his plan failed. Again."

"Yes," Harry agreed. "Although in his defense, the plans weren't so bad, it's just really kind of hard to conquer the world and get it in a state where everyone accepts that situation."

"Oh, I wasn't accusing," the old wizard smiled.

"Anyway, he came to Hogwarts in the same year I would," Harry continued. "Where he must have quickly realized the plan hadn't exactly gone as planned. But it was close enough: I wasn't a young version of him, but I did end up smart and ambitious, and somewhat isolated from other children. So he became my mentor, to guide my thinking along the desirable lines, where I would eventually want to rule the world. He might have succeeded without Hermione pulling me back, or if he'd had more time before I figured him out. As it was, he was pretty far along, seeing as I did in fact want to overthrow the government of magical Britain."

"Which you did," the old wizard observed.

"Well yes. Anyway, since I was removed from his mentoring, he had to move quickly, before other people influenced the direction of my ambitions too much. Therefore, he started a war. It was always only a matter of time before the Statute of Secrecy would come plummeting down; with technology improving and magic degenerating, I don't think we could have kept up the masquerade for more than another twenty, maybe thirty years. So he must have had dozens of safety precautions in place, and that's why he felt safe starting it now. It started very violently, but I think that he could easily have kept tensions going for years if necessary, like so many conflict areas, or like the ten year war in Britain. A war with Muggles would create many opportunities for me to prove myself, and I was always going to make a large move eventually, because whether or not I want to rule the world, I do want to stop people dying."

"And you rose to the challenge rather earlier than expected."

"Oh, I'm not sure about that," Harry contradicted him. "He always did have rather high expectations."

"But you said he knew you," Dumbledore noted. "Why would he expect you to subjugate Muggles?"

"I don't think that's what he had in mind," Harry shrugged. "More likely, he intended me to act the way Lucius expected. I would bring peace – with his cooperation, I should be able to pull that off. That, combined with my past, would give me a lot of credit, which would allow me to rise to a leading position in the political landscape, and earn the respect from Muggles too. Since there's a lot more things I want to do, I probably wouldn't be able to stop myself from using that influence, and over time, I would be able to become the strong leader he desired all along. And then I could either rise naturally to a dictatorship over both worlds, or set the golden example of a benevolent magical dictator, to be replaced after my eventual demise by someone more suitable to his plans. That, or I'd manage to encourage the space program well enough to allow wizards to escape the earth before Muggles destroy it."

"I see." Dumbledore frowned. "And yet you didn't. You held that potential, and you deliberately threw it away."

"I do not trust myself enough for such authority," Harry answered simply. "I don't think I'd trust anyone like that. Democracy is not a very good solution, but at least it stops the more extreme imbalances of power."

"You don't fear the destruction of the world, then?"

"Of course I do! And I do intend to prepare for that. But there is one thing that Riddle never understood, or at least never believed in." He sat up a little straighter. "People can learn. The failures of democracy are not so much because people are selfish, but because they are stupid. There's loads of experimental studies showing how people's minds go wrong and make terrible mistakes that might work great in a tribal environment but not really in the current world. Professor Quirrell always got cynical about that sort of thing. But I believe it can be fixed, and I'm planning to use the influence I hold now to do just that."

The old wizard looked intrigued. "How?"

"Many ways," Harry said. "The first was the requirement for a caution course that any scientist working with magic is obliged to pass. Since magic is likely to become a large part of many sciences, I suspect the course will end up making its way into standard undergraduate curricula, which means that even those scientists and engineers who only work with strictly Muggle methodology will be aware of it. Once this becomes standard, there will probably be a large discussion on the publish or perish culture, which wizards can fuel and – judging by my father's opinions – Muggle scientists will almost certainly back us on completely."

"Do not think too lightly on what 'wizards' will do," Dumbledore warned him. "We are not all of a single mind. You will almost certainly need to push the issue yourself, or at least encourage your allies to do so."

"That's the other part," Harry said. "I'll still be in the Wizengamot, and so will Draco be once he's of age, but I'm hoping you will cooperate on fixing the problem from the wizard side as well. There's fewer of us, but I expect we'll be very visible as sub-culture, so we can can set an example. When Hogwarts is rebuilt, I want science and rationality to be put into the new curriculum as a mandatory course."

The former Headmaster frowned. "I'm not sure –"

"You already approved something very close," Harry pointed out. "When you hired my father as a temporary Professor. What do you think he was teaching? He never got more than a single week, and it was only an elective class, but it's the same idea."

"The curriculum is already very full, though."

"So add a year! Perhaps you could even add Muggle electives like French or maths if an extra year gives you too much time to spare."

The old wizard looked very grave now.

"Just think about it," Harry urged. "Now that we're going to have closer ties to the Muggle world, teaching wizards the style of thinking and methodology of science would be a really good idea. Many of those students are going to be working together with Muggle scientists later. As for rationality, if we can teach all children to think properly and not just believe things through some crazy pattern-matching scheme, then in twenty years you'll have a Wizengamot whose members would actually realize that someone like Hermione Granger probably didn't commit a cold-blooded murder. And if they encountered someone who did, they'd still be able to think about such things as proportional response and reintegration in society rather than going with gut feelings of revenge. I know you yourself haven't had this training, Professor, but you must also see that the gains to the world would be tremendous."

"I suppose..." the old wizard said slowly. "But did our enemy himself not think 'rationally', as you describe it?"

"He did," Harry conceded. "But he was... special. Cold. Besides, in a world where a substantial portion of people think rationally, even he would not have felt a need to act as he did. When everyone thinks properly, all you need to make people work towards your goal is to shift circumstances so that it advantages the people you want to influence – which in his case would be very easy, as his goal of not getting the earth destroyed was pretty much good for everyone. Because most people don't think like that, he decided that the only way was to manipulate them through fear and narrative expectations."

The old wizard. "Very well. If Hogwarts is rebuilt – and I must warn that it might well take years, and will only be a semblance of its former self – and if I am still Headmaster at the time, I will do as you ask."

"Thank you."

Dumbledore leaned forward and picked up the diary again, rifling through it and casting a number of spells. "At first glance, it is strictly non-magical, but more tests will be necessary to be sure."

"I don't think there's much of a hurry. But will you study it, or get someone else to?"

The man looked weary.

"Do keep in mind that it's almost certainly a trap –"

"Perhaps. But for now, I'm not asking for anything to be done, I just want to know what information we have. If the diary contains a hint as to some kind of location, I'll ask volunteers to go look there, and it's not like we could make sure people stay away from such a location forever anyway. I will be sure to consult you on safety measures, as long as those safety measures do not involve me not knowing certain things. Can you live with that?"

The old wizard sighed. "Very well, then. Let us see what Tom Riddle intends us to do."

Marielle sat still in her cell, reading quietly. She wasn't allowed a wand, or her Time-Turner when she wasn't forced to use it, but while she was well-behaved she could at least peruse her school books and was fed three meals a day. Not that the arrangement was necessary to keep her in line; the moment she stirred out of bounds that madwoman would be allowed to deal with her. She'd been thinking of becoming an Auror, before, but if she ever got out of here – and she was losing more hope of that with every passing day – she was going to research alternative career paths. After two tastes of the Cruciatus Curse, she was not about to risk ever being on the wrong side of dark wizards again.

Suddenly, a blinding silvery-white light appeared. A Patronus? No, it couldn't be, the human shape was impossible. And yet, what else could it be?

The woman on the other side of the bars looked at the thing with an expression of wonder, which baffled Marielle more than its presence. The woman reached out a hand to touch the glowing man, and it spoke:

"Hello mother. It's me, your son Lesath. The Aurors have sworn that if you surrender, you won't be harmed, and you won't be sent back to the Dementors either. You don't have to if you're in a better place now, but if you're stuck wherever you are, please consider it. I don't want you to die."

The woman stared at the magical creature and opened and shut her mouth several times, before she finally asked the question Marielle, too, was struggling to wrap her mind around.

"I have a son?"

-o-o-o-o-o-

Author's Note: the amulet introduced in the last two chapters has been a matter of some question in discussions and reviews, so I figured I'd give my ideas on its history...

Merlin made the amulet to allow the king a modicum of control over their wizards, but not ultimate control: it limits their power, but doesn't take it away altogether. A single dark lord, or a small group of magic users, cannot just go after the king, because the latter will limit their power and then the king's own wizards will be able to overpower him. However, a bad king (or at least, one who treats wizards badly) would quickly be overthrown, since wizards can still band together at half power and be strong enough to take out the army; they couldn't kill him with magic, but they could simply cut the head off with a sword.

The Queen, of course, does not descend directly from King Arthur, which is the king Merlin would have given his amulet to. The English crown has been passed on through a lot of war, murder, betrayal and whatnot. However, in the days before the Statute of Secrecy, the existence of the amulet would be known among the higher nobility and their wizards. I imagine the people taking the crown would generally be at least moderately aware of the amulet – and if not, they might recognize that a precious jewel that glows is obviously magical, and inquire. Even if wizards were reluctant to give information, a king could torture it out of close relatives of the last king.

Of course, such a way of passing the information is faulty, and at some point, the instructions on how to use the amulet were lost. Still, knowing as little as "protection from and control over magic users" (the general explanation that a king might leak to friends and family members) would definitely be a good reason to keep passing it on.

As someone on the reddit pointed out (and I like this suggestion so much I might consider it canon): given the desirability of an amulet that gives you power over and protection from magic users, it is entirely likely that it was the reason for the bloody succession of English royalty!

Riddle did not know about the amulet: it was extremely obscure knowledge about a magical item that can be used only by a single person who doesn't even know about it in a somewhat local setting (parts of Britain following boundaries no one can figure out anymore). Even Thicknesse, who worked for the Ministry for all his adult life and made it his business to know all the laws and workings of the country had only heard of the law that the monarch was above them, not about the item itself. Then again, in the end, the effect of the amulet was very small. Given the limits to its functionality – restricting magical power, rather than blocking it altogether – it cannot really win a battle on its own, although it can turn the tide.

Chapter 114: The Deathly Hallows, Pt 1

CHAPTER 114: THE DEATHLY HALLOWS, PT 1

Harry nodded, turned the stone over three times in his hand, and spoke: "Cadmus Peverell".

The stone glowed warm in his hand and a mist formed, which twisted and turned until it settled on the shape of a man.

"Néade sé bregus ongrataþ on þín dæg."

Harry grimaced and turned to Professor Dumbledore. "I forgot about that part. I don't suppose you have a sequence of portraits spanning from time the Peverells lived to the present, with two-century gaps so they can translate from each other?"

The old wizard quirked an eyebrow and turned to one of the devices on his desk. After a few seconds of prodding and whispering, the Grey Lady, Ravenclaw's house ghost, appeared.

"Ah, Helena," the old wizard spoke gently. "I apologize for disturbing you today, but I find myself in need of someone of your expertise. As you may notice, we have a... guest, from a very distant past. I believe he died about two to three centuries before you were born. Would you be willing to help us with some translations today?"

"I am honor-bound to serve the Headmaster of Hogwarts," the young woman said crisply, in perfect English. "I will help you, even though there is little left to be a Headmaster of."

"I am grateful, Helena." He turned to Harry, who was suddenly realizing that, unlike the portraits, all the ghosts he knew spoke modern English, no matter when they had died. Were ghosts capable of learning somehow, or was it a part of their magic to update their language over time? "Helena is Rowena Ravenclaw's daughter, who has always been an accomplished woman with a solid grasp of the literature of her time, which makes her familiar with the language shifts from well before her birth."

The ghostly woman turned to the specter hovering before Harry, who was looking at the three of them with a curious gaze.

"Hálettung," she spoke.

"Néade sé bregus ongrataþ on þín dæg," the man repeated.

"He says hello," she translated.

Ah. "Euhm... I am Harry James Potter-Evans Verres; for what I'm told, I'm a descendant from your brother Ignotus," Harry introduced himself. "I was wondering whether you could tell me what exactly this stone does."

The specter gave him a searching look, as Helena Ravenclaw translated this introduction. Then, it chuckled.

"An interesting question. Most ask for how, not what." His dark eyes looked Harry over. "You do not at all look like a Peverell."

"Yes, well, a few generations have passed," Harry answered dryly when Helena had provided this translation. "For what I'm told, it's been about eleven hundred years since you died."

The specter's eyes widened. "That is a long time. Can you prove that you are truly a descendant?"

Does it matter? Harry wondered, but he didn't really want to argue with a vision that was probably just the product of his own imagination. Instead, he reached inside his pouch and drew forth the Cloak of Invisibility.

"Do you recognize this?"

He waited as "Cadmus Peverell" studied the cloak, then threw it around himself to demonstrate its functionality. The specter nodded.

"Well then, heir of Ignotus, the stone simply retrieves the chosen soul from the ether, and gives it shape and speech according to what the soul itself would expect. The soul stays bound to the stone until dismissed, or until it chooses to depart – provided it is capable of such choices."

Questions flooded Harry's mind. This was not an answer that seemed like it would have been drawn from his own expectations. "Why wouldn't it be capable?"

"Disembodied souls cannot have original thoughts," the specter clarified, "nor change their minds once they are settled. You need a body to accommodate change." He smirked. "But before you get any ideas, you will not find me that easy to manipulate. I have considered many eventualities before my death, and as such, my mind is made up with regards to my responses to all situations I could envision."

"Oh, don't worry," Harry reassured the ghost. "I don't intend to manipulate you, I just want to understand." Well, for now anyway. "What exactly do you mean by a 'soul'?"

The image frowned, and Helena's ghost frowned at him as she translated his answer. "Has knowledge degenerated so far in this time that you have to ask such a fundamental question?"

Harry shrugged. "I just want to make sure I get the right answer, and you seem to be an expert."

"A soul is all that a person is," the image answered. "Memories, personality, intellect, inclination."

"But if that is laid out in the soul, then how can brain damage affect it?"

The image frowned again. "I am not sure I understand your question. Are you asking how the body can affect the soul?"

"Euhm, yes?"

"I am not sure of the mechanics, exactly, but the soul is naturally shaped and influenced by the body it inhabits. Why would you imagine it to be immutable? The body – or rather, the brain – is what makes you think, gives you character. The soul is what preserves it."

Harry's heart sank as he parsed the meaning of those words. "Are you telling me that if someone rams a piece of metal through your head and you end up with a damaged brain that turns you more aggressive, then it will change your immortal soul so you'll be damaged for all eternity? And, and if you get Alzheimer's disease – I mean, if you go senile – you'll be stuck like that forever?" Technically, in the view of the world he'd held so far, it was already the case that if you got the wrong kind of brain damage you'd be affected for the rest of your life, and living in a damaged state still seemed preferable over not living, but even so, it didn't take Harry more than a few seconds to see the implications. If the soul was affected by the body, it meant that the moment someone would show the beginnings of mental disease, the right and proper thing to do was to kill them before it got worse. Hell, if there genuinely was an afterlife, you should probably just kill people the moment they were fully developed, before anything could happen that would adversely affect their soul...

"Not quite," Peverell answered with a wry smile. "I see that you think somewhat like my brothers and I used to do, but you are woefully ignorant. The soul alters itself gradually along with the body, but sudden, outside changes are not immediately reflected in it. Over time, it causes strife when body and soul are not united, so eventually the soul must either adapt or move on. However, this process can take many years depending on the shift in the brain, which should leave ample time to repair the issue when a young person is concerned. What is more, the deficits of old age mostly lose parts of a person's character, intellect and memories, rather than truly changing them, and as such the stress on the soul to retain its original facilities is significantly smaller. Indeed, I find that most of the souls I tested with – Muggles and wizards alike – remembered events with greater clarity than their bodies did, even though they were slow to form new memories. Of course, living for many years in a degenerating body does take its toll, but you could imagine the soul of a deceased to be that which the person would have been if all the abilities they lost were restored in the moment before their death."

Harry's mind whirled. The words promised hope. If all this was true, he might really see his parents again – all of them –, might see everyone again. Most people who ever lived were probably still there, waiting to see him in some kind of afterlife...

No.

No. He stamped down on that line of thought before it could run away with him. He shouldn't give himself false hope, only to have it destroyed again. He was jumping to unwarranted conclusions. What was he really seeing here? The image of Cadmus Peverell and the strange things it said might well have been built directly into the stone, in case anyone should ask for a clarification. Or in fact –

He turned around to Professor Dumbledore, who had silently sat down behind his desk. Harry wasn't entirely sure what Dumbledore thought about souls, or whether he even had a complete picture, but Peverell did seem to be channeling much the same ideas as those Dumbledore had stated before. If the stone merely created an image from your mind, the specter could well be drawing on the old wizard's expectations rather than his own, or even from both. The way to test whether the stone actually summoned a person's soul was to find someone who had died with secrets whose veracity could be confirmed in the real world – assuming they would not mind telling either Dumbledore or himself those secrets. It probably couldn't be gained from someone who'd died this long ago.

Still, there was a real, non-zero chance that the vision was telling truth, and he had many more questions, including some which the former Headmaster might not have an answer to.

"The Cruciatus Curse," he demanded from Dumbledore. "It leaves people permanently insane. Would you say that means they lose something, or they actually get new behaviors?"

"Both," the man said quietly. "But primarily the former, I believe. The change in behavior is the result of confusion more than anything else."

"The Cruciatus Curse, if held too long, induces a form of senility," Peverell nodded when the ghost of Helena translated the interaction.

"So if –" Harry began, "suppose a couple were tortured into insanity by the Cruciatus Curse, and they are in their early twenties which means they probably have at least a century left to live... they'll be okay after they die?" This line of questioning was potentially dangerous in Dumbledore's presence, but if the stone didn't actually summon souls, he'd be able to prove it soon enough, and the Chief Warlock was unlikely to act rashly upon the information. All the more so because he was still legally Harry's servant, as Harry had not officially released the House Vows – and while he had removed the magical bonds at the first opportunity, he hadn't actually told Dumbledore and Thicknesse about this.

The specter gave him a piercing look.

"There's little okay about being dead, but their souls may still personify who they once were. A hundred years is a long time, however. The soul would almost certainly be affected."

"So..." Harry summarized. "In a case like this, it would be immoral not to kill those people?"

"Harry –" Dumbledore began in a horrified tone.

The specter frowned. "I suppose in the case of Muggles it might be preferable, if the risk of altering the body is deemed too great... I would not wish to persist in such a state even regardless of the consequences to my soul. But when Healers are available, when the magic is not yet lost, it would seem extraordinarily wasteful."

Harry blinked. "Are you implying that, in your time, people turned mad by the Cruciatus Curse could be cured?"

Peverell's eyebrows flew up. "Are you implying that, in your time, they cannot?"

"Indeed," Professor Dumbledore said gravely. The man had stood up and was now looking at the appearance with a strange expression on his face. "We have lost much of our art, over the centuries. I could not begin to think how such a feat might be achieved."

"You transfer the person's mind from their body to their magic, creating a spirit," Cadmus explained. "Then move the spirit out of the body for security. Assuming extensive testing to locate the seat of the brain-damage, you can then use mind-altering charms to bring the brain back in line with the soul. You can do it without the spirit step, which would of course be necessary for Muggles, but then you run a small risk of affecting the soul, as mind magic is a dangerous field which can have irreversible repercussions."

"Ah," Dumbledore spoke. "I can see why that information was lost. It would be too dangerous to lightly pass on."

"And I suppose this falls under the category 'powerful spells' which the Interdict of Merlin stops you from teaching us?" Harry questioned.

The ghostly man smiled sadly. "Indeed; the stone cannot bypass that. However, I would not lightly do so regardless. I am more than happy to explain things of little importance – especially trivialities which in my time even the smallest of children knew – but I hope I do not offend when I say that I see no reason to trust you with anything dangerous, distant family or not."

Harry smirked. Of course we cannot actually learn anything new from this. "I am not offended, sir. And I hope I do not offend when I say that I see no reason to believe you are anything but a figment of my imagination anyway."

The corners of the specter's mouth twitched upwards. "Not to be lightly convinced, I see. Why would you doubt?"

"Well, for a start, I never really believed that souls existed, before, and I haven't seen any evidence."

The man looked intrigued. "But they do."

"Sure, but can you prove that?"

The man frowned, looking confused. Harry started to wreck his mind for ways to explain the concept, but then stopped.

He said that he cannot have original thoughts, or change his mind. If he grew up believing in souls, and everyone around him held the same beliefs, he may not be able to wrap his mind around the idea of someone who doesn't share them. That is, if he was telling the truth, in which case he's right and I'm wrong. If he's just a vision made from our expectations, there's no point reasoning with him anyway.

But that was a strange idea, too. How could you be the same person, without the ability to change your mind or come up with original thoughts? What exactly counted as an "original thought"? The man had contemplated the novel idea of killing someone who was crucioed into insanity, so he wasn't limited to simply answering questions from memory. Would he be able to solve logical puzzles? Would the soul of a mathematician be able to write proofs as long as they did not involve new proof techniques?

"To give a different answer, then," he spoke carefully. "I don't fully understand it. Even with your explanation of what a soul is, I cannot make predictions as to how it will behave in any given experiment."

Cadmus Peverell shrugged. "I believe I understood my brothers better than anyone, yet when I asked them what they wanted for dinner, I could not always predict the answer. This does not mean they didn't exist."

"All right, that was a bad argument," Harry admitted. Just because he didn't have the full picture didn't mean that the theory was false. It could merely mean he needed to experiment more.

"Let's move on. What happens to the soul after the body dies?"

"It goes into the ether," Cadmus replied. "There, they cannot feel, hear, think... just drift. Centuries can pass by almost unnoticed, as sense of time disappears much like in sleep. There is nothing, in short, unless the soul is called back by the stone or similar magic, or unless the person in life has chosen to stay behind as a ghost, and there is a large enough outburst of magic at the time of their death to anchor them."

Dumbledore's eyes widened. "There is no afterlife?"

Cadmus smirked. "Always people jump to conclusions. They see the soul and assume it has a destiny, some greater life beyond the current. No, there is nothing beyond the here and now. If there was, why would anyone disapprove of murder?"

"But then..." the old man protested. "How can there be justice? Why should there even be a soul if there is nothing for it to go on to?"

"There is no inherent justice in the universe," Harry said tiredly. "There's just us."

Although actually, Dumbledore had a point. For what Peverell had said, the soul had no function at all besides preserving someone's personality and memories, which were rooted in their brain – or apparently, in the case of a spirit, in their magic – while they lived, and which was pointless when they died. Why would there be a soul if it didn't do anything? How would something like that even evolve, or if it was created, what intelligent designer would make something so useless?

"You are both right," the ghostly figure answered with a smile. "I am not certain – I have studied the literature extensively but there wasn't much to go on – but it seems likely that the soul was designed rather than arising naturally. All living beings have something that might be called a soul, a consciousness, but only the human soul retains qualities of the owner's personality, and only the human soul persists beyond death. This strongly suggests the hand of a human, and I believe the Atlanteans have had something to do with it. Unsatisfied with the idea of death, I surmise that they designed a piece of magic that would attach itself to the consciousness and preserve a human mind as well as possible, so they could be recovered after death. An unformed soul is shaped from the ambient magic on birth and starts growing during the first years of a human's life – and since it doesn't rely on a person's own magic, even Muggles obtained souls, either as a side effect or because the Atlanteans still considered those without magic worth saving. Unfortunately, either they never found the way to create a new body to supply to a soul, or more likely the art was lost with Atlantis's fall. In short," he nodded to Professor Dumbledore, "there is a purpose, and there is an afterlife. However," he turned to Harry, "it will have to be of our own making."

"This... is a lot to take in," the old man spoke quietly even as Harry's heart raced and a bright sense of purpose ran through his mind. This rang so true to him that he was suddenly willing to forgo his doubts, to just believe that it was true. This did seem like the kind of thing an advanced civilization of magic users might do. And as for the Peverell brothers...

"That is what you were doing," he breathed. "The deathly hallows – you were trying to end death. To reproduce the Atlantean immortality magics."

"Of course," Cadmus nodded. "Did you think us mere artificers?"

Harry glanced at Dumbledore, who was staring at his wand, a startled expression on his face.

"I think the finer details of your history got lost over the years," he said carefully. 'Actually, you're a children's tale now."

"Oh, are we?" Cadmus's voice, speaking the unintelligible ancient English language, took on a harder tone. "Let me guess. We serve as a warning, and the moral of the story is that you should just accept death?"

"Well, yes," Harry said apologetically. "The story says that the three of you met Death on a bridge after just having tricked him by not drowning or something silly like that. He offered you gifts to fool you. Antioch demanded a powerful wand, you wanted the power of resurrection, and Ignotus, the youngest and therefore the cleverest – sorry, that's how fairy tales tend to go – asked to go forth without getting chased by Death. Antioch got his throat slit in the first Inn he visited, you brought back your fiancée but committed suicide because you couldn't really be with her, and Ignotus lived a long life until he passed the invisibility cloak he was given to his son and met death as an old friend. The end."

The specter looked increasingly angry as Helena translated this summary, but composed himself before speaking. "Well. That is quite far from the truth."

"It is known," Professor Dumbledore volunteered, "among the seekers of the 'deathly hallows', it is known that yours is more than a mere story. That the three of you were powerful artificers, making great devices that could withstand the centuries. Some believe that to unite the three hallows is to master death – to bring, evade and undo – but the wiser ones consider the connection with death to be nothing more than a tale that sprang up as your history turned into myth. Or so I thought, but it seems that we who deemed ourselves wise were the fools in this matter."

"They didn't see it," Harry breathed, connecting the dots. "Of course they didn't, the hallows were 'lost' for centuries, and those who had them were sensible enough not to talk about it much. The wand isn't just powerful, I saw that when you fought Riddle: its main strength is defensive power, isn't it? It makes your shields stronger, and it helps you dodge the Killing Curse, but offensively it's no better than other wands."

Dumbledore nodded, and moments later Cadmus did the same.

"So the wand protects you from murder and accident. There was never any doubt about the stone. And the cloak... Well, everyone thought that was just about invisibility and protection from normal detection charms, but that's because they didn't know about Dementors!"

Cadmus raised a spectral eyebrow. "What about Dementors?"

"People didn't realize that the cloak protects you from Dementors, because they didn't know that Dementors represent Death," Harry explained.

"Well, yes, but..." Cadmus began, looking confused, then he stopped. He blinked a few times, as though suddenly realizing something. "You mean you don't know?"

"Know what?" Harry asked, even as a strange and wonderful suspicion started to dawn in the pit of his stomach.

"The cloak stops death," Cadmus said simply. "No more, no less. There's really nothing mysterious about it."

Harry had trouble finding his voice. "You mean that, while I wear this, I cannot die?"

The specter nodded. "The cloak keeps body and soul united. It helps against Dementors because Dementors sense by drawing out small, replaceable pieces of the soul, but that's just a side effect. The main purpose is that it stops you dying."

A glance at Dumbledore told Harry that the old man was just as baffled by this particular tidbit of information as he was.

"So why does it make you invisible?" He blurted out. "Why not make it so that you can constantly wear it without social repercussions?"

The specter grimaced. "Looking at a person's body when the soul is invisible to you is disconcerting to say the least. Ignotus has experimented with methods to circumvent this issue, but while he has succeeded in making the wearer look less disturbing, he could not make it seem normal no matter what he tried. This is why he combined the protections with an invisibility cloak of our mother's design. The invisibility would hide the true purpose of the cloak from outsiders, and it adds an additional layer of protection: in dangerous situations, where you most want to wear the cloak, it is better to not be seen than to stand out, after all. The true owner can will people to see through it, although there is the obvious flaw that when they are heavily wounded, they may not be capable of willing it any longer."

"Ah." Harry had never tried this, but it made some sense that if he could will himself to see through the cloak, he might be able to allow others to do so as well.

"Besides," Peverell continued, "there is only so much point in constantly wearing the cloak. Ultimately, we all failed to reach our goal... Ignotus might have found a way to stall death, but not disease, age or injury."

"Harry blinked. So if you constantly wear it –"

"– you will never die, but you will slowly fall apart, yes. Eventually your body ceases to function, and you will die the instant the cloak is removed."

Damn. Harry deflated. Of course, no one had ever really invented a device that protected you from death. If they had, they wouldn't have died and passed it on. But still, the cloak sounded like it had a lot more potential than what had initially seemed to be the case.

"Can you mass-produce cloaks like this? And if so, could you teach me?"

The specter looked very serious all of a sudden. "What would you do with them?"

"Stop people from dying to curable diseases for a start! If we don't have the medicine or tools to cure people yet, we just put them under a cloak and stun them or put them in an enchanted sleep or something like that, until we've figured out how to treat their disease. Maybe we can do the same for people dying of old age – we're bound to figure out a solution to aging sooner or later, and it's likely to be easier to keep them alive than resurrecting them afterwards. Although, now that I think about it, if the stone can indeed bring souls back –"

Harry had not expected the burst of laughter that followed this question and interrupted his train of thought. The ghostly figure had a deep, warm laugh, and his eyes shone with genuine mirth.

"Oh, you do remind me of Ignotus – you are a heir of the Peverells indeed."

"So is it possible?"

"No," Peverell said simply. "Not unless you manage to invent a shortcut. Making a single cloak takes years of work, even if you are familiar with the spells Ignotus created, which I suspect you are not since you did not even know what a soul was."

Harry nodded glumly. "There's something else. I have a bunch of dead bodies around, who were preserved right after they died. I think we can fix the injuries in most cases, but with the two people I tried, we couldn't get the heart to restart, even though one of them was in perfect condition. I think that result might be entirely consistent with the soul being gone, though... can I use the stone, maybe together with the cloak, to put the souls back into the bodies?"

Cadmus looked him over, frowning.

"I fear you think entirely too lightly of this," he said seriously. "I do not blame you. Ignotus was not much older than you when we embarked on our quest, and I remember his enthusiasm and ambition all too well. We actually thought we would secure immortality in the first twenty years or so." He looked grim. "And yet, we spent all our lives working, and it wasn't enough. We made progress, but ultimately we failed, and had to leave the job to our descendants."

Harry didn't wilt under the implied rebuke. "I am a descendant, and I intend to complete it."

Cadmus smiled, his wispy eyes meeting Harry's. "I'm glad that another member of the family is willing to follow in our footsteps, but I hope you are truly prepared for the path ahead. It is long, and heavy. You might never finish your self-imposed duty."

"I know." Harry stared back into those eyes, his resolve growing. "But I'm going to at least try."

Cadmus smiled, and looked considering. "I am glad for it. Did you have more questions?"

Harry tried to sort out his thoughts. A large part of him was starting to believe the specter's tale, but a smaller part was urging caution not to believe something too easily just because he wanted to believe it. Even if the story was true, though, it wasn't exactly helpful. It was promising if souls were indeed saved in the ether – whatever that was – for later recovery, but there was an incredibly long path still to go, and all the spells the three brothers had developed would have been lost due to the Interdict of Merlin. He'd basically have to start over, although the specter of Cadmus might give him some pointers – if he could persuade the man (ghost, soul?) to trust him with potentially dangerous information.

In the silence, Professor Dumbledore stepped forward. "If I may ask... was there a prophecy? This has been a point of contention for centuries."

Cadmus turned to him. "There was, in fact. That is part of what started our quest." He smiled at the old man. "Should I regale the true tale of the Peverell brothers?"

"You would indulge the curiosity of an old man for the phantasms he used to chase in his youth," the man replied. He glanced at Harry.

"I don't mind." In fact, it would probably be useful to get the specter talking about his history; it might bring up questions he wouldn't even think about asking otherwise.

Cadmus beamed brightly, leading Harry to suspect that the revelation that his life's work had been reduced to a children's tale with the contrary moral had been a severe strike to his ego, seemed to take a deep breath, and started his tale.

"There were three of us: Antioch, Ignotus and I. Our father a Muggle smith; our mother – Manura Peverell – a witch and the greatest artificer of our age. Indeed, her creations were renowned all over the known world. She took all of us as apprentices, and taught us most of our crafts. The beauty of the Runes, combined with plants and creatures, and the life she instilled in father's work... She taught us that almost nothing is impossible with magic, when you know what you're doing." He sighed deeply. "She was killed in a duel when I was fifteen, Antioch twenty and Ignotus thirteen.

"My brothers and I talked a lot, after that. Father gave us the usual spiel of how death comes to everyone in time, and we should learn to accept it. We disagreed. Unfortunately, our training was incomplete, especially Ignotus's, and father was talking with a local wizard to apprentice him out. Our resolve might have been broken by circumstance and the absolute dismissal of everyone around us, until we heard that prophecy. 'Three shall be their devices by which death shall be defeated.' Those were her actual words. Shall be defeated. We concluded that, if we embarked on our quest, we were destined to succeed, which settled the matter. Together we swore that we wouldn't bow to death, nor allow ourselves to be cowed by the limited views of those who would call us dark, fools or both.

"Antioch, greatly affected by the way mother had died, focused on premature death. He searched the world for defensive and healing magics and developed several defenses of his own. Ignotus and I were more ambitious, and desired to stop death altogether. Ignotus started to study what exactly happens at the moment of death; my own research was focused on the soul.

"As Antioch had been studying the secrets of wand lore before we set out on our quest, his research culminated in the development of a wand which provided the greatest protections magic could afford. It was far from complete, however. The wand is powerful – it can sustain the strain of customized spells which are impossible to cast with normal wands, and can channel near-limitless magical power if required – but it cannot modify or overpower existing spells except those Antioch built it for, self-defense spells. Its protections could not be extended to others easily, nor be turned towards healing without first designing new charms. It was a first attempt; we had only been at this task for twelve years. Unfortunately, it was already sufficient to cause jealousy, and an old friend poisoned him and stole the wand."

"And so Death took the first brother for his own," Dumbledore muttered.

"Yes, I suppose the fairy tale got that part right," Cadmus spoke sadly. "Antioch's death came as an enormous shock to us, and threw off our plans and our faith. We had intended to work on our goal together, we hadn't expected to die before fulfilling it! And then, as Antioch was supposed to be the one dealing with disease and Ignotus, emerged in his studies, had barely even started what would become his life's work, there was nothing I could do when my beloved Liaire contracted Glowpox and succumbed to it three days later. She was then but nineteen, and I twenty-seven, and the only knowledge my research had provided thus far was that there wasn't an afterlife." His voice took on a bitter tone. "It took me seven years before I finally managed to give shape and speech to souls, and then another six years to find individual souls through a connection they made in life. And then, at last, I could be with her again. Or so I thought."

He sighed wearily. "I should have realized it earlier, through my experiments with the random souls I could capture. She was no longer alive; she had lost the capacity for change. She was who she had always been, which meant that she was forever stuck as an immature teenager, even though I had changed. And whenever I would ask her to make a non-obvious choice, she simply could not do it, like a donkey torn between food and water. She could hear new information, but would never change her opinions. And in realizing that, it was like losing her all over again.

"I let her go, and plunged myself back into my research with a zeal. I did a great many experiments, and succeeded in making a permanent artifact to summon souls: the stone you see before you. Having done that much, and understanding the nature of the soul and the ether better than anyone alive, I started looking into ways to return thinking capacity to souls – perhaps in the form of magic, but ideally by creating new bodies for them. Often I worked together with Ignotus whose experiments to stop death coincided with my own in several ways, but he had a wife, he had children, he could not always work. I could, and did. Unfortunately, I was so consumed with my research that I stopped taking good care of myself. Ignotus, using the stone, told me afterwards that his wife found my body slumped over a large sheaf of calculations.

"As for Ignotus... Where my research was focused on retrieving souls from the dead, Ignotus preferred to stop them from passing on in the first place. We reused a lot of each other's discoveries – for example, we both made artifacts to bind a soul in place – and he made his cloak that kept the soul firmly anchored in the body shortly after I completed the stone. Unfortunately, we both knew it wouldn't be enough, as it wouldn't stop aging. He had pinned his hopes on the creation of a Philosopher's Stone, as the cloak could protect him from the worst of the backlash, but the spells on the cloak interfered with the alchemical magic, and that hope was lost. Without this protection, he didn't dare take the risk; he had too much to live for.

"He spent the rest of his life with his wife and three children, both improving the cloak and working on medical research. He discovered a great many things about the functioning of the body and, with the help of his family, developed treatments for various magical and non-magical diseases, including a potion that would have saved my Liaire if it had been available before. However, he never found a way to halt or reverse aging without a greater sacrifice, nor to make a new human body without a soul to inhabit it. And then, as he was nearing the end of his natural life, he lost his wife, his eldest child and all her children in some stupid, senseless war. He told me of that, the last time we spoke. He had been disillusioned with the project for years, but this... he said that we'd attacked the problem from the wrong direction. That we should fix the world before trying to deliver immortality to the wrong people. I disagreed with him, of course, but then, that would have been my response in life; I do not know whether he would have been able to persuade me if I had been able to change my mind."

"The last enemy that shall be destroyed is death," Dumbledore whispered.

Peverell turned to him sharply. "Where did you hear that?"

"James Potter," Dumbledore replied. "Harry's father, an earlier descendant from your brother. It was their family motto, in a sense, an ancient text from the Christian bible. James said that it simply meant to move beyond the fear of death, or so his father had told him."

Cadmus grimaced. "That is a bizarre interpretation."

The former Headmaster shrugged. "In hindsight, I am forced to agree."

"I also disagree with Ignotus's analysis, though," Harry spoke up. "If death is irreversible, you want to get rid of it before spending too much time on things that can be fixed. If it isn't, then knowing that resurrection is possible is likely to be helpful for those other problems. Immortality is the ultimate bribe. Would a small dictator still accept money to screw over the people in favor of large corporations if he knew that doing too much evil would lose him the chance of living forever?"

"That assumes that sensible and well-intended people are always going to be in control over who gets resurrected," the specter pointed out. "But yes, there are arguments either way." He shrugged, then shot Harry a penetrating look. "So tell me... if more than a thousand years have passed, what does the world look like today? Have its ills been fixed yet?"

"Well... no," Harry confessed. "Things have gotten better, I think, but they're not exactly good yet. Definitely not everywhere, and you probably wouldn't like what has become of the magical world."

"Oh?" Cadmus asked, raising his eyebrows.

"A lot of magic has been forgotten," Harry said blandly. "A lot. We don't know how to make artifacts which last for centuries anymore. Witches and wizards have been growing steadily weaker as powerful spells were lost, most likely due to the Interdict of Merlin."

Cadmus winced at that.

"But there have also been some good changes," Harry continued. "Particularly in the Muggle world. The entire magical world has lived in secret for almost five hundred years, and Muggles have invented science – I mean, they systematically started testing their beliefs and figuring out the laws of the universe, except that they didn't notice magic yet, probably because we were hiding it. So now, it isn't good everywhere, there's a lot of places in the world which are still way behind, but at least in the richer countries there's far less poverty and disease, and also not much fighting. Muggles also use all kinds of inventions, which have brought their quality of life much closer to the standard witches and wizards are used to. For example, you don't need magic to talk to someone on the other side of the planet anymore. Kings and emperors have lost most of their power; the people choose their own rulers now."

The ghostly image inclined its head. "So the Muggle world has been gaining, and the magical world only losing?"

"Well, not only," Harry said, remembering himself. "That's really just the vibe I've been getting from the last five hundred years. I think one of the major events after your death was Hogwarts: four powerful witches and wizards built a school where all magical children in Britain and Ireland were invited to learn magic. I think that probably made a vast difference with your time. There are magical schools in other countries too, now."

"All children learning magic in a single place rather than through apprenticeships?" Peverell asked, surprised. "Yes, I imagine it would make a large difference."

Dumbledore cleared his throat. "Don't forget about recent events."

"Oh, right. Compared to your time it probably doesn't make that much of a difference, but the Statute of Secrecy was overthrown last month. Witches and wizards are back under the authority of the Muggle government, and we've made all kinds of cooperation agreements. Oh, and a couple of friends and I destroyed all Dementors."

Cadmus's eyes widened at the last point. "So that stain is finally removed from the world. And you participated? How did you do it?"

"A variation of the normal Patronus Charm which I developed. The key is simply to cast the usual spell with defiance of death as your happy thought. Expecto Patronum!"

Cadmus stared at the glowing figure, and then back at Harry, his eyes filled with considerable interest.

"That is weighty news indeed!" The specter spoke when Harry lowered his wand again. "I am impressed; it would never have occurred to me to do that. Have you tried the stone on any victims of the Dementors?"

Harry shook his head. "Not yet, I wanted to check with you first to know what I should think about the stone in the first place."

"Hmmm. Well, I would be interested whether it works. I know that the soul of those Kissed by a Dementor does not seem to go into the ether, regardless of whether the body survives. However, one possible reading of the ancient texts suggests that a consumed soul stays with its Dementor. If the soul persists rather than being destroyed, you may have liberated them."

That sounded good, unless... "They wouldn't have been aware during all that time, would they?"

"It's enough to make you hope that the souls have been destroyed, is it not?" Cadmus spoke quietly. "I do not know. I have done many experiments during my life, but those with Dementors were limited as there weren't that many around, and I wasn't foolish enough to create some, or evil enough to sacrifice people to it. I should like to know what you find, if only to satisfy my curiosity."

"You can still be curious?" Professor Dumbledore queried. "Forgive me if the question offends, but I have never known a ghost to wonder about facts of the present."

"I am not a ghost," the ghostly figure smiled. "I am a summoned soul. In particular, I am the soul of the person who made this stone, and in life I have placed a significant part of my own magic inside it. This allows me a better memory and awareness of the world than most while I am tied to it, although it will still not allow me to change my mind on any subject."

"I'm happy to try it," Harry said, suddenly very curious for this experiment as well. "I'll need to turn you off to test this though, won't I?"

"Yes, go ahead. But do call me back soon, there is more we need to discuss. And keep in mind that you can only summon specific people, whose life you have touched in some way. I am an exception due to my connection with the stone, but for other people, the stone cannot find a soul merely by the name of the body they used to inhabit in life. It needs to draw the connection from your mind, so you must have known them personally."

Harry nodded. "Is it entirely safe? Can a malicious soul do anything to me?"

"Other than attempting to manipulate you, no. They have no power but speech, and you can dismiss them at any time."

"Thank you." Harry turned the stone over in his hand, and the shade of Cadmus Peverell disappeared.

"Please tell me you're not about to do what I think you are about to do," the old wizard whispered.

"Why not?" Harry asked. "I know it's not a good test due to the horcrux thing and all, but Peverell said it's safe, you said the stone hadn't been tampered with, and this is a question we really want an answer to."

Before the other could argue further, he turned the stone three times in his hand. "Tom Marvolo Riddle."

-o-o-o-o-o-

Author's Note: "Néade sé bregus ongrataþ on þín dæg." is supposed to be the translation of "May the gods smile on your day." If some reader actually speaks old English well enough to provide proper translations, I'd be open to replacing the current sentences. ;)

Chapter 115: The Deathly Hallows, Pt 2

Within moments, mists started gathering like before. Harry heard a sharp intake of breath from the former Headmaster as they swirled into the figure of a handsome man with dark hair and darker eyes. The man didn't look anything like Professor Quirrell had, but nevertheless, there was something familiar about him.

The specter looked around, at himself and the room, glancing dismissively at Dumbledore before settling his eyes on Harry.

Harry swallowed. "Hello Professor."

The man stared silently for a long time before speaking.

"I see the dynamic of our respective situations has been altered somewhat. How much time has passed?"

"Three weeks," Harry answered.

"Hmmm. And have you managed to destroy civilization yet?" There was no anger in the question, merely resignation.

"No," he replied. "Actually, we're doing quite well. The Muggle and magical governments have merged, the violence has stopped, people in the space program are looking at phoenixes with considerable interest, and several collaborative research projects have already been proposed – but only in approved fields, like medical and nuclear science, and with all possible precautions."

The specter rolled his eyes. "Precautions. What do you know of caution?"

"Not enough," Harry admitted. "But there are other people who do, and they refined my initial ideas quite a bit. I never planned to work alone, Professor."

"Like Dumbledore?" He hissed . "You follow him now?"

"It would be closer to say that he follows me," Harry answered with a shrug and a glance at Professor Dumbledore to see how he took this answer. The former Headmaster did not respond; he stood silently in the corner, staring at the specter with a look of what could only be hatred on his face, an expression that seemed almost alien on him. "Or simply that I take his advice into account along with many other people's."

"You may wish to choose your advisors more carefully." Tom Riddle turned his head to the former Headmaster and shot him a look of pure venom. "Tell me, Albus. It was you, wasn't it, who told lesser wizards of the Death-ritual? I can even understand the boy's idiocy, but for all your faults I would never have believed it of you."

"You are hardly one to reproach me, Tom," Dumbledore spoke, his voice hard.

"Oh, I do not blame you – you were saving your own life, after all. I might have done the same, in your place. But then, I never pretended to be noble."

Harry thought he saw a slight crack in Dumbledore's demeanor as Riddle smirked. Riddle's eyes turned back to Harry. "But congratulations. You won, for however brief your victory may last."

"If you are trying to steer me to your point of view," Harry said coolly, "it won't work. I will never agree that being cautious requires the kinds of sacrifices you tend to make."

"That is only because you have not the slightest sense of what it means to be cautious. Had you possessed even a shred of self-preservation, you would have not have dared to summon the soul of a known enemy so quickly, particularly one who has partaken in soul magics far beyond your understanding."
Harry swallowed. "The stone only summons a ghost-like specter, I knew it wouldn't give you any power but speech.""You knew?" The specter raised an eyebrow. "Did you determine that beyond all reasonable doubt? Did you take preparations for the eventuality that you were wrong?" He stared in Harry's eyes, unblinkingly. Harry tried to school his expression, not looking away even as he felt a hot ball of embarrassment start in his stomach.
Riddle smirked. "You did not, nor did you send another, more replaceable person in your stead. You might have summoned a spirit, given me power and allowed me to possess you – or the old man for that matter. If I had retained my magic, and the stone works as I surmise, this is exactly what would have happened." He grimaced. "You are fortunate, however. It seems that while the Dementor did not manage to destroy my soul, it has taken my magic and thus rendered me incapable of independent action."

"Cadmus Peverell said it was safe," Harry defended himself, ignoring the voice of self criticism that was whispering in his ear that he hadn't asked what the likely consequence would be if the soul in question had active horcruxes, an omission that seemed rather dangerous in hindsight. Would Peverell even know that? The situation between him and Riddle seemed reasonably unique, especially since it involved destroying a Dementor. In fact... Harry had been foolish enough to bring a horcrux in Riddle's presence. Tom Riddle hadn't said it, but that might be because he didn't know whether Dumbledore knew what he had done to Harry.

Note to self: think before acting. Thank you for that lesson, Professor Quirrell.

Riddle inclined his head. "If you managed to persuade the stone's creator to speak with you, I suppose it is possible that your questioning was adequate. Did Cadmus Peverell have other things to say?"

"Yes," Harry said curtly. "He did." He wasn't quite sure whether he should give a known enemy more information than that. "But why don't you know that already? You had the stone before me. Didn't you want to take the risk?"

"Some risks must be taken in the pursuit of greater power," the specter shrugged. "However, he was not very forthcoming towards me or those I asked to try. I could not begin to unravel the enchantments and runes on the stone without harming them, so it is entirely possible that information about the person summoning Peverell is passed onto him. That, or he is just very careful. Others did speak to me, but I could only summon those I had personally known, which rather limited its usability."

"I see." Or it is because I'm part of the family and have the cloak to prove it. Or in fact... maybe Cadmus trusted me because I was asking for completely different things than what you would have tried. That, or you're lying and trying to lure me into a false sense of security by pretending that I know things that you don't.

It didn't really matter. He studied his old mentor, taking in the somehow-not-quite-unfamiliar face.

Riddle broke the silence first. "You summoned me here. Why? After as little as three weeks, I assume that you are not yet ready to resurrect me. You wish to boast of your victory, perhaps? To tell me that you were right and I was wrong?"

Harry looked up, meeting his eyes. "Mostly, to see whether you were there. I never thought of you as my enemy, Professor."

Riddle gave him a long look.

"I suppose such words have less meaning between the likes of us. What do you want, Potter?"

"Answers."

"Naturally." The handsome face twisted into a small smirk. "And why should I give them?"

"Ultimately, I believe that we want the same thing." The man inclined his head to show he was listening. "Immortality, safety, and for people to stop acting so bloody stupid all the time. I fully intend to resurrect everyone who's died before, as you predicted when you wrote that letter, and I'm also planning to bring you back. I will need some reassurances that you aren't going to kill a bunch of people again, though."

"I wrote that letter before I witnessed your final stupidity," Riddle pointed out, voice bitter. "You held the world in your hands, and you elected to pass it over to fools."

"Actually, the final treaty has turned out perfectly fine," Harry said icily. "And as for giving the world away, I like to think that I still have some control. Not formally, perhaps, but the part of your plan where I draw a lot of positive attention actually worked out pretty well, even if it's more from the side of the Muggles. The magical side don't hate me anymore, though, and since I'm the public face of our world to Muggles, I could still potentially end up ruling the world. Not that I'm planning to actually do that."

"You had better be prepared for it," Riddle spoke calmly, "and soon. You have brought the world into a very volatile position. Now things look well, now people want peace, but give it a year or two and you will see how it all falls apart when the politicians are allowed to run with the situation." There was not a hint of doubt in the specter's words. "Will you be there, when the next threat to the planet comes? For unless you hurry up with your resurrections, I will not be there to protect it any longer."

Harry swallowed. "What have you been doing so far to save the earth?"

"Would you like a list?"

"Yes, actually, that would be rather useful."

"And what will you do with it?"

"Learn from what you did and continue the protection," Harry said patiently. "I like the world. I would really prefer not to see it destroyed. And that's in your interest too, because eventually you'll want to be brought back to it. Was that not why you gave me the stone? Because some hope for a real existence is better than none?"

The specter made a vaguely agreeing movement with his head. "And what kinds of measures would you be willing to consider taking?"

Harry hesitated.

"Not such extreme ones as you seem to favor," he said eventually. "I don't like killing people or other questionable techniques like memory-charms. Also, I like Muggle science, and I'm not willing to hold it back, although the proper study of magic will probably have to wait for a generation until there are enough sensible scientists in both worlds to do careful research."

"Yet with such an attitude," the man spoke softly, "you will see everything destroyed."

"Perhaps," Harry shrugged. Riddle had died believing Harry to be a hopeless case, he realized. And as Cadmus had said, he would be unable to change his mind, no matter what Harry said. Nevertheless, he'd had the stone for months before passing it on to Harry. He must have prepared, considered what he would do in all conceivable situations. And that meant that it had to be possible to bargain with him. "But you really can't stop me, as these are some of my core values. You're better off hoping that it works out, and giving me more information to work from will only improve your chances. So, are you willing to help, or not?"

The specter gave him a considering look, and Harry wondered whether he had asked a "non-obvious question" that would leave the disembodied soul incapable of choice.

"I will," the man said, eventually. "Indeed, I shall offer you more than what you ask for. If you wish it, I will serve you with advice on your endeavors. I may well be able to catch some of your idiocies before they go too far." He grimaced. "I cannot say it will be pleasant, as I care very little for this state, having neither body nor magic and what is infinitely worse, an impaired mind, but I suspect my help may be invaluable."

In the corner, Dumbledore made a choked sound, which caused a brief expression of amusement on Riddle's face.

Harry frowned. He was undoubtedly getting manipulated, but he and Riddle were on the same side, unless he was completely mistaken about what the man wanted. The specter would have a major cognitive deficit in not being able to ever update his beliefs, but if Harry took that into account, it could be overcome. Harry was also still not a hundred percent convinced that the specter was actually a real soul rather than the product of his imagination, but in the latter case, it would come out soon enough.

"Thank you." He glanced at Dumbledore again, who looked white in the face but didn't seem to want to reprimand Harry in front of Riddle. There were many more questions to ask, but they could wait; his old mentor was likely to be more honest when Dumbledore wasn't listening in (although it might be a good idea to ask the old wizard for protections he really should have before being alone with the "ghost" of Voldemort).

"In order to test that you're real, could you tell me –" he thought for a moment, "did you teach Bellatrix any of Slytherin's lore? And if so, could you persuade her to teach me?"

"Just to test whether I'm real?" His mouth curled into an amused smile. "I taught her some things, but nothing that your good friend and loyal follower Albus wouldn't also know. The ritual to summon Fiendfyre for example, although I would strongly urge you not to attempt this until you have practiced your force of will in trials less likely to kill you if you fail. Should you wish to learn from her regardless, she will obey you as she would me if you tell her that the basilisk lies forgotten by Salazar's feet."

"Thank you." This could be tested easily, and was valuable for far more reasons. Aside from power over Bellatrix Black (something which he'd better not abuse too badly), Riddle had just – probably on purpose – given Dumbledore a reason not to withhold magical knowledge from Harry.

He quickly rifled through his mind, but there were no other urgent questions; most could be postponed until later, when Dumbledore wasn't around, and when he'd had the time to sort through a list of priorities. Which left the question he'd summoned Riddle for in the first place. Mostly it had been answered by Riddle actually being summonable, but there were some details open.

"I have many questions left," he said. "But for now... I wanted to ask you about your death. Do you remember it? And maybe what came after?"

Riddle stiffened, and his expression darkened. "I do." The tone could have cut steel.

"Could you... tell me about it?"

"It was unpleasant," Tom Riddle said icily. "I believe you have some moderately similar experience, although I assure you that the sensation of being sucked into the darkness, having your magic ripped apart and your world melting down into pure fear, anger and regret, and then persisting in that state with the ability to sense but not think for seconds or minutes or hours until your consciousness is finally snuffed out is likely to be several factors beyond what you sensed for merely being in the presence of a Dementor."

Harry swallowed. "I see. We destroyed the Dementor roughly a minute afterwards. You didn't sense that?"

"That might have been the ending of consciousness," Riddle replied. "As I recall, quite a few people have been taken by Dementors not too long before me; I would suggest that you ask some of them whether their torments lasted longer."

Harry took a deep breath, a choking feeling of horror starting to rise. "Okay. I guess I will. Thank you, and, um, I'll see you later." He turned the stone over in his hand, and Riddle disappeared.

"Harry!" The old wizard said urgently when they were alone again. "What are you doing? How can you make such promises?"

Harry stared at the stone, not really caring much about the old man's qualms at the moment. "Do you know any other Dementor-victims?"

The old wizard blinked. "Yes, I do, and I understand why it's important, but Harry. You just promised Lord Voldemort to seek his advice on all your future endeavors!"

Harry sighed. "He may be right, you know. I'm in over my head, and I might not see it coming if things are about to go wrong. Even just killing him might have put the world in danger. His input is bound to be valuable."

"He is manipulating you! You are not in over your head." He grabbed Harry's shoulders, gently but firmly. "The world was never yours to control, and thus it is no problem that you lack the power to do so. Do not make that mistake, Harry. You are not like him, and the more you allow him to guide you, the more you will start believing that you are."

Harry looked up into the deeply worried eyes, and felt a twinge of guilt. Perhaps he had allowed himself to get carried away by the former Defense Professor. But right now, his feelings were in turmoil for an entirely different reason, and he wasn't about to get distracted.

"I understand what you're saying, Professor," he said slowly. "If the only thing he can do is manipulate me, then that's exactly what he's going to do, so I should be wary, I get that. I promise you that I won't just call him again, I'll at least check with you or someone else first. Is that okay?" The old man didn't look convinced, so he added: "He can be useful, extremely so. For example, if what Riddle said was true, then I can get Bellatrix to listen to me now. Weren't you worried about her torturing your friend Moody?"

Dumbledore nodded slowly. "I suppose that you are right that some good may come of it, although I am not convinced that it outweighs the risks."

"Right. So, we'll talk about this, but right now I have something bigger on my mind. Do you, or do you not, personally know anyone else who has been subjected to the Dementor's Kiss?"

"Some," Dumbledore said cautiously. "But Harry, are you sure you wish to know this? If what you surmise is the truth, only grief can come from its confirmation."

"What is true is already so; owning up to it cannot make it worse."

Helena humphed at that. Harry jumped. He'd almost forgotten she was still there. "Yet what is in the past is in the past. Knowing about it cannot make it better."

Harry considered arguing with the ghost, but thought better of it. "We still need to test it. Riddle was a very bad sample, seeing as the Horcruxes might have kept his soul from being destroyed."

The former Headmaster sighed and took the stone from his hands. He stared at it for some moments.

"Do you believe now, then? That the stone functions as is claimed, and the appearance of souls is not some trick conjured from your mind?"

"I cannot yet be sure either way. But..." He shrugged helplessly. "I feel like it's genuine. I know that I'm probably affected by my own biases, not least the standard bias of taking things at face value, but I'm still inclined to believe it. And that might not even be so bad, as long as I keep reminding myself that there is a real chance that it isn't all true."

"And as you grow towards belief in what we see before us, I find myself having trouble to accept it," the man said gently. "Although I confess I have no justification, beside an old man's inability to change his mind and the wish that what he sees is a deception."

He took a deep breath. "But very well. Let us see this investigation to the end." He turned the stone three times in his hand. "Arya McFusty."

The thing that appeared before them didn't have a human shape. It didn't look like much of anything, just a large blob of mist.

"Hello?" Harry tried.

There was no response.

"Madam McFusty?" Professor Dumbledore tried.

There was no response.

Dumbledore turned the stone over in his hand, his face pale. "I suppose that answers some questions."

Dumbledore's next attempt was one of Voldemort's former followers who had been imprisoned during the last war, and then given to the Dementors when he tried to attack his guards. The misty shape looked more like a human now, but barely. It made some incoherent sounds which might have been English, but they couldn't speak to it.

Arya McFusty had died during Grindelwald's war, roughly fifty years ago. There was nothing left of her consciousness. There was something, but not much, left of Alfred Carrow's consciousness after twelve years. Apparently, the Dementors took their time to consume a soul completely. Dumbledore didn't personally know anyone who'd been Kissed closer to the Dementor's destruction, and they couldn't summon any of the victims of Dark Monday simply by name, but Harry couldn't shake the fear that the souls might have been aware during all that time, while the Dementor steadily consumed them until nothing remained. There would have to be more tests, but somehow Harry didn't feel that knowing the truth would necessarily be a good thing anymore. He was feeling rather sick at the moment.

If Dementors are death, how can they be so much worse than the real thing? How can they destroy a soul when death only stores it?

The answer came easily. They represent what death used to be, before the Atlanteans designed the soul as a backup-mechanism. Perhaps they even created Dementors as a new form of death which would be able to kill immortals who crossed some line. But if that is the case, they wouldn't have needed to make their victims suffer for a long time on top of that, would they? It doesn't fit the "death" picture to do so.. Or were they really that cruel?

A House Elf placed a glass of chocolate milk and a plate of cookies in front of him.

"Rest some, Harry," the Chief Warlock spoke gently. "I know this is a lot to take in, but it doesn't do to rush to conclusions, or to torture yourself over things which cannot be changed." Despite the words, the tone of the voice echoed the old man's grief and horror as much as Harry felt them.

Harry took a sip, but shook his head. "I want to finish talking with Cadmus. Are you up to it, Helena?"

The ghost, who was also looking subdued, nodded. "I will help."

This time it was Dumbledore who summoned the specter of Cadmus Peverell. Harry didn't mind. A small part of him observed from the back of his mind that if Cadmus suddenly behaved very differently, it was a data point for the stone being a ruse, but he didn't believe in that anymore. When presented with information that he really wanted to believe, Harry had still found it in his heart to be skeptic, but with the opposite, his doubts had all but faded.

"It appears," he told the specter with a lump in his throat, "that Demented souls indeed persist."

He couldn't go on after that, but Professor Dumbledore stepped in with his own account of what had transpired.

Finally, Cadmus nodded, looking sorrowed. "That is grave news indeed. But if they suffered, at least they do not do so any longer, little comfort though that is."

"Hardly," Harry said, staring ahead. "The only good thing I can see about this nightmare is that souls aren't destroyed or obviously affected immediately. There was a huge Dementor-raid just a few weeks back with some ten thousand people getting Kissed, but we destroyed the Dementors very quickly afterwards. Those people, at least, did not suffer for long, and should be just as resurrectable as everyone else."

"Hmmm," Cadmus nodded, looking thoughtful. "Did you happen to keep the bodies around?"

Harry looked up at the tone. That did not sound like it was a random question.

"Most were killed, but some got away. Why?"

"Because the Dementor's Kiss takes the soul and the magic, but not the body's life force," Peverell explained. "That much is certain, for otherwise the bodies could not continue to function, but would rather start decomposing. If the souls are now liberated – and can be retrieved by the stone – I do believe it should be possible to reunite body and soul."

Dumbledore blanched, his eyes widening. "By my hands..." He whispered. "For my folly. Oh Merlin, what have I done?"

Harry felt a stab of pain, too, on top of the horror he'd already been nurturing, and none of the hope that the words should have brought. He hadn't spent much time thinking about Dumbledore's – and various other people's – act of killing the Dementor-victims in a misguided attempt to save the Statute of Secrecy or help them in some way; between watching thousands of people get killed in the span of one six-times repeated hour, Hogwarts getting destroyed, seeing his friends, Professor McGonagall and his mother die in front of his eyes, taking command in a battle and being responsible for ending a war, he'd pushed everything that wasn't of immediate importance to the back of his mind. The murder of some ten thousand comatose people who might have been salvageable had been overshadowed by all the other violence, loss and grief. However, it came back with a vengeance now.

Ten thousand people who could have been saved had died because of ignorance.

"Get yourself to the Ministry," Harry snarled at the old man who was now shaking all over his body. "And send word that any further Dementor-victims should not be euthanized, nor lethally experimented on for that matter."

The grieving wizard didn't reply, but simply disappeared in a burst of flame.

"How?" He demanded from Cadmus.

The vision regarded him for a long time. "I suspect there is some context I am not aware of."

"Even if only one in a hundred are still alive, it's better to save those than to pretend we never could have done it to stop people from feeling guilty or being accused of murder," Harry said coolly.

"Ah." The specter raised his eyebrows. "And what of the consequences? Have you considered the possibility of suicide?"

Harry blinked. He hadn't. But then, the Aurors who'd gone out to kill the Dementor-victims had been well-intentioned, just like Dumbledore had been. The Muggle doctors who had declared their patients beyond help had been well-intentioned. This evil had not been done out of malice, and any line of action would come at a price.

"We can deal with that. I'll talk with sensible people – people who don't have an emotional investment like Professor Dumbledore has – to figure out the best way to break the news."

"You do seem sincere." Cadmus continued staring at him. Finally, he added: "I will trust you."

"Thank you. So, you'll tell me how it works?"

Dumbledore reappeared with a flash of fire. "I have passed the message."

"Welcome back," Cadmus said politely. He held out a hand, pointing at the old man's wand. "You do realize you have dear Antioch's old wand, don't you? Does it recognize you as its owner?"

"It does," Professor Dumbledore replied, slightly confused.

"Well, you might have mentioned it before. Anyway, young Peverell, the method in question should be simple in theory, although I must warn you that this is merely a thought experiment which I have debated with Ignotus when we were younger. I have never had the opportunity to apply it in practice and there may well be complications. The idea is to use the stone to summon the soul, place it on the body, and dress the body in the cloak. Dismiss the soul, which cannot leave because of the cloak, and use a charm to bind it into the body."

Straightforward. "Professor, do you happen to know any good charms to bind the soul back into the body?"

The former Headmaster frowned. "Not directly, but I may be able to construct one. Soul magic is generally considered a dark art, but I may know some people who would have books I could use as reference material."

The specter nodded. "For obvious reasons I never developed such a spell myself, but I imagine it should be possible. Especially since you have Antioch's wand: it will allow its owner to cast customized spells which are infeasible with normal wands. That should give you enough leeway to use even a naive design, or build additional protections into your spell."

Harry breathed deeply. In between all the worries today had brought, there was one shining point of light.

"And thus death is defeated when the hallows are united," Professor Dumbledore spoke quietly.

"Yes," Cadmus nodded. "Or at least, Dementation is. However, I must warn that we never got far enough to bother looking into ways to restore someone's magic. Even if you manage recovering these people, they will be Muggles afterwards."

"They were Muggles anyway," Harry shrugged. "But if it's so easy for Dementor-victims, why would it be impossible to bring back people with perfectly preserved corpses? Can't we use the same technique?"

"I never said it couldn't be done," Cadmus pointed out. "Merely that it wouldn't be easy. Which it won't be. I would not have embarked on this mission if I believed the goal to be fully impossible, however. Tell me, how were those corpses preserved?"

"An anti-decomposition charm. Most of the bodies were under the charm before they died, but they did mostly die rather violently. It was non-magical damage, though, and I think in most cases the brains are intact."

"Hmmm. Does the spell in question preserve life force?"

"No," Dumbledore answered sadly. "I believe it preserves the potential force and growth status, but it doesn't stop the deactivation upon death."

"Then unless you happen to have a philosopher's stone lying around..."

Harry coughed. "Let's assume, for the sake of conversation, that we do."

"Ah? That changes quite a lot. And you have access to a phoenix, I see, not to mention Antioch's wand." He looked thoughtful, then sighed.

"I cannot design the setup you would need, even though I have the feeling that something could be done. You have the stone and the cloak to place the soul back into the body, and I suspect that even a single drop of Elixir could reactivate the life when you have a phoenix. The problem is in the combination. The soul will not lightly attach itself to a non-living body, nor does the Elixir have anything to latch onto when the soul is not attached. You will certainly need some dedicated spells... but if you make a mistake in the spell design, you risk damaging either the body or the soul beyond repair."

He stopped, massaging his head and looking stressed. "I'm sorry. If I were still alive, I would have come up with a dozen potential solutions, but neither I nor my brothers ever had access to Elixir of Life, so we never considered questions like this in great depth. Ignotus finally found a way to give some of your own life force to another, but that's a lossy process which only works if both parties are alive, and willing. Not to mention, it was decades after my death, and very close to his own; we certainly did not develop any magic specifically dedicated to this task. There are some spells which might be useful, but I could not pass those to you due to the Interdict of –"

"– Merlin," Harry finished, gritting his teeth. He was really starting to hate the mythical mage.

"Yes," Cadmus nodded. "I can offer you my input, though. Advice on how the body and soul work, knowledge of magic that may have been forgotten, even if I cannot teach you spells. I believe that, if you set your mind to it, you may be able to create the magic to restore those lives within a couple of years. You certainly have the right kind of personality to develop the requisite spells."

Years. He didn't have years to study just one subject, he had to finish his education too, not to mention all the political maneuvers he might need to try. And would he even be able to stop the grieving parents from wanting to bury their children? Would they believe him if he said there was still hope?

Developing this magic would be useful even without the immediate need, of course. Future people could profit, when dying of illness or injury; they merely needed to be frozen or put under an anti-decomposition charm on the moment of their death, and then their bodies could be fixed afterwards. But if the method fundamentally relied on Life Elixir, its use would necessarily have to be extremely limited. Unless they could find a way to stop the "deactivation" of life force on death, whatever that meant?

"I'll take it," he whispered. "Thank you."

Cadmus smiled a strange smile. "You really are genuine in your motivations are you? I believe you. Heavens protect us if I'm wrong, but I trust you."

The specter drew himself up to his full height. "I think you should speak to my brother, Ignotus. If you manage to gain his trust, he will be able to help you far better than I can, both in the form of advice and of spells."

Harry blinked. "Wouldn't the Interdict of Merlin stop that?"

"No," Cadmus smiled. "Because I don't think he's dead."

...

...

"I see I have you both speechless," Cadmus grinned. "Ignotus was old and grieving the last time we spoke. He had lost his eldest daughter, but still had two children remaining to pass our life work onto. Although he believed that we had prioritized incorrectly, he did not go so far as to resent the work we had achieved. He had developed a second cloak, and told me that he would pass it on to his son, while passing my stone to his daughter. The first cloak, he intended to use for himself, to be able to offer advice and spells to continue our research when the other problems in the world are fixed. He urged me not to speak of this carelessly, however, as to be discovered by someone with the wrong incentives would likely mean his death."

"And... he's still alive? After more than a thousand years?"

"I think he must be. He intended to use a spell of enchanted sleep that will slow aging, but can only be broken by an outsider. His soul cannot leave until someone either removes the cloak or wakes him so he can do it himself. His body will likely have stopped functioning, however – you will need to bring Elixir of Life to restore him, unless you're prepared to sacrifice some of your own life force."

"Elixir should not be a problem for this," Dumbledore muttered, a spark of life in his eyes quite unlike his usual twinkle.

"How do I find him?" Harry's heart was beating rapidly. It might be mercenary, but his mind had instantly jumped to the implications. If Ignotus Peverell proved cooperative, he wouldn't just be able to develop some form of magic to resurrect the Hogwarts children; there was so much more potential. The Peverells had lived centuries before Hogwarts, and had been extremely powerful. Likely, Ignotus Peverell could teach him more than even Slytherin's monster could have.

"He said that he would make a grave, alongside mine and Antioch's. That grave is empty. Speak your vow against death there, and when the grave lights up, draw a circle with your wand around the motto. Then, you shall learn. That is all I know."

"Thank you."

"Good luck, young brother."

Chapter 116: The Man Who Lived

Sunday 14 July, 1pm local time. Not that time had much of a meaning here.

Harry looked down at the almost-nondescript piece of ocean floor he was standing on. It was only half a kilometer deep here, so you could survive with only the minor kinds of spells that could be learned from books. As long as you knew the location where Ignotus Peverell was hidden, you would be able to get there, even if all the powerful magic in the world had been lost.

He had gone to the grave and done as Cadmus had told him to. There had been a burst of magic and he had fallen unconscious, and when a severely dismayed Dumbledore had finally managed to wake him up, he had crystal-clear memories of a set of instructions, including pointers to a location. Dumbledore had half-heartedly suggested sending someone else in first, but Harry had not been willing to allow another to go in his stead, sensible though it might be. For all the possible risks, this was his destiny, his family, and even his father had been more eager than concerned when he finally returned from Australia and Harry told him what he was up to.

Then, while a trustworthy witch historian set out to deciphering and confirming the location (the reference points had changed a lot since the time of the Peverell brothers, and to find an exact spot in thousands of square meters of random ocean floor was decidedly non-trivial), Harry had spent his free time with a Muggle Medievalist, studying Old English to hopefully be proficient enough to hold a conversation. The historian had also developed a translation spell for him, but there was always a little delay in the translation and a small risk of inaccuracy; more importantly, since it might not be polite to cast the spell on Ignotus Peverell, Harry really wanted to be able to say his own parts directly in Old English.

And now, here they were. Harry was excited and a little nervous, but he wasn't really afraid of what he would meet. Albus Dumbledore stood beside him, the phoenix on his shoulder, looking very strange with a large bubble around its head. Beside him, Hermione with Xare and Dad were looking around with curious expressions and, in Dad's case, gleaming eyes. Neither they nor the phoenixes could accompany him – only one person was permitted entry at a time, and animals, even magical ones, were not – but they had wanted to be there all the same. Hermione and Dad would go back home if he didn't return or contact them in an hour; Professor Dumbledore would wait for days in case his help might be needed.

Hermione and Dad both gave him a hug, while the old wizard just looked ahead. "Good luck, Mr. Potter. We shall await your return here."

Harry stepped forward, to the exact spot where a tiny crack could be seen in the floor. This was the place which the vision from the grave had shown him.

"Alacrillgo Miakueep."

The floor shuddered, and a field of something surrounded him. And then the floor disappeared, or he himself disappeared, and he was lifted down, into the ground, and everything went dark and bright and all colors at once, until suddenly the movement stopped and he found himself standing on the floor of an ancient chamber.

Harry drew in a sharp breath as he stepped off the dais where he had appeared, and looked around. He was in a large stone room. The air was clear, air-freshening charms apparently still active. There was light, although it had no obvious source. The stones felt warm beneath his feet, and there was no dust anywhere. This room had withstood the centuries unharmed.

And alongside all the walls were shelves upon shelves of books and scrolls. There must be thousands here, untouched by the hands of time. Professor Michael Verres-Evans would have felt right at home, and Harry felt a twinge of regret that his father was out there, just outside the entrance, and unable to see this.

Harry didn't touch the books. There was history here, he knew, and a tremendous amount of knowledge, but he would have time to look at that later. First, he must do what he came for.

In the very center of the room stood a large pillar, made from some unidentifiable transparent material. It reached up to the domed ceiling overhead. Harry approached it. This, he suspected, was the final resting place of his ancestor.

"Cloak," he whispered, reaching into his pouch, and drew forth the Cloak of Invisibility. One of the Cloaks of Invisibility. He threw it around his shoulders, and willed himself to see what was hidden behind all such cloaks.

And there, inside the pillar, stood a stone bench. A figure was stretched out upon it, asleep or dead, while a transparent cloak covered the whole.

The man on the bench looked very, very old. Older than anyone had any right to be. He was bald, spotted, and his skin looked so dry as to be almost mummified. His hands were crossed over his chest, a wand still held in his right hand, which was marked with spots and cuts and had bone sticking out of it.

Harry carefully reached out a hand to touch the pillar. It felt... weird. Not glass, nor any substance he recognized. It was more like a wall of force, separating the outer room from the tiny chamber that hid the living body of Ignotus Peverell.

Twelve hundred years old. Of course, Peverell had been asleep for most of that time. Not physically dead and kept under preservation charms, as Harry had expected at first; there were no anti-decomposition charms powerful enough to stop degeneration for centuries. So the enchanted sleep Ignotus Peverell had placed himself under more than a thousand years ago actually kept his essential functions active – just very, very slow. In a sleep like that, he could last for two or three millenniums before his life finally ran out completely and his body would start to fall apart.

Harry cleared his throat.

"Ignotus Peverell," he spoke loudly, his voice echoing hollowly all through the room.

From the ground beside him, a golden pillar rose up, on top of which stood a marble bowl, a gleaming sharp pin in its center.

The magic might have kept Peverell's body functioning on a base level, but after a thousand years he could not have enough life left to be conscious, let alone speak. This – or so Cadmus had explained, after Harry had watched the vision on the grave and asked him for clarification – was why he had supplied a way for visitors to help him. A sacrificial ritual, which would take the visitor's own life force and pass it to Ignotus. The ritual was costly, requiring the sacrifice of far more life than the recipient would obtain; the visitor would have to spill half a liter of their blood into the bowl and sacrifice ten years of their life just to provide Ignotus with enough strength to speak.

Fortunately, Harry had other options. He held his hand over the pouch. "Bottle of Elixir." Flamel had been very interested in this development, and had gladly supplied the necessary amounts of Life Elixir. Harry carefully tipped the contents of the bottle into the bowl. This would be the moment of truth. Would his great-great-and-some-more-great-grandfather still be alive?

At first, nothing happened. But then the figure started to glow. Harry sat down on the ground, waiting, until finally the eyelids slowly opened.

"Who are you?" The whisper came out like a sigh in the wind. The man's lips had hardly even moved.

"My name is Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres." Almost without thought, Harry's voice fell into a reverend tone. The surroundings just seemed to require it. "I have been told that I am a direct descendant from you."

Immensely slowly, the ancient head turned to look at the boy.

"You are very young."

"I am. But I have done much, for my age."

"What is the year?"

"1992 in the Christian calendar."

"So long... Tell me, Harry with the long name. Has our family completed its sworn mission at last?"

The voice was so brittle, so dusty, that it made Harry wince to hear the old man speak more than a few syllables at once.

"No," he confessed. "Our family... has forgotten its quest." Had someone in the line, like Harry's father, died too young, before he could tell his children? Passed on the cloak and all other possessions as inheritance, but not the meaning behind it? "I do not know when or how. I never knew my own father; he was killed when I was a baby. But for what I was told, he did not know what our family's motto meant anymore. I fear... I suspect the knowledge was lost early on. Someone died, and didn't pass it on –"

The man of tissue paper let out a deep sigh. It could have been his final breath, if he had not still been lying beneath the cloak, unable to die until he removed it. Would he even have the strength to do so if he wished it?

"And so Death wins at last," the ancient wizard breathed. "By taking those who would fight Him first. They were right, then, those who called us fools, when we wasted our lives trying to achieve the impossible."

"No!" Harry exclaimed. "You were not fools, and Death has not won." He stepped closer to the pillar, willing the man to believe him. There had been pain and resignation in the voice, and he couldn't bear the idea of the ancient wizard giving up after so long. "While there is life, there is hope. I might be your last descendant, but I am still here, and I am still going to fight. I've sworn months ago that I will never cower in fear of Death, long before I even learned of my ancestry, and I'll swear it again."

Some muscles moved in the ancient face. It was hard to tell, but Harry thought that the man might be smiling.

"Time leaves strange echoes," the papery voice whispered. "How did you find me?"

"I... inherited the resurrection stone. Cadmus told me about you."

"And so you came here. To seek immortality."

"Not just for myself! I want to stop everyone from dying. And bring back those who have died in the past, as well. I have some issues with this whole death thing, and thinks it's beyond time to fix it."

"And what have you done about it?"

It was only a soft, almost inaudible whisper. Harry didn't know whether it was a challenge, or a simple question that Ignotus just assumed he would have an answer on. Had children, or maybe even adults, in the Peverells' time, not been allowed to approach their superiors unless they had proven themselves first? Or did he assume that his brother would not have told Harry where to find him if he hadn't had any achievements to his name?

It didn't matter; Harry, fortunately, did have a pretty good answer to that one.

"I have invented a spell to destroy Dementors. Together with my friends, I have wiped every single Dementor off the face of the earth."

"A good start." The man was silent for a few moments. "How?"

"I could show you... Can you bear more light in here?"

Without a word, the force field darkened. "Yes."

"Expecto Patronum."

The blazing humanoid appeared. Even behind the almost-dark field, Ignotus Peverell must see the shape.

"I developed this spell, by casting the normal Patronus Charm using my absolute rejection of Death as the basis. I did not realize that it was a new spell at the time, but when I did, I taught others. It projects a solid field of life force, which Dementors cannot see behind, and which can destroy them, given enough strength." He lowered his wand, and the figure disappeared. It would be easier for the old man, this way. "I later found that it can also block the killing curse."

"If it can do that, it might well do more," the voice of Peverell spoke, as the force field became transparent again. "This opens many questions. Ah." He paused, breathing deeply what might have been a sigh. "How I wish I were younger. I do not have the energy to research, not anymore. The mind is eager, but the body..."

"But I do have that energy. I am willing to dedicate my life to research." The man's eyes moved over his face, but he did not respond. "Just tell me what to try and I will do it, as long as it's safe. Or teach me what you knew, and I will try to finish your research. A cure for old age might not be beyond reach."

"A tempting bribe." There was a strange repetitive breathing, which might have been an attempt at a chuckle. "So you wish to learn all that I have spent my life discovering?"

"Of course! I mean, I'm going to work on it anyway. I will start over from the beginning if I must, but if I can start where you and your brothers left off, that would save a lot of trouble."

"Look into my eyes."

Harry obeyed, and then a different mind pushed into his own with an unstoppable force. He tried to call up his Occlumency barriers, even just pretending to be a rock, but it was useless, the mind cut right through him. He tried to turn his eyes away, but he had no control anymore, he couldn't move, couldn't even cry out, there were images running through his head, but he couldn't understand them, he was struggling, and failing, and even despite the cloak he thought he might be dying –

And then it was over. Harry fell over backwards and lay there for long minutes, trembling. The mind had gone from him, but the terror was still there.

"I apologize," the thin voice breathed at last. "I had to know whether you were sincere."

Of course. Just because he is twelve hundred years old and dead except for the dying part doesn't mean that he has lost any of his powers. He probably lost some to old age, but he lived about three hundred years before Salazar Slytherin. Even if his magic has faded – and supposedly Flamel's magic never fell below fifth-year levels, so the same can be assumed for Peverell – he would still be extremely powerful for all the forgotten knowledge he has, probably more powerful than Riddle. It occurred to Harry that he was completely at the mercy of the ancient wizard who was lying there, whom he didn't know and had no reason to trust, other than that the man's long-dead brother had said it would be a good idea.

"You looked into my mind?" Harry scrabbled up to his feet, but stayed well away from the force wall now.

"Yes. I might cheat Merlin's Interdict, but I will not risk destroying the world." There was a pause, as the skeletal figure drew a raspy breath. "The knowledge you ask for would be very dangerous in the wrong hands. I had to understand what kind of person you are."

"Did you... see everything?" Harry felt violated. Even if the man would never stir from this place, he had no right to see Harry's thoughts, let alone the things he'd done in private. Even if Harry would have told him everything he'd asked for, that should have been his choice.

""A fair bit. I could not see everything; you are too young to bear my possession for long. But I think I saw the important parts, even if I did not understand it all."

"Possession?"

"One of Antioch's discoveries. I destroyed his notes. That one is far too dangerous to pass on."

"If you can kill someone just by looking at them, I can see why."

"Hardly." Again the strange breathing that might indicate a laugh. "That was common, in my day. Possession is dangerous because it is useful. I could have left my body for yours, if I was willing to let you die. It would drain your body, but that would take long enough. Immortality, in exchange for one wizard death every twenty years or so."

"Ah." Harry swallowed. That had been too close.

Peverell closed his eyes. "Ssssh. Let me analyze your memories."

Harry shifted awkwardly, and sat back down on the ground. Truth be told, he was still shaky, and didn't mind some rest either.

Time passed. Harry allowed the post-possession lethargy to take him, closing his eyes and just controlling his breathing for long minutes; five, ten, twenty.

"We have fallen so far," the ancient man eventually spoke. "I wonder what Merlin would say."

"Wizardry has lost much," Harry felt the need to point out. "But Muggles have grown. They have research of their own now, and thinking machines, and they have traveled into the heavens."

"Yes." There was silence for a moment. Then – "And wizardry we can fix."

We. "Does this mean you will help?"

"Some." He paused briefly before adding: "Death is not the only enemy."

"I know," Harry conceded. "But it's the greatest."

"Perhaps," Ignotus whispered. "The world is malleable now, more than ever before. And you wield influence. There is... opportunity."

"True," Harry nodded uncomfortably.

The papery man closed his eyes again, silently thinking. Harry didn't say anything, just waited, not sure what to hope for. It sounded like the man was prioritizing the other problems in the world, as his brother had said he would. Not that that was necessarily wrong, per se, but it wasn't what Harry had come for, and he also wasn't so sure that he wanted to follow the guidance of a ninth-century wizard on the matter of how to fix the world. But if his help meant restoring ancient magic like the healing spells that could save the Longbottoms...

The silence stretched, until Harry started wondering whether the old wizard had fallen asleep again.

"A lot of my friends died recently," he brought up. "We preserved the bodies. Cadmus said that you might be able to help?"

The ancient eyes slowly opened again.

"I might." Another silence, then: "But you do not need my help."

"I don't," Harry conceded. He was pretty sure he already had most of the necessary ingredients. The bodies could, for the most part, be healed with normal magic and perhaps some Muggle methods; a few drops of Elixir of Life could restore the life force pool while the True Patronus Charm and phoenix tears could fill it; the soul could be returned using the resurrection stone and forced to remain inside the body using the cloak. All they needed was some kind of spell to bind the soul and body together for long enough that the Elixir of Life would have something to latch on to, or alternatively, to restore the body to a "Demented" like state which the soul could easily be returned to. With the help of Dumbledore, Flamel and some of the master healers who had already expressed an interest in the project, they should be able to develop such spells before long. The only problem was the fine-tuning and experimenting. Any mistakes with soul magic might lead to a damaged soul which they had no knowledge to restore, and they could not afford to waste too much Elixir of Life. "But with your experience it would be a lot easier."

"Hmmm."

Easier, Slytherin said contemptuously. That sounded like you just woke up an ancient wizard from a thousand-year sleep to solve your problems for you a tiny bit faster than you could do it yourself.

"I didn't mean it like that!" Harry quickly blurted out. "I didn't just wake you up to save myself some time, but –"

"I know," Peverell breathed. "I have seen your intentions. I do not mind helping. But remember that my help is not free. I cannot function without Elixir of Life."

That was a good point, Harry realized. If, as Cadmus had hypothesized, "reactivating" the life force in someone who had been preserved right after death would take no more than a few drops of Elixir, then every day he kept Ignotus functional might amount to another life he could have saved instead. It was a sobering thought. There was a deadline on saving the Hogwarts children and professors and Mum; if he took too long their bodies would be damaged despite the preservation charms. But wouldn't there always be people dying, important to others even if they were less close to him?

Harry swallowed. He hadn't at all considered that trying to mitigate the war's losses in this way might be the selfish choice.

"I guess... I guess you must spend your time on whatever is most needed." He blinked away the moisture that was threatening to gather in his eyes. No matter what they decided to focus on, the souls of the dead were safe, they could be resurrected in whatever distant future humanity would have the means to do so. "Like teaching people your healing knowledge – Cadmus said that it used to be possible to restore people who were tortured into insanity, and it would be really, really good to get that back. But I did mean what I said: I want to work on the death problem, and I would really prefer to continue where you left off over trying to start from scratch." Standing on the shoulders of giants, as his father liked to say. Very few scientific breakthroughs happened in isolation, and understanding what the Peverells had done would be a key starting point. "I want to learn all that you learned, so I can spend my life doing something better – doing the things you never got around to, I mean. But... maybe a good place to start learning would be to look into resurrection of people with preserved bodies?"

"Hmmm. You may be right about that."

He took a deep, rasping breath.

"It will take time, to understand your memories. Months, likely. And what I took is not complete." There was another pause, then a whisper too soft for Harry to hear, and suddenly the platform Harry had arrived on moved up.

"I have enough magic left for one possession. Call in your teacher, who is waiting outside. I have opened the room for him and his phoenix. I will read him, and pass him the spells he needs to rebuild your school. He should be able to bear my touch long enough. Then, I propose that you go from this place, and study. If your teacher arranges sustenance, I shall return my body to sleep – but not my mind. That should allow me to contemplate the changes in the world, what knowledge can be shared, and what must not."

The brittle old man coughed, at the end of this long monologue, his entire body shaking. Some flecks of blood fell from his mouth, but with just a tiny twitch of the wand they disappeared again.

"Will you be all right?" Harry asked, concerned. It would be a great loss for the world, not to mention rather embarrassing, if the man had lived for twelve hundred years and then died within an hour of Harry coming near him.

"I should last some more centuries, before my voice gives out," the man whispered. "If you supply enough food and water, I may be conscious – if inactive – for three months without harm, even if you do not return with further sustenance."

"Oh, I will definitely come back."

"Good," the voice breathed again.

To Harry's left, a part of the wall loaded with books and scrolls lit up in a golden light.

"Take these," rasped Peverell. "The books discuss the ideas of soul magic. The scrolls are my own notes. You will study them, and design spells and experiments for your mission of resurrection. When you return, we will speak of it."

The living skeleton paused for a while, breathing deeply as though gathering the strength to speak again. A smaller section to Harry's right lit up in red, and a scattering of books and scrolls all around the walls became a bright, shining blue.

"The red works are for your teacher – I will pass him the spells he needs, but have not the strength for instruction, which the books will supply. The blue ones are for your friend, if she wishes it; the girl with the phoenix."

"She definitely won't mind," Harry blurted out. Hermione would be dying to get her hands on the books in this room. There was no doubt she'd go through everything Harry was allowed to take from here, and she'd probably have memorized the books on soul magic before he'd even read them once. "What are they?"

"History, culture, philosophy – useful, no matter what she chooses. Ask her to come with you, when you return. I will speak to her then. And bring a reliable Healer, who can be trusted with forgotten spells."

Harry nodded, a sudden lump in his throat. Teaching a Healer some forgotten spells didn't definitely mean that he might be able to give Neville his parents back, but there was hope, more than ever before. "I'm sure such a person can be found."

"Now call your teacher, my apprentice. There is much to do."

Apprentice. Yes, that was exactly what he'd asked for, wasn't it?

He took the mirror from his pocket to contact Dumbledore. "So... does that mean you're going to teach me all you've learned about death?" It sounded like it, but the man hadn't actually said so...

Harry wasn't sure, but he thought the expression on the papery face might be another attempt at a tired smile. "I will." His eyes turned serious, his gaze piercing. "And in return, will you give me life again?"

Harry stared back, unafraid. "I will."

-o-o-o-o-o-

Author's Note: And that's where the story ends! Thank you all for reading, and for your feedback. :) Your responses have helped to make the experience of writing and online-publishing a story thoroughly exciting, even if occasionally terrifying.

This story is now marked as complete, as it's reached the end of the main story. However, there will be an additional "epilogue" chapter with flashes from the future at some point, probably in 2015.

This story was fully written before the final arc of HPMoR, and has been known to sometimes confuse people as to what was canon and what wasn't. That is why, originally, I posted a short recap of the important things which weren't known at chapter 81 and which, therefore, i completely made up. With HPMoR complete, this probably isn't an issue anymore, but in case people are going for a reread "with full knowledge", or are otherwise curious for the recap if only for historical reasons, I've left it. In HPMoR:

* there is no such thing as life force

* we don't know whether there is such a thing as the soul (and if there is, it probably doesn't work that way)

* the philosopher's stone doesn't work that way

* the resurrection stone probably doesn't work that way

* horcruxes (probably) don't work that way

* powerful spells do not work that way (that is, it's entirely possible that powerful spells do in fact require a lot of power, and that the TPC doesn't count)

* the events in Godric's Hollows, Quirrell's and Dumbledore's motivations, the reason the last war lasted so long and certain people's secret identities are not (all) the same

* Hermione didn't go to Azkaban, didn't get Xare, and might have ended up... quite differently from being a basically normal teenage witch with a phoenix

* nobody but Harry has learned how to cast the TPC

Chapter 117: Epilogue

Author's Note: I had initially intended for this epilogue to be a series of short flashes, showing the months and years after Harry meets Ignotus. However, this turned out to be a bit too long, with 17k and going before I even reached the end of 1992, so instead I'll be posting those flashes as a separate story – for that, see "Following the Phoenix - Flashes" in My Stories under my pen name. Instead, I hope you enjoy this alternative epilogue!

Also note, for those who haven't seen it yet: there is a fanfiction of Following the Phoenix now. Yes, that's right: a fanfiction of a fanfiction of a fanfiction! It's not entirely consistent with the Epilogue, but that's only fair because it was posted months earlier! Look for EagleJarl's "Squiring the Phoenix", or just go straight to /s/11107471

Darkness...Drifting... Pain. The warmth of the sun on his face and a distant rustling – waves?

Consciousness returned slowly, like a gentle awakening after a long, long sleep. There was dizziness, along with a slight headache, but otherwise he felt quite comfortable. Except... there was something. Something important had happened... although he couldn't quite recall what, exactly...

Tom Riddle opened his eyes to a yellow-green sky.

Carefully, he sat up and looked around, taking in the area. He was on a beach of some kind, but it looked... well, alien. The sand was black, the water was far bluer than it had any right to be, and in the distance there were some red-brownish shapes that might be trees, but not any that he recognized. To his left stood a large gleaming building. This was not any place he had ever been before; of that, he was certain.

His reflection in the building, distorted though it was, showed a face he did remember: his own, but much younger than the last time he had seen it. He inspected his hands, his body. He was dressed in some outlandish clothing; long, wide trousers and a vest, but not a style he'd ever seen Muggles wear. His hands were well-formed and his flesh healthy, unmarred by the many disfigurements his magical experiments had given him later in life. The body felt natural, without the touch of glamors or the strain of a possessed body. And yet... something still felt just a little off...

"Hello Professor Riddle."

He almost jumped to his feet as his head snapped towards the source of the sound. On pure reflex he grabbed for his wand holster, but it wasn't there, so he stepped sideways, taking in a more tactical position and readying himself for combat. Only then did he register who had just appeared.

Before him, a short distance away from the building, stood a strong-looking man, not visibly holding a wand. A man seemingly in his twenties, with messy black hair and deep green eyes. A man whom, had he been a boy, Tom would have known.

"Harry Potter," he observed, as memories came flooding back to him. His plans, the war. The Dementor. He knew now, what must have happened. "You brought me back?"

"I promised I would," the young man said simply. "Although you might not remember that."

Tom narrowed his eyes at him. He did have some memories that must have happened after his death, or flashes of them. There had been conversations, primarily with the man before him. Most of it was a blur, but he remembered... feelings. The boy must have used the Resurrection Stone more than once on him. The Resurrection Stone which Tom had left him, as a final precaution in the event of his defeat, minuscule though the chance of needing it had seemed at the time, and near-negligible the chance that it would actually help.

If he had made me no promises, then I would never have consented to help him with any of his goals. And I'm sure I did help, at least sometimes.

"Perhaps I do."

Potter just nodded. "How are you feeling? Any pain?"

"A light headache and some dizziness," he admitted. There did not seem to be much reason to hide it, and right now, cooperation was likely to be a good idea. The boy, his killer, would not have done this if he did not have some kind of power over him, and he was no longer the gullible eleven-year-old he had once been.

Potter nodded again, as to himself. "That's a common problem. It usually passes in a few hours, though."

Usually. So he wasn't the first. Of course he wasn't.

"How long has it been, exactly?"

"Today it is nine hundred and twenty-three years, five months and seventeen days after you died."

Nine centuries. He took a deep breath, enjoying the feeling of air in his mouth. There would be a lot to learn. "And what is this place? We are not on earth, are we?"

"No, we're not. This is Meretseger Penal Colony."

The curiosity shattered as his blood temperature dropped to freezing point. "Penal colony?"

"Well yes. What exactly were you expecting? You killed and tortured quite a few people, that's not something I would ever have allowed you to get away with."

"So you brought me back just to punish me?" Oh, Potter would hurt. He didn't know quite how he would do it yet, but there would be a way. There was always a way.

"No," the man before him spoke with a sincere tone. "We brought you back to live. But that doesn't mean that there will be no consequences for past crimes. What is more, you are quite frankly a menace to society, and you will have to learn a different way of thinking. This place will help you adjust."

For this audacity you will suffer for years before I allow you to die. He clamped down on the impulse to lash out at the man. There was nothing to be gained by showing his anger.

"Such noble goals," he stated coldly, although retaining his outward calm. "You truly expect me to believe that your intentions towards me are benevolent?"

"No," Harry Potter shrugged. "I don't expect you to believe that. Not yet. Too much has happened between us for you to really think of me as a friend, and I don't think you ever understood friendship in the first place. But perhaps in time, you will."

His anger flared. It would be foolish to try killing Potter without understanding the full situation, but something had to die. He focused on a nearby stone, and started gathering his magic to –

Oh no. No no no no no.

Potter just stood there, a sad expression on his face as Tom reeled back in shock. "Were you planning to hurt me?"

"No," he ground out, as some of the anger drained from his blood and was replaced by sheer terror. "You took my magic?"

"The Dementor did," Harry answered. "But you were resurrected as a non-magical, yes. It's not as bad as you might think."

"Not as bad? Help me adjust? How could you resurrect me like this?!"

"You no longer need to fear death," Potter answered bluntly. "Nor torture, hunger or excessive misery, unless you break the most fundamental laws of the interstellar government. You will not be surrounded by idiots if you do not choose to be. Indeed, there will be ample chance for intelligent conversation, with greater minds than yourself if you so choose and they are willing to entertain you. You will have the opportunity to study and apply yourself to any field of your choice. Is this not what you desired?"

"No! I never desired to be a Muggle! Damn you, Potter, my magic is part of who I am!"

"It was part of who you were. Now, you will have to learn to live without it." The voice was firm, accepting no arguments, but then turned more gentle. "For now. You can get a new body, with magic, if you can afford to pay for an additional resurrection or are wiling to perform community duties using that magic. But not until you are released."

Ah. Stick and carrot. How elegant. Slowly, the red-hot rage retreated, leaving only crystal-cold clarity in its wake. The situation was agonizingly clear. Potter and his associates – whoever they were – were dominant, and they were intent on teaching him whatever lessons they had in store. The only sensible course of action was to take the slap, follow their little plans, and allow them to see what they desired to see. There was a bitter taste in his mouth; he had hoped never to have to do this again. But he could do it; for now, he would pretend to lose. His revenge would be all the sweeter for it later.

"Very well," he finally bit. "What are the terms of my incarceration?"

Harry looked at the face of his ancient friend/enemy as the seething anger dissipated, to be replaced by cold calculation. He could see it, the moment Tom Riddle decided to pretend to lose. He had known many such moments himself, over the course of his long life, more than enough to recognize the pattern of thinking in the one who first taught him to do so. Except that Harry had learned the original lesson Riddle's Sensei had tried to instill. He knew that he was imperfect, and that not every battle could be won; when the situation called for it, he could lose without planning a come-back. Riddle, Harry was sure – and Kahimari-Sensei agreed with him – never had learned that lesson.

He had no illusions: Voldemort was unquestionably evil. He would not lightly forgive Harry for the humiliation of being imprisoned like a common criminal. But there would be time. Voldemort would be imprisoned – and following an advanced social reformation course – for almost as long as he had lived in freedom, and in time he would almost certainly come to see that more could be gained by playing within the system than by trying to overpower it. Harry's Dark Side had mellowed; been turned to good. Its originator could do the same.

"Very well," Tom Riddle spoke at last. "What are the terms of my incarceration?"

Harry took a deep breath. "You will be confined to this island for fifty years –"

"Fifty?"

"Yes, but there will be both company and intellectual stimulation. For the company, you've got me. I'll come over every day in the first few months, then at least a few times a week for as long as you need me, both just for talking and to get you acquainted with the way the world works now."

A flash of anger crossed Riddle's face. "Don't you have anything better to do?"

"Plenty," Harry shrugged. "But I've made the time. Anyway, it's an official function. To avoid isolation, every prisoner has the right to a friend."

"I hardly think you count as a friend, Potter."

If only you knew, Harry thought grimly. What do you think would have happened if I hadn't spoken up on your behalf? Resurrection had been possible for well over five hundred years, and a routine procedure for almost four hundred. For a while, this had been used only for benevolent purposes, as Ignotus and Harry had been able to ensure socially responsible practices. But once their patents had expired, there was nothing they could do besides political pressure to stop the resurrection of history's villains for the purpose of revenge. Harry's influence had stretched just far enough to protect minor dictators and warlords. He had managed to save Voldemort by arguing his goal of preventing the destruction of the world, and illustrating that the man had indeed succeeded in halting the third world war before it began. There had been no way to stop what was done to Hitler, Grindelwald, Pot, Mao, Nero and quite a few others. Harry had waited and lobbied for centuries, until the judicial system had fully transformed to focus on reformation and reintegration, before he had proposed also bringing back the darker personages of times past and giving them a new chance at life.

But you are not ready to hear that yet. You will find out on your own eventually, when you start looking for it. It's all a matter of public record, after all.

He merely shrugged. "I suspect that I am the best friend you have. However, I suppose that since there is somewhat of a history between us –"

"Like you being directly responsible for my death?"

"For example. Or you killing my parents, having my best friend sent to Azkaban and then attempting to murder me."

"It was self-defense."

Harry raised an eyebrow. "Including the parts about my parents and Hermione?"

"In a sense." There was even something resembling a brief smirk there. "And they got better, didn't they?"

"Eventually," Harry conceded. "Although my parents, at least, were not very happy with you for wrecking their lives. But yes, I have forgiven you for my personal grievances." He sighed at Riddle's dismissive look. "Even so, you do have reasonable cause to protest my presence and ask for a replacement. But unless you happen to have someone in mind who is licensed for the function, you will probably be assigned a professional therapist instead."

Riddle's face twitched. "I suppose you'll do."

"Thank you. Now, as for the material details... this island is yours for the term of your sentence. No one else can come here, but on the flip side, neither can you leave it."

"I cannot, or I am not supposed to?"

"Both, I hope. There's nothing on this planet but a bunch of scattered islands, and the water currents are such that even just trying to get to the next one would most likely see you killed. The entire planet combined does not have the resources, mundane or magical, to support leaving it, and it's heavily warded besides."

Tom Riddle frowned. "And, hypothetically, what would happen if I were to die?"

"Depends on how you die. If it happened in a misguided escape attempt, you would most likely be placed on a no-resurrect list. Future generations may choose to ignore that list, or just to use your soul as fuel for some sacrificial ritual. I would advice against finding out."

"I see."

"Anyway," Harry continued, "this island is yours, and contains everything you need to survive – you will need to farm and mend your own clothing, but there are enough supplies to get you through the starting period and several bad winters."

Harry smirked inwardly as Riddle grimaced in distaste. Yes, Professor, you will have to learn to work as Muggles did during the time you grew up. I doubt you're ever going to like it, but it will do you a world of good to actually have to put in a bit of work to live, rather than chasing your ambitions while getting by on your magic.

"Besides that," he continued, "you have a computer – although it does not much resemble the early computers you used to have a passing familiarity with. You shouldn't have a problem handling it, though; plenty of wizards from our time and well before have managed it, even purebloods of well-below-average intelligence. The computer gives you access to a vast library of literature from all the ages and cultures, as well as training programs to learn how to live in the modern world."

"I suppose this is the intellectual stimulation of which you spoke?"

"Part of it. You will also be allowed access to the Internet, in a month or so once you've properly settled in. The Internet is, well... like a huge collection of worlds where the inconvenient rules of physics and magic don't need to apply. You can meet people there, debate politics or anything of your interest, you can access all the unrestricted knowledge of humanity, join scientific projects... A large part of most people's daily life takes place in the virtual universe. That's sort of a necessity, actually, with people living all over the physical universe – it's pretty costly, even with magic, to transport people over interstellar distances, but data is easy, so the people developed ways to simulate all kinds of physical interactions without having to actually leave your room."

Riddle raised an eyebrow. "And you would give me free access to that? This would seem to defeat the entire point of imprisonment."

"Well, social views of what punishment should entail have changed a bit. But you're right, it's not entirely free access; there will be restrictions and places which are closed to you or where you are denied anonymity. Also, most importantly, all your activities will be monitored by Mad-AI."

Riddle frowned. "Mad-AI?"

Harry grinned. "A portrait of Mad-Eye Moody, hooked up to a computer and linked to other portraits for advice. Basically Mad-Eye's personality but thinking a million times faster, which is able to avoid certain reasoning flaws Mad-Eye is prone to. He is aware of everything you do on the Internet – and certain aspects of your presence on the island for that matter."

"Including any communication I may have?" The ice dropped back into the voice.

"Yes," Harry admitted. "I'm afraid people in detention do not have the right to privacy. I am sorry about that, but at least nothing is passed to a human unless there is reason for concern."

Riddle scowled. "Will I at least have mental privacy?"

Spoke the greatest Legilimens of his time. "Mostly. Your mind will not be studied while you are here, but when the time of your release approaches, you will have to undergo strict testing to verify that you are safe to be released in society. That of course includes a complete examination of your mind by a human professional. They will be Obliviated afterwards, but they will point out any potential issues of concern first. And since I know you're wondering: yes, Muggles can practice Occlumency, but no, it won't help you as the use of Occlumency can be detected on a brain scan, which of course you will be exposed to during the examination."

Tom Riddle looked livid. "And what will happen if they find something 'of concern'?"

"That will be judged at the time by more specialized people than me," Harry shrugged. "It isn't really something you need to be worried about right now. There are many options. For example, you could be resurrected into a three-year-old body and Obliviated –"

"No."

"Not even if you get all your memories back on your thirtieth birthday?"

"Absolutely not."

"Well, that won't happen unless you choose it, anyway. It worked very well for Albus, though – becoming a child again was what finally allowed him to heal and forgive himself for his mistakes. Although I suppose being raised alongside his original brother and sister also helped."

"I am not Dumbledore," Riddle hissed. "What happens if I refuse that?"

"I'm not sure, it doesn't come up very often. You might be assigned therapy, or killed until such time as humanity has evolved enough to figure out what to do with you, for example. But there really is no reason to assume that any of this will be needed."

"Truly? Do you so fully believe that you can change me? That I will let you?"

"Honestly, I don't think you need all that much changing – you mostly need to adjust. The world has changed, people have changed. The universe isn't what you used to know, and most of your old beliefs just don't apply anymore. You never truly sought power for yourself, and there are a lot more rational people around these days to achieve whatever goals you set in a constructive way. You have true immortality, once we solve the entropy problem – which, if the theoretical magicians are to be believed, should be doable well before it becomes an issue. And if you need a negative incentive against acting up, law enforcement is a lot more effective and run by some highly intelligent minds these days. Basically, there is absolutely no reason whatsoever why you should be a menace to society once you understand how it works."

"Perhaps," Voldemort shrugged noncommittally. "But forgive me if I am not too enthusiastic about a system which has taken away my magic, freedom, privacy and control over my life, which insists on seeing my inner nature 'adjusted', and yet expects cooperation and gratitude."

"That's not quite –" Harry stopped. There was no point arguing. "It's fine, you have every right to be angry. But if you want a small point of light to look forward to, Salazar Slytherin is quite interested in meeting you. I'd be happy to introduce the two of you when you have Internet next month."

Riddle's eyes widened only slightly. There were a few moments of silence, before he spoke again, in a tone more detached than cold. "You know him, then?"

"Quite well. He is one of my earlier apprentices, and still a good friend. Usually we guide people into their new life by having them taught by someone they used to know in their first one – a grandchild, friend or student, typically – but it takes quite a while to get far down history that way, and Salazar was a bit of a special case due to his example function."

There was a longer silence after that, as Riddle's hostile look turned measuring.

"I'm over nine hundred years old, Professor," Harry said quietly. "I'm a scientist, teacher, politician and business owner. I have lived half a dozen lifetimes, adapting to constant changes in the world all the time. I'm not the child you used to know anymore."

"I can see that."

Harry smiled wanly.

"I think it's time for me to go. I'll be back tomorrow." He hesitated, then glanced upwards. "One more thing you might like to know... I realize the sky here isn't much to look at, but at night, you can see the stars. In winter, it's a near-perfect image."

Riddle froze.

"Whatever else you might feel," he spoke quietly. "There is still beauty in the world. Just... keep an open mind, okay?"

With a last look at the man before him, he canceled the hologram and closed the communication channel. He wasn't on the same planet, of course; he wasn't even in the same star system. Being physically near Riddle would not have been safe. Besides, he was needed where he was, in an intergalactic exploration vessel under Hermione's command, searching for signs of non-earthly life.

Several million light years away, Tom Riddle kept staring at the place where Harry had disappeared for a long time afterwards.

-o-o-o-o-o-

Sometimes, when this flawed world seems unusually hateful, I wonder whether there might be some other place, far away, where I should have been. I cannot seem to imagine what that place might be, and if I can't even imagine it then how can I believe it exists? And yet the universe is so very, very wide, and perhaps it might exist anyway? But the stars are so very, very far away. It would take a long, long time to get there, even if I knew the way. And I wonder what I would dream about, if I slept for a long, long time...

-o-o-o-o-o-

Author's Note: And that, truly, is where this story ends. I thank you all for reading. :)